<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Philanax Anglicus, or, A Christian caveat for all kings, princes &amp; prelates how they entrust a sort of pretended Protestants of integrity, or suffer them to commix with their respective governments : shewing plainly from the principles of all their predecessours, that it is impossible to be at the same time Presbyterians, and not rebells : with a compendious draught of their portraictures and petigree done to the life, by their own doctors dead hands, perfectly delineating their birth, breeding, bloody practices, and prodigious theorems against monarchy / faithfully published by T.B.</title>
            <author>Janson, Henry, Sir, 1616 or 17-ca. 1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 219 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J482</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16845</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12861725</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12861725</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94686</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46673)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94686)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 985:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Philanax Anglicus, or, A Christian caveat for all kings, princes &amp; prelates how they entrust a sort of pretended Protestants of integrity, or suffer them to commix with their respective governments : shewing plainly from the principles of all their predecessours, that it is impossible to be at the same time Presbyterians, and not rebells : with a compendious draught of their portraictures and petigree done to the life, by their own doctors dead hands, perfectly delineating their birth, breeding, bloody practices, and prodigious theorems against monarchy / faithfully published by T.B.</title>
                  <author>Janson, Henry, Sir, 1616 or 17-ca. 1684.</author>
                  <author>Pattenson, Matthew. Image of bothe churches.</author>
                  <author>T. B. (Thomas Bellamy)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[50], 123 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Theo. Sadler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First published anonymously before 1663 and taken mainly from Image of bothe churches, Hierusalem and Babel, by Matthew Pattenson; the present edition (subscribed "Thomas Bellamy") corrected and enlarged by Henry Janson.  Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Sir Henry Janson. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Musuem.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestantism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94686:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Philanax Anglicus:</hi> OR A CHRISTIAN CAVEAT FOR ALL <hi>Kings, Princes</hi> &amp; <hi>Prelates,</hi> How they entruſt a ſort of Pretended <hi>Proteſtants of Integrity,</hi> or ſuffer them to commix with their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Governments. Shewing plainly from the Principles of all their Predeceſſours, that it is impoſſible to be at the ſame time <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and not <hi>Rebells. WITH A</hi> Compendious Draught of their Portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures and Petigree done to the life, by their own Doctors dead hands, perfectly delinea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their Birth, Breeding, bloody Practices, and prodigious Theorems againſt Monarchy.</p>
            <p>Faithfully Publiſhed by <hi>T. B.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Tunc male res agitur, cum ad guſtum populi Principatus exigitur.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Caſſiod.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Qui ſtat, videat ne cadat,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 10 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Theo: Sadler,</hi> next door to the Dolphin, againſt <hi>Exeter</hi> houſe in the Strand, 1663</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:94686:2"/>
            <figure>
               <head>T. Jolley <abbr>Esq</abbr> F. L. A.</head>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:94686:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:94686:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94686:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Gilbert</hi> Lord-Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and Dean of his Majeſties Chappel Royal.</head>
            <p>AFter a tedious. Contraſte with my ſelf, whoſe Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage I might moſt properly implore, to protect this fatherleſs piece; I muſt needs confeſs that your Lordſhip was the firſt and laſt of my thoughts; and I hope good reaſon will vindicate me in that bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe your Lordſhip is by Divine Providence, choſen to be the Dioceſan of this great City, where ſo much miſchief and villany has been of late (and we ſtill may juſtly fear is) concentred: and your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is ſo far concerned in the care of
<pb facs="tcp:94686:4"/>thoſe ſouls, that it may be hate yours, that thoſe whom you cannot bring into your Fold, by your ſweet Paternal-Call, may be drawn to it by the power of your Paſtoral-ſtaff, or abandoned to the mercy of their own beloved Wolves in Sheeps-cloathing.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe your Lordſhip is honoured to be ſo neer his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Royal Ear, and is, as to all Church matters, his chief <hi>Intellectus Agens;</hi> ſo your Lordſhip is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned again, to inform his Majeſty of the Civil dangers, that are like to proceed from ſuch religious Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers. For this ſect here treated of, are of the very race of the <hi>Hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanii</hi> that ingenuous <hi>Barclay</hi> ſpeaks ſo largely of in his <hi>Argenis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bar. Arg. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 92.93.94.</note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from the ſame Father <hi>Uſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulca,</hi> and are truly (as he is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſay) a ſort of people, who as certain creatures are nouriſhed with poyſon, ſo they grow ſtrong
<pb facs="tcp:94686:4"/>in publick calamities, and are only fatted with War and ſlaughter. The firſt Children of the Church, bore neither rod nor ſtick to plant faith in the hearts of men; but theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of Integrity (as they call themſelves) have publiſhed a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to the world, all briſtled with Swords, all ſooted over with the ſmoak of Canon, all beſprinckled with the blood of Chriſtians. <note place="margin">Senec. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> Now in ſuch a caſe the Philoſopher ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth all States-men, <hi>Quicquid fieri poteſt, quaſi futurum cogitare,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that all things may, which can come to paſs: and though the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Modern Statiſts has been ſeen a little in ſome neat and cleanly evaſions, fine deliveryes, and ſhiftings of dangers when they are neer, yet the moſt approveable part of pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence will be ſeen, as it has alwayes been your Lordſhips courſe, in ſolid and well-grounded preventions of them before they fall, and to keep
<pb facs="tcp:94686:5"/>them aloof: and therefore <hi>Joſephus</hi> that learned Jew moſt judiciouſly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſeth likewiſe, that <hi>Bonum eſt dum adhuc ſtat Navis in portu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſeph. de Billo Jud. l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>praecavere tempeſtatem futuram, &amp; non eo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore, quo in medias irrueris procel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, trepidare;</hi> It is neceſſary for him that goes to Sea, to foreſee a Storm coming, if he can, and not to ruſh into the fury of the Seas, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the tempeſt afterwards; that will avail little, but to be rendred ridiculous for raſhneſs.</p>
            <p>Your Lordſhip very well knows that this kind of Caterpillers when they have once taken head, will not eaſily be taken off: and it is as true as old, <hi>Turpius ejicitur, quàm non ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur.</hi> They are of the nature of thoſe birds, whoſe feathers are ſo imperious, that they will not quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mix with the plumage of others; if they do, they then conſume them as with a dull file: Nor are they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like that unſociable Tree, which the
<pb facs="tcp:94686:5"/>wiſe Secretaries of Nature have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the name of <hi>Iff,</hi> that inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly draws the juice of all plants to it. But I need not enlarge more concerning the danger of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into power; for there is none that has converſt with them, but knows, that the Sea it ſelf is leſs fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, a Thunder-clap leſs dreadfull; nay the gall of Dragons, and poyſon that ſwelleth up the necks of Aſps, is much more tolerable.</p>
            <p>My Lord, all this that I have ſaid, is not to inform or adviſe your Lordſhip, whoſe knowledg is ſuper-excellent in all things; but to juſtifie to the world, the oeconomy of your Prelatical Proceedings: For under whoſe wing ſoever this Cockatrice Egg gets life, it will repay it with a death, and ſting to the heart of him whoſe boſome hatch'd it, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnaring him in his own goodneſs. Theſe Cockatrice Chriſtians doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs intend nothing more (for they
<pb facs="tcp:94686:6"/>are not afraid to ſpeak it) than to play their old game over again, and rebel again againſt this moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and Clement King, and the Church, and will grow every day more and more inſolent upon his Majeſties, and your Lordſhips pious mildneſs and gentleneſs: For we have ſeen ſufficiently, that how great vertue ſoever may be in a Prince, or Prelate, it will be all contemned by them, if there be not ſeaſonably ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded an opinion of their juſtice and ſeverity: For no Perſons in power are better beloved of the people, than they that ſhew in time, that they have in themſelves matter worthy of fear. They muſt be made I ſay to know, ere tis too late, that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Prelates, are like the Crowns of the Kings of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which carry Aſpicks upon the top of them, that inſenſibly ſting thoſe who too neer approach with intention to offend them: and by this means your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb facs="tcp:94686:6"/>ſhall prove to the world, that you have not ſpent ſo much time in your former divine ſolitudes, and the ſweet delights of your ſtudyes, to gather ſo much honey, but that you yet retain the vigour of a ſting; which caſts me naturally upon the third and greateſt reaſon of my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent preſumption: Which is, that I have had the honour long to know your Lordſhip, (though the Authour of this piece now departed much longer and better) when you were a principal Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour amongſt us, in that moſt famous Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Seminary of ſo many great Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that have held predominance in all manner of learning and ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Warden of <hi>Allſouls</hi>-Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: which hath always been a moſt principal part in that <hi>Pantheon,</hi> and like the Altar of the Sun, from whence light has been borrowed to illuminate all other Lamps. I have
<pb facs="tcp:94686:7"/>been long knowing (I ſay) to your moſt incomparable piety and parts; and indeed what is fitter then that that Soul ſhould be full of light and flames, that is to ſerve others, for ſo great a guide? for by your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips great reading of men as well as books, there are become incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in your ſole perſon, the vertues and faculties of thouſands others. Your fair ſoul ever appeared to be (like the <hi>Ibis,</hi> that precious bird of <hi>Perſia</hi> that builds her neſt alwayes in <hi>Palmes</hi>) perpetually converſant in great contemplations, and had no more impreſſions of earth, than the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Sphere of Celeſtial Bodies. As nothing was too high for your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſo nothing was too low for your bounty &amp; beneficence. <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>104.</hi> Ep. ad Heb.</note> God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty has beſtowed upon you the gift which the Scripture attributes to the Patriarch <hi>Joſeph,</hi> to oblige hearts by ſweetneſs; not unlike the Engins of <hi>Archimedes,</hi> which made
<pb facs="tcp:94686:7"/>water mount in deſcending; ſo your Lordſhip ever cauſed your humility to deſcend, but ſtill to make it rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to the ſourſe of the prime ſublimity; and your vertues upon earth, will make your Crowns in Heaven. Your Lordſhip has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes communicated your ſelf with ſo much ſweetneſs, facility and affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, that you encreaſed alwayes reſpect by familiarity, which uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſſolves it; and like a precious Amethyſt, ſhined ſo much the more, as it hath been often worn. It has been only the miſchief and misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of our late times, that hindred your Lordſhip from being ſooner preferred to the Pontifical Robe; for the opinion of the world did point your Lordſhip out for it with your firſt blooming beard: your early learning and gravity ſo much anticipating your years, and vertue rendring you Reverend before time. But it is your Lordſhips glory to
<pb facs="tcp:94686:8"/>have deſerved the honour of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick, ſooner than to enjoy it.</p>
            <p>Pardon my Lord, that I have dared to draw your youthfull Character with my rude pen; but thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent endowments of your Soul, ſo much akcnowledged by envy, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be admired by truth. And now that your Lordſhip is ſo far ſtept into years, we find yet the vigour of your divine vertues augmented by time, in their happy influences upon us, as it is ſaid, that the beſt Incenſe comes from old Trees, and Torches made of Aromatick-wood, caſt out their odoriferous Exhalati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons when they are almoſt waſted. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you were an example only to youth, but now your Lordſhip is become a pattern to Prieſts, and a preſident to Prelates; under whoſe heart remains a Temple of true Piety. Who then ſo proper for the higheſt Prelacy, as he that can enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marry Sobriety with Chaſtity, and
<pb facs="tcp:94686:8"/>Piety with Learning? How pure ought thoſe perſons to be, who are not only of the Houſe of God, but of his Cabinet, and as it were of the very boſome of God? In the Sacrifices to the Sun, there was never made an effuſion of Wine; How far from that then ought they to be, who are to ſacrifice to the great Maſter of the Sun? And Chaſtity as holy <hi>Zeno</hi> telleth us, is happy in Virgins, ſtrong in Widdows, <note place="margin">St. Zeno.</note> faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the Married; but with Prieſts and Prelates, it ought to be as it is in your Lordſhip, wholly Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphical.</p>
            <p>Some Biſhops we have known, that have lived in Biſhopricks like blind Cyclopes in a hollow cave, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that they have gone very far towards a perſwaſion of the world, that piety was a thing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible to be aſpired to, like ill-Phyſicians that make the ſick deſpair of health, becauſe they
<pb facs="tcp:94686:9"/>cannot cure them. <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> wondred to ſee men dandle Apes, having Children in their houſes; and who can but admire in Prelates, to whom God has afforded ſo many ſpir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tual Children, to ſee them kiſs Monkeys, and it may be ſomething worſe, play with Dogs, and carry Hawks, <hi>&amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all theſe vanities your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips known innocency and piety has alwayes defended you, and you appear now in the Church as you ought to do, like thoſe ancient Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of <hi>Polycletes</hi> and <hi>Phydias,</hi> of which there was not a lineament but ſpake. Your Lordſhips example has been a perpetual Sermon, which is the beſt of preaching (as St. <hi>Greg. Nazianzen</hi> divinely obſerves of the great St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi>) that his voyce was as a Thunder-clap, and his life a Lightning flaſh; <note place="margin">Greg. N.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z. in Jamb.</note> becauſe words never thunder well, if examples en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten not. There is no Libertine
<pb facs="tcp:94686:9"/>but will be daunted at the ſight of ſuch a life, lead truly according to Chriſtianity: it is a mirrour that kills Baſilisks by the repercuſſion of their own proper poyſon. So may your Lordſhip thunder on ſtill, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten this diſtracted people with your pious Precepts and Practice; that theſe poor ſeduced Chriſtians, may be reduced out of the Clawes of the Cockatrice, and recovered into your Chriſtian Fold. And ſure I cannot at all deſpair of the effect, if their refractory ſpirits will be at all won with ſweetneſs. It is ſaid, that Amber ſweetly drawes a trifling ſtraw, and Adamant gently wins the hardeſt iron, and with a Hony-comb fountains of the moſt troubled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are cleanſed. Nothing diſarmes a Paſſion, (and their whole Religion is no more) ſo much as Patience and temper, which your Lordſhip is known to be the accompliſhed Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of; and ſo ſhall by that means
<pb facs="tcp:94686:10"/>throw proſtrate at your feet, thoſe hair-brained Zelots, who ſeem now to roar over your Lordſhips head. <hi>Flecti autem qui recuſant, frangi opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet; nec invaleſcenti Eccleſiae &amp; Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicae morbo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Fulgent.</note> 
               <hi>molli uſpiàm Diaetâ ſuccurrendum eſt, ſed Chirurgiâ.</hi> So may your Lordſhip proceed and proſper in your happy Prelacy, and grow up to be as exemplary an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of your Royal Maſters peace, his Kingdoms happineſs, the Churches good, glory of your gown, and honour of your Univerſity and Colledge as that great and glorious Prelate <hi>Henry Chichly</hi> was, your moſt famous founder; which is meant for as much temporal felicit, as can be wiſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d from the heart of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>My Lord, Your Lordſhips</hi> Moſt humble Honourer, and moſt dutifully obedient Servant, <hi>Tho. Bellamy.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:94686:10"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader, rendring the occaſion of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe, with ſome <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> marks or characters of that ſort of Chriſtians that call themſelvs <hi>Proteſtants of Integrity.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THough the Authour of this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Treatiſe intended it princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally for a Caveat to all Chriſtian Princes and Prelates; yet it is as properly applicable to all ſorts of Chriſtian people too, who ought to take it for a Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Piece, to arm themſelves againſt that moſt horrid cheat of Presbytery, now cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Proteſtancy of Integrity: For how can the ſupream Prince either of Church or State, be capable to govern well, unleſs their Subjects be taught how to obey? which is abſolutely impoſſible they ſhould ever learn to do, ſo long as by the Principles of any wretched Religion, that they ſhall ſuck in with their firſt milk, they find themſelves bound to rebel? Now that the Presbyterian Profeſſion is cleerly ſuch a
<pb facs="tcp:94686:11"/>one, and not onely inconſiſtent with Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, but all ſorts of Civil Government, you ſhall find moſt evidently made out to you by the Proceſs of this diſcourſe. The oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion whereof was (as I have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) this. There was a Presbyterian Pamphlet publiſhed about a Twelvemonth ſince, under this glorius Title, <hi>A Letter from a Proteſtant of Integrity, in anſwer to a Letter from a perſon of Quality,</hi> to the ſame Principal Peer of the R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alm now ſitting in Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Upon the ſight and full peruſal of beth theſe Letters, our Authour truly concluded, that he who writ the former, was indeed as the Title ſpoke him to be, (a Perſon of Quality) and that was evident by the evenneſs of his ſtile, cleerneſs of ſenſe, ſtrength, rationality and candor of his diſcourſe: and the other to be (as he likewiſe entitles himſelf) a True Proteſtant of pretended Integrity, noe onely for the barbarous <hi>Billingſ-gate</hi> language, moſt abominable lyes, and unchriſtian vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulency that fell from his pen, without any reſpect had to the reaſons which he pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to anſwer; but alſo for his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous daring to defend the moſt noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Traytors and Rebels in the whole world; and to that purpoſe has an entire
<pb facs="tcp:94686:11"/>Paragraph to prove, nay does moſt magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterially affirm, that the Presbyterians by name, ought to be numbred amoneſt the beſt of Subjects, if they would be as conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in Eccleſiaſticks, as they were ſound in their Politicks.</p>
            <p>Our Authour therefore finding himſelf offended with that inſufferable affront of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to his Majeſty, and indeed to all Chriſtianity, by ſuch an irrational, undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, and trayterous vindication of thoſe Perſons, and their Doctrines, fairly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to prove how unſound they are in their Politicks; and that it is as utterly impoſſible that they ſhould be ever brought to a conformity to the Civil, more then to the Eccleſiaſtical Government; and all this he does out of the undeniable dictates of their own dead Doctors, though but lately flouriſhing, and their moſt Primitive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; Let him look to it then that dares (now they are declar'd) to defend them.</p>
            <p>Now if they ſhall pleaſe to diſabuſe their own ſouls, I beſeech them to peruſe this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Treatiſe, with all patience and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiality, and then I am confident that they will quickly find by their own reaſon, thoſe falſe ſpectacles to fall off, that have been ſo long clapt over their eyes, by their
<pb facs="tcp:94686:12"/>own falſ ſeers, (poſſeſt with the Spirit of lyes) who are continually working of more for their deception and forgeing on ſtill in the ſhop of Hell, their Religious Inſtruments of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, which ſhall perſwade men alwayes (if they will believe them) to take glaſs for Diamond, and ſuch Keſtrels as they are, for Faulcons. But he that will find out the bottom of any religious or civil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, muſt prepare himſelf to carry a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit throughly diſcharged of all anticipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, bold animoſities, and falſe apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which will raiſe miſts even upon the moſt reſplendent lights of Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauſanias</hi> tells us of a falſe Mirrour kept in the Temple at <hi>Smyrna,</hi> which did repreſent the moſt beautifull and amiable faces, with notable deformity; and on the contrary, gave to Creatures ugly and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhapen, ſome falſe luſtre of a borrowed and wholly imaginary beauty.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of the Presbyterian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion make no little uſe of ſuch mirrours as thoſe in their Temples (as they call them) and repreſent in the falſe glaſs of their Doctrines, the true Church of Chriſt, (that has all the Epithets of beauty and comelineſs given to her, in the divine book of Canticles, as the onely lovely, and chaſte
<pb facs="tcp:94686:12"/>Spoaſe of Chriſt) as a Monſter compoſed of all ſorts of abomitation: and their own pittifull and ugly geer, for the onely pure and legitimate product of the Goſpel. If the People have their ears perpetually beaten, with the ſeven Hills of <hi>Rome,</hi> with Antichriſt, with the horned Beaſt, with Idolatry and Superſtition, which they maliciouſly obtrude upon all Hierarchy; and their own Hereſies, Blaſphemies, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanations, Sacriledges and Rebellions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and their King, are all cover'd with the ſpecious outſide of Godlineſs, which they now call Proteſtancy of Integrity; how can the poor people chuſe but embrace them as the bleſſed fruits of the Spirit it ſelf? if they remain fixed in theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, how can they chuſe but hate what they know not, or that which is repreſented to them for bad? Some there are, that in the opinion of the world (at leaſt the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant or indifferently knowing part of it) are gazed at, and admired in their Pulpits, as flying fire in the air, when indeed they are meer nothings, or truly (which is far worſe then nothing) ſtark nought, and vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanous <hi>Ignes fatui,</hi> only diſpoſed to lead men to their deſtruction. The Hebrews there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ha l a moſt excellent ſaying, that Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar
<pb facs="tcp:94686:13"/>was an ill Son of a good Father, for it is commonly made of the beſt wine; ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thitg can be worſe than a corrupted Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: capable they may be perchance, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex the moſt evident propoſitions, and that is indeed a moſt eminent piece of their learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which is no more then that of common Sorcerers or Conjurers, (as they call them) who can caſt miſts upon the cleereſt morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or like the divinity of Dogs, who do uſually bark at the Moons brightneſs: The bleſſed eyes of Bats they have, to mock at the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ateſt lights, and the malice of the old <hi>Atlantes,</hi> to ſhoot their arrows againſt the Sun. Nothing is ſo abſolutely conſirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on all ſides, as that no man can be ſaved without true Religion, and yet nothing) by the malice of the Devil and ſuch Doctors) is ſo controverted, as the verity of Religion: notwithſtanding, if we err in the choice, we make ſhipwrack before we weigh anchor; and ſo long as we remain in error, nothing can ſave or deliver us from eternal damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <note place="margin">St. <hi>Fulg.</hi> in lib. de fid. ad Pet. Diac. c. 48</note> as St. <hi>Fulgentius</hi> declares at large, in the book which he compoſed of Faith, <hi>ad Petrum Diaconum:</hi> For we muſt all know, or be maliciouſly ignorant, that the true Church, is as the Pole-ſtar that is ever in motion, but never ſets. It is high time
<pb facs="tcp:94686:13"/>therefore, and as I humbly conceive, huge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary, to lay down ſome <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or certain marks, to diſtinguiſh theſe pure Proteſtants of pretended Integrity, from the true Profeſſors and Practiſers of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p>Now firſt, we are ſure, that all true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion hath this property inherent, to tend wholly towards Monarchy, that is Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy; and whoſoever goes about to introduce any other form of Government into the Church, as if it were fit, or reaſonable, it is cleerly to thruſt thorns into the feet, and to put ſtraws into the eyes of it; and this property is ſo well agreeable (we all know) with our holy brethren of the Presbytery, who pretend to be the pureſt Proteſtants of Integrity, that I ſhall not need to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further dilucidation. So I ſhall paſs to our ſecond <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or mark of diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which you may pleaſe to take to be cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this.</p>
            <p>All Innovation is utter poyſon to true Religion; and it is as cleer, that the whole perſwaſion of all theſe wretched Religiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that call themſelves Proteſtants of Integrityis nothing elſe but a heap and hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of Novelties: for as to Antiquity, and ſucceſſion of their Doctrines, they do not,
<pb facs="tcp:94686:14"/>or ever did (for as much as I have ever heard) pretend at any time to it; but juſt like <hi>Aeſops</hi> Aſs, that vaunted he had great ſecrets of wiſdom to communicate to other beaſts; and that he might the better authorize his Philoſophy, and gain credit to himſelf and diſcourſe, he hid himſelf a long time a deep dry pit, from whence he came out at laſt with a goodly grave Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers cloak about him, ſaying, that all the while that he had been ſo inviſible, he had very much addicted himſelf to the ſtudy of ſciences, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertul.</hi> in Marc. l. 4. c. 23.</note> and the knowledge of truth.</p>
            <p>This was the very Parable that <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> ſpake to the Hereticks of his time (and that is pretty ancient) They come forth, ſaith he, as an Aſs out of <hi>Aeſops</hi> pit, and can neither tell who they are, nor whither they would, from whence they came, nor who ſent them; nor what right they have to extinguiſh that glorious light of our bleſſed fore-fathers. Juſt ſuch a ſhameleſs and ridiculous beginning have our pretended pure Proteſtants of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, which well proves their nullity, and that they ought to be ſo nobly attended, as to to have for retinue, Rapine, Robbery, Murder, Sacriledg, Rebellion, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicide. All innovation, we know, is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb facs="tcp:94686:14"/>in any State, whither Civil or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, but principally in matter of Faith; but you may pleaſe to take this for a Rule; They that follow the main current and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rality of a Religion, ancient and well-grounded, cannot periſh, but by the falling of Heaven; nor ſtumble in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, but by entombing themſelves in the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of Chriſtianity; which God neither can nor will ſuffer to be loſt, according to his Promiſes. They which adhere to Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſail na Sea full of Monſters and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, without Pole-ſtar, without Rudder, without Pilot, or any other guide then their own ſingle judgment, which cannot chuſe but very certainly deceive them; and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs if there be any flames in Hell employed for the puniſhment of ſinfull Souls, there is no queſtion but they ſhall be inflicted chiefly on thoſe who do endeavour daily to rend the garment of Jeſus Christ, to break the ſacred ſeams and connexions of the Church, to ſtrike at all the lawfull powers ordained by God, to throw diſorder, fire, and blood into the State of their Prince; nay upon his very perſon, commit that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred murder (called Parricide) upon their King and ſheath their ſwords ia the bowels of their Countrey, which puts me
<pb facs="tcp:94686:15"/>naturolly upon the Third <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or mark of a true Religion, and that is obedience to Magiſtrates both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, and adue reverence in divine Worſhip, and to all holy things. As to the point of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, how well it ſquareth with our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of Integrity, and how demonſtrable it is, that they are, and muſt be Rebels, according to their own Principles, this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Treatiſe does moſt ſufficiently make appear, to which I refer you. But for the manner of their Divine ſervice, (as they call it) it is ſo barbarouſly ugly, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominably naſty, that it would turn the ſtomack of a good Jew, or reaſonable Turk, ſo much as to look upon it: Nay all the reverence that they bear to holy things, is onely to prey upon them by ſacrilegious ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, and horrid prophanation: But let them look to themſelves, for ſuch Godly doings; for thoſe Crimes which do affront the Divinity, ever bear their puniſhments behind them. Did not <hi>Craſſus</hi> feel amongſt the Parthians, the Religion of the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſeph.</hi> lib. 18. c. 28.</note> which he had ſo ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſly violated? God making the ſteel of thoſe Barbarians to revenge his injured Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> has well obſerved. A hand from Heaven character'd a dread fall
<pb facs="tcp:94686:15"/>Decree againſt a great Babylonian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, which has ſerved for a Tragedy ever ſince the Prophet <hi>Daniels</hi> time, <note place="margin">Dan.</note> and will be ſo continued as a terrible ſpectacle to all poſterity. And afterwards we find <hi>Heliodorus</hi> in the <hi>Machabees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Mach.</hi> c. 3.</note> to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digiouſly puniſhed by exterminating An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the mid day ſcourged him in the ſight of all the world; employing their heavenly whips upon his body, for the ſame crime, as he had beſtowed his hardyneſs, and audacious hand, to ſteal a jewel from Heaven. Whatſoever they think of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I am ſure the moral of it is not Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphal. <hi>Herod,</hi> in like manner, opened King <hi>Davids</hi> Sepulcher, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſeph.</hi> l. 16. c. 11.</note> and took the ſpoil thereof; but note his miſerable end, and what diſsaſters did ever after attend him, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> will relate to you; <hi>Urraca</hi> went to rob the Sanctuary of S. <hi>Iſidore</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> to defray the charge and expence of his wars; <note place="margin">Hiſt. gen. <hi>Hiſpan.</hi> part. 4.</note> and his guts burſt out of his belly in the Church-Porch: as is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Hiſtory general of Spain. <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth Emperour, took a moſt precious Crown out of the Church of <hi>Sancta Sophia,</hi> in <hi>Conſttntinople,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sigon.</hi> l. 1. de regno. <hi>Ital.</hi>
               </note> which was dedicated to it; and he dyed ſoon after of a cruel Carbuncle, as <hi>Sigonius</hi> witneſſeth.
<pb facs="tcp:94686:16"/>
               <hi>Gondericus,</hi> King of the <hi>Vandals,</hi> when he took <hi>Sevil,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tarapha</hi> in Houric.</note> took alſo the ſpoils of the Churches, and ſeiz'd upon the riches there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and to requite him, the Divel ſtreight ſeiz'd and poſſeſt him, as <hi>Tarapha</hi> tells us. What Puniſhment had <hi>Julian</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtata, amogſt his other ſins, for his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Church-robbing at <hi>Antioch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Trip.</hi> l. 6. c. 31.</note> the Tripartit Hiſtory will inform us. To conclude, (for what need I uſe more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of terror?) read only the ſtory of <hi>Nicephorus Phocas,</hi> who reſumed all do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations that were made unto Monaſteries and Churches, commiting a thouſand Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines and prophanations upon ſacred things; but ſee what afflictions and furies haunted him ever after: and therefore his ſucceſſor <hi>Baſilius</hi> thought fit to abrogate thoſe Lawes of <hi>Phocas,</hi> which tended to the ſuppreſſion of Monaſteries, as the Root of all the cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities that happened in that time. I have been a little larger upon this particular, becauſe our Pure Brethren of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, theſe pretended Proteſtants of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, do pleaſe themſelves ſo much with this their ſacrilegious Dalila, though it is not a little admirable, <hi>quorum facta imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur eorum exitus non perhorreſcere</hi> So I paſs to the next mark of true Religion,
<pb facs="tcp:94686:16"/>which I take to be a faithfull, conſtant, ſolid courſe of devotion towards God, by a dutifull addreſs to him in Prayer, and practical imitation of his Holy Life.</p>
            <p>The Spirit of the beſt man, (we know) is in no better condition than a Sun-Dial; which is of no uſe at all, but when the Sun reflects upon it: nor can any man expect that his underſtanding ſhould receive any true light, but what is reflected from the Rayes of God; and that muſt be by the means of Prayer. The practice therefore of this holy Duty, has been every ſtyled and eſteemed by all the holy fathers of the Church, as the key of Heaven, and confuſion of Hell; the ſtandard of our Chriſtian warfare, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of our peace, the bridle of our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience, the guardiau of our temperance, the ſeal of chaſtity, the Advocate of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendors, the conſolation of the afflicted, and the Paſſport of the dying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the Just do live and die in prayer, as the Phaenix in her perfumes. A Chriſtian therefore without Prayer, may be compared to a Bee without a ſting, which can neither make honey, nor wax. The Apoſtle therefore bid us to pray alwayes; which St. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> interpreteth thus, that we are to have God in our minds ſo often as we
<pb facs="tcp:94686:17"/>breath. It is not therefore unfilty ſtyled the Spirit of Prayer, for it is the breath of the inward man; <hi>Os meum aperui,</hi> ſaith the Scripture, <hi>&amp; attraxi ſpiritum,</hi> I open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my mouth, and drew in the ſpirit; we are all of us ready to be choaked with filthy fleſh and fat, and to be devoured with the flames of concupiſcence, unleſs upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, we do open our mouths, to take in that gentle air of God: a good Chriſtian is therefore reſembled to the Palm-tree, which as it is the talleſt and ſtraiteſt of all trees, ſo bears its beſt and moſt ſolid ſtrength in its top: just ſo has a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian his whole vigour in God, and for God; his life is a perpetual Sabbath, <hi>Sabbathum delicatum,</hi> a moſt delicious Sabbath, as the Prophet cals it, nouriſhing and repoſing the Soul, with the conſtant draught of this holy Spirit of Prayer; a true Chriſtian makes it not onely his lock and key of the day, but his bolt at night; nor only ſo, but his very meals and recreations. The Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians therefore were uſually called the Crickets of the night; becauſe at any time of it, if any interruption of ſleep hapened, they ever made it out, with eſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatory Prayer, and elevation of their hearts. Thoſe that love God truly, will
<pb facs="tcp:94686:17"/>have recourſe to him at all hours, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions, not confining their devotions to time or place. <hi>Jonas</hi> and the three Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, found ſufficient Chappels in the Whales belly and in the fiery Furnace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the love of God, the wiſeſt Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect had erected them; and God was as neer them in the intrals of fiſh, or the midſt of flames, as he would have been in his moſt holy Temple. Now methinks I hear our Phariſailal Proteſtants of Integrity crying out, O we have enough of that to ſay for our ſelves; there are none living ſo converſant in that holy duty of frequent, and Family Prayer, as we; Yes indeed, like ſome of thoſe devotes which <hi>Horace</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Jane Pater Clare, Clare cum dicit</hi> Apollo —<hi>Labra movet metuens audire, &amp;c. Da mihi fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere, da juſtum ſanctum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> videri:</hi> Pray much, and very often; but immediately fall to cozening, lying, and cheating, and to ſtudy how to entrap men: a devotion much like his, whoſe way to his wench, lying through a Church-yard, ſaid his prayers alwayes going and coming. This is not the true devotion that is ſpoken of; but as St. <hi>Gregory</hi> well expreſſeth it, to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice the Calf without the flower; which is
<pb facs="tcp:94686:18"/>to make Prayer with the lips, without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the heart: ſo granting the Prayers of theſe Proteſtants of Integrity, to be never ſo good or frequent, they do no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than one <hi>Neanthus</hi> did, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving inherited <hi>Orpheus</hi> his Harp, and thinking to do wonders with it, played ſo ill, that dogs affrighted with his untune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able skreaking noyſe, tore him all to pieces: So it is not enough, to have a great many holy Frayers in our hands, which ſound like the ſtrings of Gods Harp, and may be conſign'd to us by Jeſus Christ himſelf, and all the Primitive holy Fathers, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat them as often too as they did; but we must uſe them with that true devotion of heart, as is required, least we find our pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment in the very ſacrifice of Propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Nor must this high Chriſtian duty be performed in that ſtrange, ſawey, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar and Phariſaical manner, as is cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary with theſe Proteſtants of integrity; but rather in our most retyred privacies, and a becoming ſilence, better than any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior oſtent, reſembling thoſe rivers which run under the earth, chooſing to ſteal from the eyes of the world, to ſeek for the ſight of God only: So true devotions ever ſtudy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude and retirements, and are alwayes
<pb facs="tcp:94686:18"/>beſt, when ſhut up within themſelves. I have the rather choſe to inſiſt upon this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the pretence of theſe Proteſtants of Integrity, to a true performance of this duty, is the grand cheat and impoſture, that they put upon poor Chriſtian ſouls, to draw them into their unchriſtian Conventicles. So I come to the ſecond part of our last re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark upon true Religion, which is, a pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Piety towards God, and Man; for as the heart and marrow of Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts wholly in the interiour, ſo we can make no other judgment of that, than by the apparent practiſe of Piety, and true Godly and religious lives of men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all this is but a natural effect of that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Spirit of Prayer before ſpoken of. For true devotion (as the great St. <hi>Tho.</hi> of <hi>Aquine</hi> has deſcribed it) is nothing but a prompt will for the ſervice of God: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquin.</hi> l. 2. q. 82.</note> his words are theſe, <hi>Voluntas quaedam promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta tradendi ſe ad ea, quae pertinent ad Dei famulatum,</hi> A very prompt and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate vivacity in things which concern the ſervice of God: nay we may find ſo much as that ſaid by <hi>Porphyry</hi> himſelf a Pagan, and one of the most Atheiſtical ones that ever lived; <hi>Deus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium Pater nullius indigit, ſed nobis eſt
<pb facs="tcp:94686:19"/>bene, cum eum adoramus, ipſam vitam precem ad cum facientes, per inquiſitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, &amp; imitationem de ipſo:</hi> That is, God the Creator and Father of this great Univers, hath no need at all of our ſervice; but it is our good to honour, ſerve, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore him, making our lives to be perpetual prayers to him, by a diligent enquiry after his Perfections, and a holy imitation of his Virtues; <note place="margin">St. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </note> All this St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> (the Oracle of the Latine Church) recites out of that Heathen, to teach us faith from the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy of the most perfidious, and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion from the writings of the most irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious man in the whole world: just as if an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>honest man ſhould pull a thing ſtoln out of a thieves coffer. And indeed it is a most evident truth, that the best life is the best prayer, and therefore St. <hi>Greg. Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen</hi> tells us, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note place="margin">Greg. Naz. in Jamb.</note> A dumb work ſpeaks a Chriſtian better, than the most eloquent ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and a golden tongue, and a leaden heart make an ill march together: yet we know that ſome there are of theſe pure Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of Integrity, who have appearance enough of the Spirit, and will pray in the ſimilitude of Angels, but practice like Devils, reſembling the Aſs in the fable, that
<pb facs="tcp:94686:19"/>carries daily to the hot-houſe, wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to ſhift and cleanſe others, and yet goes himſelf perpetually bemired and ſlovenly; ſo whilſt they preach to others, (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle tells us) become caſtaways them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: or yet more like the impertinent drone, they can go buzzing up and down, with their empty prayers, and yet as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, neither make honey nor wax. To what purpoſe is it therefore to be ſo, <hi>vox &amp; praeterea nihil,</hi> to warble like a Nightin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale, or a well ſtrung Lute, and to be deaf to all harmony? Is not that to be at best (as the Apoſtle tells us) but as ſounding braſs, or a tinck ling Cymbal? Undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all the devotion of a Soul truly Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, tendeth to practiſe, as the line to its Center; and therefore St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> moſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly proclaims thus, <hi>Philoſophi factis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> in lib. de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientia.</note> 
               <hi>non verbis ſumus, nec magna loquimur, ſed vivimus,</hi> Our Philoſophy and Chriſtian wiſdom, ſaith he, is a prudence of works, not of words; and we are to live, not talk great things. We are to march in our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian warfore, like the brave Soldiers of <hi>Gideon,</hi> with the torch in our hands, as well as the trumpet upon our lips. But now all this is Superſtitious, nay Popiſh in the eſteem of our pure Proteſtants of Integrity,
<pb facs="tcp:94686:20"/>who will do no good works at all, for fear of meriting by them, and profeſs none but a ſolifidian way to heaven, which my faith can never reach to believe, will bring them thither: ſomethings, it may be, they'l do as their elder brothers, (the Phariſees before did) but with ſuch a pittifull deal of oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and vain glory, or the ſame abominable pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed hypocriſie too, that it is plain, they court their own intereſt in all that, more than their conſcience, and apparently love themſelves ſo, more than they do God, for which they are like to receive their reward in this life, which is to have the execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all mankind; for verily there is no vice deſerves it better, than that, which diſtends ſnares over Altars, and under colour of zeal and piety, ſeeks to entrap men. God Almighty therefore requireth of us, that all which we do, ſhould be done with ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and alacrity; with ſincerity firſt, and for Gods ſake, and our left hand ought not know what our right hand does: but theſe Proteſtants of Integrity forſooth, will none of that ſincerity, nor do any thing that may appear good, but the whole Town ſhall ring of it, and all the Trumpets ſound to it, to proclaim their great Integrity. The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Majeſty (in the mean time we know)
<pb facs="tcp:94686:20"/>ha's ever reproved, condemned, and chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a moſt particular indignation of his heart, that abominable playsterd kind of life, amongſt Chriſtians ſure, as well as Jews, to whom (we find) that therefore it was given for <hi>a</hi> Law, that the Swan and the Oſtrich ſhould never be made uſe of, in divine Sacrifices; upon which Moſaical Ordinance, all the interpreters of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are joyntly of opinion, that the Swan was first rejected, notwithſtanding the whiteneſs of her feathers, and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of note, ſo much aſcribed to her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe under thoſe pure white plumes, ſhe hides ſo black a fleſh. Then for the Oſtrich, which carries onely an oſtentuous boast of faire large wings, and very little or no flight at all, ſhe could never he admitted into the number of divine Victims. So much does God abhor apparencies fruitleſs and effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs. What ſhall we ſay leſs of theſe pure Proteſtants of integrity, do they not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly appear like thoſe Swans and Ostri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? Or rather like to pityful Snayles, who in their courſes, make long ſilver tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and are indeed in their interiour, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but meer froth. They have their backs, like Cuſhions, cover'd with Velvet, Sattin, Taffata, or Cloth of Gold, and
<pb facs="tcp:94686:21"/>ſtuff't within, with nothing but Hay. They make a fair ostent of leaves and verdure like a wood, but are repleniſht with nothing but ſerpents. In fine, theſe Hypocrites, and formal Profeſſors of Religion, are very Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphims in appearance, but Seraphims without eyes, without heart or hands, and have wings of mighty zeal, inflamed with a prophan fire, onely fit to burn the Propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatory it ſelf, which indeed is their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſtudy to do. To conclude the ſincerity aforeſaid in theſe practical parts of piety, is not more requiſite or agreeable to God, then alacrity in his ſervice, nor indeed more a mark of a true and undefiled religion. God loveth a cheerful giver, not only of his mony, but of himſelf: God loveth (I ſay) a cheerful Liver, as well as a cheerful giver. For what hinders (as our incomparable Lord Chancellour, <note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce lour.</note> was pleas'd in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment moſt judiciouſly to alledge) that a merry man may be a godly man? nay the Godlieſt? For there is no game, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation in the world, can be compared to the ſoul of a good Chriſtian? whoſe conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is not onely a continual feaſt, but a Portative Theater, wherein are inceſſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſented moſt admirable ſhews, as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> tells us in his Book <hi>de Spectaculis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Yeptull. de Spectac.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:94686:21"/>Undoubtedly there is not a thing in it ſelf more unacceptable to God, then that dull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and heavineſs of ſpirit, taken up as a practice amongſt theſe Proteſtants of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity. God is not pleas'd, that we ſhould enter into his ſervice, as if we were to be lifted upon a rack to be tortured. Nay I do affirm it muſt be of neceſſity a moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid injury done to the divine Majeſty, to think there can be no true Piety, or devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the world, if our bodies be not torne in pieces, and our ſpirits quite to be beaten down; And therefore <hi>Gilbertus</hi> (an excellent Doctor) writing upon that Sentence of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gilbertus.</note> 
               <hi>Glorificate &amp; por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Deum in corpore veſtro,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> Glorifie and bear God in your bodies, makes this most elegant and remarkable obſervation, you muſt bear Jeſus Chriſt, not dragge him. <hi>Portari vult Chriſtus, non trahi,</hi> ſo he proceeds, <hi>non eſt foenum Chriſtus, ſed flos campi, &amp; faſciculus mirrhae, inter ubera ſponſae, &amp;c.</hi> Now he plainly draggs him, who makes himſelf ſurcharged with him, and who indiſcreetly afflicts himſelf in the ſervice that he renders to the divine Majeſty, not conſidering, that Jeſus Chriſt is the Flower of the field, or the Poeſie of Mirrh, between the breaſts of the Spouſe,
<pb facs="tcp:94686:22"/>and not a load of hay, to be drawn, under which we muſt needs groan, like to wheels ill greaſed; this was ſo fooliſh a ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo old a one, that the Philoſopher himſelf (though a Pagan) could not but find extream great fault withal, and condemn for horridly extravagant ſuperſtition. <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitio</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quos colit violat, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandos timet.</hi> It is a ſtrange fond Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition indeed, ſaith this wiſe Pagan, and raiſed by ſimple people onely, which through groſs errour feares, what it ſhould love by virtue, and can hardly have any knowledg of, or approach to the Deity, but by viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Clemency (a thing moſt hateful to him) through a falſe preſumption of his ſeverity. They muſt be very ſilly ſouls ſure, and have very little or no feeling of the divinity, that can apprehend God, whom we hourly find to be infinitely merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to be as Terrible as a <hi>Minos</hi> or a <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damanthus</hi> mentioned in Poetical Fables, who were alwayes repreſented in thoſe Fictions, to be moſt Spiteful Deities, to come and pry into all humane actions, to number all mens ſteps, and taking pleaſure to prepare puniſhments for them, were wont to raiſe themſelves immortal Trophyes, upon poore Mortals ruins.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:94686:22"/>
            <p>It would be a pretty piece of Chriſtianity, one would think now, to be preached amongst us, that devotion, and all labours in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſhould be undertaken by us without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny relaxation; perpetual diſturbancies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone by Chriſtians, without any repoſe, and miſeries without any remedy, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort at all. This ſure must be thought the oxtream of all extreams, and fit only for our Proteſtants out of their wits, that now call themſelves Proteſtants of Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but I ſear will be found to be Proteſtants of pure knavery; I mean thoſe Hypocrites and formal Profeſſors of Religion treated of, whom we may very well compare to thoſe Oxon of <hi>Baal,</hi> who are cut and mang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for Sacrifice into little Gobbets, but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding receive no fire from Heaven: just ſo theſe pittifull creatures, this ſad ſort of Chriſtians, do moſt miſerably ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerate, and almost kill themſelves, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice only to the opinions of the world, and their own bruitiſh appetites, without ever taſting the conſolations of God. A true good Chriſtian in the mean time endeavours ſo to diſtribute his faſtings, watchings, prayer, repast, recreations and ſtudies, with ſo prudent an oeconomy, for the ſervice of his God, that he holds his life most admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably
<pb facs="tcp:94686:23"/>interlaced between Action, Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, and repoſe, that he makes on earth, a perfect figure of Angels aſcending and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending, and receives already ſo great a tast of thoſe benefits, which he is to hope for in the other world, that he ſeems to have his ſoul in heaven, whilst he dwells upon the earth, to fathom myſteries, and with his, beatified underſtanding, to enjoy an Antepaſt of Paradiſe it ſelf. Who then can with more juſtice and reaſon ſhew forth a jolly, cheerfull countenance, and make the clarity of his heart break forth at his eyes, and lips, then ſuch a Chriſtian? How well this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Character a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with the ſad Profeſſors of this age, let the whole world judge; who are just ſuch as <hi>Seneca deſcribed ſome of his time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
               <hi>Triſtes &amp; omnia deplorantes, quibus nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la non cauſa in querelam placet, ſemper preſentibus infeſti;</hi> Sad and melancholly Companions, alwayes complaining of every thing, and nothing, diſpleaſed ſtill with the preſent ſtate of Affairs; and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes upon this kind of mal' contents, <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gri proprium eſt animi nihil diu pati, &amp; mutationibus ut remediis uti,</hi> Their ſickly diſpoſitions are alwayes given to change, and ſo uſe mutations for remedies: So that theſe
<pb facs="tcp:94686:23"/>ſad Chriſtians are altogether as dangerous to all Civil States whereſoever they live, as to the State of the Church, and are only fit to hold compliance with that ſort of people whoſe Religion is to worſhip a Cat. The last <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Symptom of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, is Humility; the ſtars we know are best beheld in the bottom of a Pit, and the most radiant ſplendors of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, do appear in a profound humility; St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> therefore ſayes of this tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent virtue, that it is <hi>Primus Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis introitus, &amp; ultimus Chriſtianitatis Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> The gate of all Religion, and the very Crown of Chriſtianity; for who can think that that man will be faithfull at all to Jeſus Chriſt, that can be unfaithfull to that holy v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtue which ſhined ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in him? the whole cours of his life upon earth, being nothing elſe, from the Crib to the Croſs, but a conſtant moving Homily of humility. The Sun (we ſee) which is the Prince of Planets, diſpelleth always all the groſeſt, thickeſt, and ſtiffeſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, and draweth the thinneſt and most ſubtil to himſelf; how much more then that we do attenuate, leſſon and annihilate our ſelves, by the practice of this caeleſtial vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of humility, ſo much the neerer we are
<pb facs="tcp:94686:24"/>ſure to approach to the Son of righteouſueſs, and true glory. But our pure Proteſtants of Integrity, are ſo overgrown with Pride of Spirit, that it may be quickly ſeen, how far they run out of the road of Chriſtianity. Their Pride is far greater then that of the old Phariſee, who boaſted only that he was not as other men are, but they boaſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be what all others ſhould be, and ſo preſcribe themſelves to be pure patterns of Perfection, to all the world: But it is (we know) the terribleſt blow in the whole world, when a man is wounded in the head, by his own proper judgment, Pride and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. We come to the end of moſt things by ſtrength of Induſtry; ſtones are pulled forth from the very entrals of men; the head is ſometimes opened, to make vapours iſſue out, but what hand hath ever drawn a falſe opinion out of the brains of a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually prond, and preſumptuous man? All ſeems green (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) to thoſe that look upon the water, and all is good and ſpecious, <note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> to ſuch as behold themſelves in proper love. Better it were according to the counſels of the old Fathers of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, to have one foot in Hell, with a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibility of ſpirit, than a hand or arm in heaven, with ones own judgment. To be
<pb facs="tcp:94686:24"/>ſhort, this unhappy Pride of Spirit, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits a maſſacre upon the whole chain of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly virtues: It marres all that can be called good in a man; let this curſed dram be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, and all together will ſignifie no more, than a wholſome medicament with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture of poyſon in it. It is ſuch a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual venom, that it turnes the ſublimeſt virtues into ſpecious vices, and makes them become but holly Trayters to the ſouls of men. Thus if the pulſes of our pure bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, theſe Proteſtants of Integrity, be judiciouſly felt, the world may quickly find, their adulterate, new, no Religion. From theſe proud melancholick, malcontent, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical Spirits, it is that all thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious doctrines of diſobedience and rebellion have proceeded; as you will ſee proved by the proceſs of this diſcours. Tis plainly they, and only they, that have ſturred up the aſhes of old Rubelais here again amongſt us, and do ſtill ſo delight themſelves to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers with putrifaction, that under their wings we do daily behold new vermin to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe in the Church, which endeavour to gnaw, and diſſipate all that hath any Piety, or fear of God, in Chriſtianity. Nor are they only content to throw poyſon and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifaction into the State Eccleſiaſtical, but
<pb facs="tcp:94686:25"/>are alwayes brewing of new miſchiefs, bloodſhed and rebellion in the Civil States of their Princes. Their Cities themſelves where their holy villanies have got footing, reſemble more Cyclopian Caverns, rather then Temples of peace, piety and juſtice: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed briefly to conclude, the whole fabrick of their Religion, is lik a Caſtle, that I have ſeen in ancient painting, built upon ruines, in a land of quick ſilver, cemented with blood, and overthrown with frequent earthquakes, and violent outragious winds: For it is certain, that if the arme of God ſuſtein not an affair, the more exaltation, it receives, the deeper ruins it finds. <hi>Sic Pereant, &amp; qui moliri talia pergunt,</hi> which ought to be the Prayer of every good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, is, and ever ſhall be, in ſpite of all Proteſtancy of Integrity, the conſtant devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him, that takes the honour to extitle himſelf.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Philanax Anglicus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94686:25"/>
            <head>The Publiſher, to the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>I Have made bold, good Reader, to publicſh this Poſthume Piece, the genuine off ſpring of a dead Brother in Law of mine, who was to my knowledg a moſt obſervant Son, and in every honeſt mans eſteem, a pious, Reverend and learned Prieſt of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> out of duty to which, as became an obedient member, and allegiance to my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, as a Loyal Subject, I have dared to produce it into the worlds light; eſpecially being informed by better judgments, that it was of a moſt conſiderable concernment both to King and Church: My zeal there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the Publick good, I hope will apologize for any particular errors in the impreſſion, there lying an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy neceſſity upon us, to collect the whole out of very diſperſt, and ill written Papers. My Brothers name I hope you will excuſe me for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing,
<pb facs="tcp:94686:26"/>becauſe is does appear to be his will to have it ſo; for it was ever his deſire to live, and ſo to die, <hi>Plebeius ſenex</hi> unnoiſed in the world. But if any one deſire a further ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. I am ready to anſwer, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes his faithfull Brother, and good Reader,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very Servant, Tho. Bellamy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94686:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Chriſtian Caveat TO ALL KINGS, PRINCES, AND PRELATES.</head>
            <p>IT has been a very great Controverſie of late amongſt Divine Antiquaries, and not yet determined by them. I muſt beg pardon therefore, that it is attempted by me now, where this Egg of the Conſiſtorian Cockatrice, was firſt laid, whether at <hi>Wittenbergh</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> or amongſt the Religious <hi>Lollards,</hi> or <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffiſts</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> or the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. But this we are ſure of (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it was laid) that it was firſt hatched at <hi>Smalcald,</hi> then foſtered and nouriſhed at <hi>Geneva,</hi> and from thence took wing over moſt of the <hi>European</hi> Continent,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94686:27"/>and at laſt arrived upon the fag-end of our Iſland, called <hi>Scotland;</hi> where meeting with too good a reception, this fiery Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ſo inflamed the zeal of that cold Climate, and increaſed his own confidence, that he preſumed to advance his flight amongſt us in <hi>England,</hi> where he has for theſe many years fed himſelf upon the blood, and deſtroyed the ſouls of poor Chriſtians. But now it is to be hoped, that he is upon his laſt wings (if not legs) unleſs ſome of his own Plume have the unhappy power to imp him again, (to His Sacred Majeſties, their own, and the whole Kingdoms ruine:) In the mean time, I take it to be the duty of all good Chriſtians, to offer up inceſſantly their Prayers and Tears to God, with their utmoſt endeavors amongſt men, <hi>A Dios rogando, y con el maſo dando,</hi> as the wiſe <hi>Spaniard</hi> adviſeth, that this devouring Dragon may be at laſt overthrown, trampled under foot, and tied in iron chains under thoſe altars which we daily charge with our vows.</p>
            <p>The duty now incumbent upon me, is onely to repreſent him and all his brood, in their truly native, and rebel colours, as they are malicious oppugners of Sacred Majeſty. Now as the skilful in the art of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94686:27"/>Imagery inform us, nothing is ſo curious in a ſtatue, nor ſo hard in any piece to poliſh, as the Nails, which are the onely outward arms that nature has afforded us; yet that is my preſent task to do, nor onely ſo, but their very ſcratchings of the faces of Kings, and the tearing up of the whole Earth with their diabolical Nails, for the undermining, ſubverſion, and demolition of Monarchy, through the whole World, like true Proteſtants of Integrity!</p>
            <p>Now to begin with the Foreman of this grand machine of Iniquity, we ſhall finde <hi>Un Suiſs a la Porte,</hi> a Swiſs at the door, as no man fitter to be Porter to ſuch an Infernal Palace; and he appears to us ſometime in his grave Rug-gown, and pretended Paſtoral-ſtaff, ſometimes again in his ſwaggering Swaſh-Buckler habit, ſtriking and laying about him like any Madman, but ſtill keeping this Cockatrice Egg in his robuſtious boſome, where he is reſolved to hatch it, if he can. The firſt letter of this modern <hi>Cerberus</hi> his name, is <hi>Uldericus Zuinglius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zuing. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. <hi>1.</hi> Art. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> and thus he begins his game. <hi>Reges</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quando per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidi, &amp; extra Regulam Chriſti egerint, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt cum Deo deponi, &amp;c.</hi> Kings may be depoſed where they advance ungodlineſs,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94686:28"/>as <hi>Saul</hi> was. Now how they are to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, he explains his own meaning beſt, <hi>Gum ſuffragiis &amp; conſenſu totius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Art.</hi> 42, 43.</note> 
               <hi>aut ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joris partis multitudinis, Tyrannus tolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, fit Deo auſpice;</hi> that is, By the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages, votes, or conſent of the whole, or the major part of the multitude; and this is a work ſo pleaſing to God, that they are ſure to have his bleſſing upon it. Here like a true Proteſtant of Integrity, he puts the Sword plainly into the peoples hands; and to make it yet more clear, ſee his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle <hi>Conrado Sonnio.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 868.</note> 
               <hi>Permittendum,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>eſt Caeſari officium debitum.</hi> We muſt ſuffer our ſelves to pay a duty to <hi>Ceſar;</hi> but upon this condition, <hi>Si modo fidem nobis permittat illibatam; ſi nos illud negligentes patimur, neglectae Religionis rei erimus;</hi> if he will ſuffer us to enjoy our own Religion, as we will have it; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if we ſhould be ſo negligent as to ſuffer him, we ſhall be guilty of aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning Religion it ſelf. Thus they will be pleaſed to obey <hi>Ceſar,</hi> if <hi>Ceſar</hi> will be adviſed and directed by them; otherwiſe they have another courſe to take with him, they will talk with him to the purpoſe; but yet he will explain his meaning fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and more fully to us in his Epiſtle
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94686:28"/>
               <hi>Ad Ulmenſes,</hi> whom he admoniſheth, <note place="margin">Epiſt. l <hi>4.</hi> ſol. <hi>196.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ut coram auditoribus ſu is, ſenſim incipiant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahere perſonam Imperio Romano, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo ſtultum ſit agnoſcere hoc Imperium in Germania, quod non agnoſcitur Romae, unde nomen habet:</hi> And again, <hi>Nimis Amantes eſt is Rei Romanae; quid Germaniae cum Roma? Sed prudenter &amp; paulatin agenda ſunt hujuſmodi atque cum paucis, quibus credere poſſis, &amp;c.</hi> That they ſhould by little and little in their Congregations, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask the uſurpation of the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and ſhew them how ridiculous a thing it is to acknowledge that Empire in <hi>Germany,</hi> which is not acknowledged at <hi>Rome</hi> if ſelf, from whence it hath its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination. He tells them further, That they ought not to be ſo fond of the <hi>Roman</hi> Government; what had <hi>Germany</hi> to do with <hi>Rome?</hi> But yet this kinde of doctrine muſt be inſtilled by degrees, and the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs cunningly carried, before a few firſt that may be truſted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Who is now ſo blinde, as not to ſee how this wicked Swiſs labors, to undermine all Monarchy, and to blow up the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire with his breath! And how craftily the buſineſs muſt be carried, <hi>Senſim &amp; paulatim,</hi> not openly and plainly, nor all at once, no by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94686:29"/>no means; <hi>Et coram auditoribus,</hi> pure doctrine for a Pulpit, a moſt rare Sermon to the people, who are moſt likely to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud it! I am already quite tired in the purſuit of this debaucht Satanical <hi>Swiſs,</hi> and tracing of his damnable doctrines of Rebellion; and I believe every prudent Reader will ſo be, or at leaſt reſt ſatisfied, with what is already produced, as all the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> may ſufficiently ſee, what they are to expect from him, and the whole brood of ſuch Reforming Brethren, Proteſtants of Integrity, when they are armed with power. <hi>Exit Zuinglius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now enter Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> and let us ſee, whether his reverence will prepare and diſpoſe the hearts of his diſciples to more obedience, humility, and patience, than this rough <hi>Swiſs</hi> aforeſaid hath done. Now as thoſe of the <hi>Swiſs</hi> race were called <hi>Zuinglians</hi> and <hi>Sacramentaries,</hi> by <hi>Luther;</hi> ſo the <hi>French</hi> named themſelves <hi>Hugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots,</hi> from one <hi>Hugo</hi> another Patriarch of theirs. So now all of that Sect have their title and denomination from <hi>Calvin,</hi> who as a Tranſcendent, hath overſhadowed and obſcured the glory and name of <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> and <hi>Hugo</hi> himſelf; and now forſooth they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94686:29"/>muſt be called Proteſtants of Integrity. For the deſcription of the life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of <hi>Calvin,</hi> of his nature, behavior, delicacy of diet, and phyſical Epicuriſm, I ſhall refer you to one that ſate long by him to draw his Picture <hi>vivis coloribus,</hi> and that is Dr. <hi>Jerome Bolſec,</hi> (one that was frequently converſant both with his pulſe, and humors) as his conſtant Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian; whoſe teſtimony is confirmed like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the learned <hi>Francis Baldwin,</hi> who concurreth with him in the portraicture of the man, and in the very colours. He was a famous Lawyer of <hi>Calvins</hi> own fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, and one that lived long with him, and knew full well what blood was nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in every vein of his body. The like is done by <hi>Florimond de Remond,</hi> a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of quality, <hi>Claudius de Saincts,</hi> and divers others, who have left us the lively image of him, and of his fine Companion and Fellow-laborer, Mr. <hi>Theodore Beza,</hi> his ſucceſſor in his Chair and Juriſdiction, an uſurping Parſon of another mans Pariſh, and an Husband of another mans wife, a greater friend to Love than Charity, to wit than Piety: But it is not my buſineſs now to meddle more with their vertues and lives, nor yet with their School Points
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94686:30"/>and Doctrines of Faith, which I ſhall leave to the examination of the more learned, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending onely to deliver to the world their Doctrines, Problems, and Paradoxes in points of State, and to demonſtrate to the world, how much their refined Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth derogate from the Royalty and Soveraign Authority of Chriſtian Kings and Princes; and how much it is more favorable to Democracy and Popular Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as more conſonant to their Conſiſtory and Elderſhip, whereby they have wrought ſuch horrid confuſions over the face of Chriſtendom, like true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of Integrity: And yet truly we may finde <hi>Calvin</hi> go as ſlily and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately to work as the other, and by certain degrees too, nor altogether ſo bluntly as the rude <hi>Swiſs</hi> before him did. Firſt, he goes about to commend Ariſtocracy, and labors to abuſe Monarchy to the height, and all that, to prefer the reputation of his. Conſiſtory and Sanhedrim, as you ſhall hear him ſpeak for himſelf in his artificial Inſtitutions. <hi>Non id quidem per ſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calv. Inſt. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi> v. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſed hominum vitio;</hi> mark his cunning, not that Ariſtocracy were naturally, and of it ſelf better (no by no means, things were not ripe for that yet) but through the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94686:30"/>Vices and Deficiencies of men; why this one would think to be pretty plauſible, but mark his reaſon, <hi>Quod rariſſimè contingit Reges ſibi moderari, deinde tanto acumine &amp; prudentia inſtructos eſſe ut unuſquiſque videat quantum ſatis eſt.</hi> So he makes it very rare and dainty, to finde a wiſe and temperate Prince, or almoſt impoſſible for a King to ſee ſufficiently into his affairs; and therefore concludes, <hi>Facit ergo homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num defectus, ut tutius ſit ac magis tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile plures tenere gubernacula.</hi> So his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon proceeds upon the defects of Princes, and maintains it to be more ſafe and tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, for many joyntly, than for one ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely to govern and command; and concludes with an ingenuous confeſſion, <hi>Atque ut libenter fatear, nullum eſſe guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationis genus iſto felicius;</hi> that no kinde of Government can be happier than that: Now the effects of that doctrine do moſt plainly appear by that Popular State, yet govern'd <hi>Ariſtocraticè,</hi> as <hi>Bodin</hi> very well obſerves, eſtabliſhed by him in the City of <hi>Geneva,</hi> after the ejection of the Biſhop, who was their lawful Prince, as his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors had long before him there enjoyed it, ſince <hi>Frederick</hi> the Firſt. So thoſe were the firſt fair fruits of the propagation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94686:31"/>of his Goſpel there, of Proteſtants of Integrity.</p>
            <p>Now after all this, to prevent that man ſhould object, That princes have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways grave and wiſe Counſellors about them, to adviſe with, and to inſpire them; and if they ſhould be ſo weak themſelves, as he imagines them to be, yet ſo their defects might be ſupplied, he gives this reſolution in his Comment upon <hi>Daniel, Kings</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>make choice of ſuch men for their Counſellors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. <hi>11.</hi> v. <hi>26.</hi> Dan.</note> 
               <hi>as can beſt fit their humors, and accommodate themſelves beſt to ſerve their beſtial luſts and appetites,</hi> inſtancing particularly in <hi>Cruelty, Fraud, and Rapine.</hi> So he makes Kings rather worſe than better for having Counſellors, and conſequently ſtaineth the honor and credit of a Counſellor, with a ſcandal and blemiſh intolerable.</p>
            <p>And yet a little further upon the ſame Book of <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 2 <hi>v.</hi> 39.</note> 
               <hi>They are</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſtrangely out of their wits, quite void of ſenſe and all underſtanding, who deſire to live in Soveraign Monarchies: for it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, but that order and policy ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay where one man holds ſo large an extent of Dominion.</hi> Nay, to make this impious propoſition ſeem good, he addes in the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94686:31"/>ſame Book thus. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 25.</note> 
               <hi>Kings</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>forget that they are men, that is of the ſame mold that others are: They are called Kings and Dukes,</hi> Dei gratiâ; <hi>to what end ſerve theſe words? to ſhew by their title that they acknowledge no other Superior; and yet they will tread upon God with their feet, under that cloak: So it is but a meer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, and blinde, to diſguiſe and conceal their wicked deſigns, when they vaunt that they raign</hi> Dei gratiâ. Is not this a moſt excellent doctrine to be preached in a Monarchy? and a very fine deſcant upon <hi>Dei gratiâ?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet he goeth a little further in the ſame Book. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>Kings</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>make their boast that they raign</hi> Dei gratiâ, <hi>yet they indeed deſpiſe the Majeſty of God,</hi> Voila quell eſt la rage &amp; forcenerve de tous Roys: That is to ſay, <hi>Obſerve here the rage, fury, and phrenſie,</hi> of all Kings, none excepted; and to make that good, he addeth this ſtrength to it, <hi>It is common and ordinary to all Kings, to exclude God from the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the World.</hi> May we not here truly ſay of him, and the reſt of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Brethren, <hi>Pluſquam regnare vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur quibus ita licet cenſuram agere Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantium?</hi> They are ſure, more than Kings,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94686:32"/>who thus imperiouſly dare paſs their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures upon Kings; and thus are Proteſtants of Integrity.</p>
            <p>But yet if you have a minde to hear <hi>John Calvin</hi> Preach more like a <hi>Switzer,</hi> and which you may think more ſtrange, to <hi>Lutheranize,</hi> with the proper ſpirit of brave <hi>Martin</hi> himſelf, See what he ſays further upon the ſame Book of <hi>Daniel. Darius</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>will by his example con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn all thoſe who at this day profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves either Catholick Kings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 25.</note> 
               <hi>or Chriſtian Kings, or Defenders of the Faith; and yet not onely do they deface, and bury all true Piety and Religion, but they corrupt and deprave the whole worſhip of God.</hi> This is not yet all neither; for in the ſame Chapter, he is bold to touch Kings a little more to the quick, and curiouſly deſcribes what kinde of Beaſts they are generally. <hi>Les Roys ſont preſque tous hebetez &amp; bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taux,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>auſſi ſemblablement ſont ils coment les chevaux &amp; les Aſnes de Beſtes brutes.</hi> Kings are for the moſt part ſtupid and brutiſh, nor liker any Brutes upon the Earth, than Hackney Jades and Aſſes: Fitting Titles for the Majeſty of Gods Anointed. At length to crown all that he hath ſaid or done in this point, he turns his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94686:32"/>tune to ſharps and menaces in this brave manner. <hi>Abdicant ſe poteſtate terreni Principes, dum inſurgunt contra Deum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>imo indigni ſunt qui cenſeantur in hominum numero: Potius ergo conſpuere oportet in illorum capita, quam illis parere ubi iſic proterviunt, ut velint ſpoliare Deum ſuo jure.</hi> Earthly Princes <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> deveſt themſelves of power, when they make an inſurrection againſt God; nay, they are unworthy to be reputed amongſt men; men had better therefore ſpit in their faces, then yield obedience to their commands, when they ſhall grow ſo inſolent, as to rob God of his right. Is not this a moſt rare and learned homily of obedience for Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and befitting Proteſtants of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity?</p>
            <p>By ſo much as hath been produced, it is evident, that <hi>Calvin</hi> was, at leaſt, a well-willer to the extirpation of Monarchy, though the affairs of the world were then in a little too good a compoſure for him to dare to adventure further at it. <hi>Exit Johannes Calvinus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now enter the <hi>Tibullus</hi> of <hi>Geneva,</hi> ſweet Mr. <hi>Theodore Beza,</hi> and by his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and practices, it will be more eaſily
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94686:33"/>made appear, that it was his Maſter <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vins,</hi> not onely opinion, but deſign, to make all the world dance the <hi>Geneva</hi> Jigg, and to propagate his godly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment throughout all Chriſtendom: For he was both his diſciple and companion, who ſoundly did underſtand his doctrine, and did as bravely ſecond him; ſo we know, that <hi>noſcitur ex ſocio, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now firſt in his Preface to the <hi>New Testament,</hi> dedicated to Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> 1564. <note place="margin">B z <hi>1</hi> Praeſ. in Nov. Teſtam. <hi>1564</hi>
               </note> he uſeth theſe words, <hi>Quo die, ſcilicet,</hi> 19 <hi>Decemb. ante biennium, Gallica Nobilitas (Illuſtriſſimo Principe Condaeo duce) tuis &amp; Illuſtriſsimorum quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundam Germaniae Principum, ſubſiaiis freta, non procul urbe Druidum, fortiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè Praeliata, prima reſtituendae in Galliis Chriſtianae Religionis fundamenta, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine ſuo feliciter conſecratunt, &amp;c.</hi> Here he ſpeaks, not onely as approving, but glorying in that famous battel that was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at <hi>Dreux,</hi> by the Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> and all the <hi>Hugonot</hi> Party, againſt the King; which act hath been by all indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent perſons, condemned as a moſt unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable Rebellion; yet brave <hi>Beza</hi> ſo boldly juſtifieth and magnifieth it, that in the ſame place commending the good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94686:33"/>at <hi>Meaux</hi> and <hi>Orleans,</hi> and that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous battel of <hi>Dreux,</hi> wherein he boaſts himſelf to have been a principal actor, not an acceſſory: He adds thus, <hi>Id quod liberius teſtor, quod iſtis tum conſiliis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Praef. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>tum etiam pleriſque rebus, quando ita Deo viſum eſt, interfui.</hi> This <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> I do more freely teſtifie, becauſe I was preſent at thoſe counſels, and moſt actions, when it pleaſed God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But to know this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman in his proper humor, and <hi>in puris naturalibus,</hi> read but his Poſitions, and Catechiſm of Sedition, the Practiſe of his Piety, <note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd. cont. Tyran. p. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> the Book called <hi>Vindiciae contra Tyrannos,</hi> where he acts the perfect part of <hi>Junius Brutus:</hi> And firſt, <hi>Page</hi> 15. he propounds this queſtion, <hi>If Subjects be bound to obey their Kings, when they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand againſt Gods Law?</hi> And then <hi>Page</hi> 22. he reſolveth, <hi>We muſt obey Kings for Gods cauſe, when they obey God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 22.</note> And then concludes <hi>Page</hi> 24. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>As the Vaſſal loſeth his life, if he commit felony; ſo the King loſeth his Right, and his Realm alſo, if he forſake God.</hi> But above all, the braveſt Maxime he produceth <hi>Page</hi> 65. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 65.</note> 
               <hi>That all conſpiracies are good or ill, as the end is at which they aim,</hi> which is a moſt diabolical principle, and capable to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94686:34"/>all the Rebels and Traytors in the World. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 66.</note> Yet <hi>Page</hi> 66. he goes a little further; <hi>The Magistrates</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and one part of the Realm, may reſiſt the King, being an Idolater; as</hi> Libna <hi>revolted from</hi> Joram, <hi>for forſaking of God.</hi> Here he gives all Rebels a <hi>ſic dicit Dominus,</hi> for their defence. But yet this is not all, he muſt fortifie his Axioms a little further, <hi>Page</hi> 132. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 132.</note> 
               <hi>The Government of a Kingdom</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is not given to the King alone, but alſo to the Officers of the Realm.</hi> And again, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 103.</note> 
               <hi>Page</hi> 103. <hi>France, Spain, and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are cuſtumarily conſecrated, and as it were put into their charge, by the States, Peers, and Lords, which repreſent the people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 199.</note> And <hi>Page</hi> 199. <hi>There is a ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation in Kingdoms hereditary, &amp;c.</hi> Now I would fain know, what can any Rebel ſay more? And upon theſe Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, what difference would there be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Crown of a King, and the <hi>la Beretta</hi> of the Duke of <hi>Venice?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot here forget, how irreverently this <hi>Euſebius Philadelphus,</hi> (for ſo Mr. <hi>Theodore Beza</hi> was pleaſed there to call himſelf) did uſe his own King <hi>Charles,</hi> in his Book entituled <hi>Reveille Martin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reveille Martin.</note> where he uſually calls the King Tyrant, and makes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94686:34"/>this Anagram <hi>Chaſſeur Deſloyal.</hi> Read his rimes and ſcandalous reproaches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Queen-Mother; peruſe the Forty Articles recorded in that Book, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Art.</hi> 40.</note> for the better advancement of Seditious and Rebellious Government; and in the laſt of them, they are obliged never to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm ſo long as Religion, as they call it, is purſued and perſecuted; that is, according to his meaning, ſo long as the King goes about to chaſtiſe their Rebellion.</p>
            <p>It were too much to trouble any inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Reader with all thoſe holy Articles of <hi>Bearne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Articles of <hi>Bearne.</hi>
               </note> 1574. coyned with Mr. <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dores</hi> own ſtamp, and communicated at <hi>Melun</hi> to all the <hi>Moſches</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> Church, that they might the more ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as they ſaid, make war againſt their enemies, till it pleaſed God to turn the heart of the <hi>French</hi> Tyrant. By all this it muſt be very evident, that <hi>Beza</hi> and his followers have cauſed all thoſe uproars and commotions in <hi>France,</hi> when he himſelf writing to <hi>Christopher Thretius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>40.</hi> Chriſtoph. Thretio.</note> ſpeaks his reſolution to fight it out to the very laſt. <hi>Ego quidem pacem nullam, niſi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellatis hoſtibus auſim ſperare;</hi> he could hope no peace, till the enemies were quite ſubdued. Now if you ask who were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94686:35"/>thoſe enemies, he quickly clears that, <hi>Cacolicorum caſtra trans Ligurim ſunt,</hi> meaning the Kings Army that were <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks; and ſaith a little before, <hi>Ab eo tempore noſtri (copiis feliciſsime inſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis) Tholoſanum agrum infeſtarunt, unde ad Rhodanum uſque progreſsi, occupatis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquot oppidis &amp; Arcibus, in quibus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidium reliquerunt:</hi> About that time our forces, with their recruits invaded and poſſeſt all about <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> and thence marched towards the <hi>Rhone,</hi> taking by the way Towns and Caſtles, wherein they had left Gariſons.</p>
            <p>Thus you may ſee, how theſe good men made no bones to diſturb the publick peace, to ſurprize the Kings Towns and Caſtles, and fortifie them againſt him, and to oppugne his forces, plunder his friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> like true Proteſtants of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity.</p>
            <p>I might here travel a great way further, and weary you with as good ſtuff out of the Book <hi>De jure Magiſtratus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. de jure Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratus.</note> a Bird of the ſame neſt; for if it was not <hi>Beza</hi>'s own, as moſt think it was, it muſt needs be <hi>Ottomans,</hi> one of his chief Comerades. But Dr. <hi>Sutcliff,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliff.</note> a Country-man of ours, and very near of the ſame Sect, confeſſeth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94686:35"/>the Book to be <hi>Beza</hi>'s and ſaith, that <hi>Beza</hi> in his Book <hi>De jure Magiſtratus,</hi> doth too much arm Subjects againſt their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and blameth him for going about to overthrow the Authority of all Chriſtian Kings and Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>To Dr. <hi>Sutcliff</hi> may be added, the judgment of the famous Lawyer, <note place="margin">Fr. Bald. Reſp. alt. ad Joh. Calv. p. <hi>74.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Baldwin,</hi> who had particularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſt with <hi>Galvin</hi> at <hi>Geneva,</hi> in his Book called <hi>Reſponſio altera ad</hi> Johannem Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinum, Paris 1562. Pag 74. <hi>Mirabar quor ſum evaderet inflammatus tuus quidam Apoſtolus</hi> (<hi>ſc. Mr.</hi> theodore Beza) <hi>qui cùm hic concionaretur, ſuis auditoribus vehementer commendabat extraordinarium illud exemplum Levitarum, ſtrictis gladiis per caſtra diſcurrentium, &amp; obvios quoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Idolloatras trucidantium: Sed nunc au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio te vix contentum eſſe talibus Levitis.</hi> And <hi>P.</hi> 128. <hi>Leviora</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſunt illa;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 128.</note> 
               <hi>cum ſtatuis, ſepulchris, &amp; oſsibus Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum ac Martyrum, Barbarum bellum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictum videmus, cum Civitates occupari, fana ſpoliari audimus, &amp;c.</hi> I wondered, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> what your fierce Apoſtle meant, and whether he would, (by name Mr. <hi>Theodore Beza</hi>) who when he preached here, did moſt extreamly recommend to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94686:36"/>his Auditory, that extraordinary example of the <hi>Levites,</hi> running through the Camp with their drawn Swords, and killing all the Idolaters they met withal; but now I hear that you are hardly contented with ſuch moderate <hi>Levites, &amp;c.</hi> And then in <hi>Pag.</hi> 128. Thoſe are ſmall matters <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> to what we hear and ſee now; a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous War is waged with the Statues, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres, and Bones of Kings and Princes; nay, and of Martyrs. Cities are ſeized on by force, Churches prophaned and ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Perfect pranks of Proteſtants of Integrity.</p>
            <p>And Dr. <hi>Sutcliff</hi> adds yet further, that that Book of <hi>Vindiciae contra Tyrannos,</hi> gives a power to Subjects, not onely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, but to kill their Kings, if they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne Gods Religion, of which, and all their other miſdemeanors, they muſt be the onely Judges, as it is fit they ſhould be. <hi>Sed Tranſant cum caeteris erroribus.</hi> I ſhall forbear to inſiſt any longer upon the Doctrines of theſe <hi>French</hi> Champions, which touch too roughly upon the String of Majeſty and Monarchy; for I fear I have ſaid more than enough already; but now to ſhew you that it is not onely a <hi>French</hi> diſeaſe, or accidental onely to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94686:36"/>
               <hi>Zuinglius, Calvin,</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> but that it is <hi>Morbus innatus</hi> in their Religion, called <hi>Proteſtancy of Integrity;</hi> and that <hi>Mali Corvi eſt malum Ovum,</hi> and an Egg ſtill of the old Cockatrice, we will paſs the Alps but of <hi>France</hi> into <hi>Germany,</hi> and there take up <hi>Bohemia,</hi> for the next Stage of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Tragedy. <hi>Exit Beza.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet before I enter the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Stage, I ſhall be bold to take the <hi>Palatinate</hi> in my way, an unfortunate Province of late, and which in a hundred years, hath changed its Religion five or ſix times; at whoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders we need not much marvel, if we read but <hi>Paraeus</hi> and <hi>Gracerus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paraeus Com. <hi>13.</hi> Rom.</note> 
               <hi>Paraeus</hi> in his Comment upon the Thirteenth of the <hi>Romans,</hi> teacheth plainly, That <hi>Subditi poſſunt ſuos Reges deponere, quando dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerant in Tyrannos, aut ſuos ſubditos cogunt ad Idololatriam,</hi> Subjects may depoſe their Kings, when they degenerate into Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, or preſs their Subjects to commit Idolatry; that is, if they go about to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh any other Religion beſides <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſm.</hi> After that, he is pleaſed to add another ground for the Excommunication, Depoſition and Deprivation of Kings, <hi>Quando praetextu Religionis quaerunt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94686:37"/>commoda.</hi> When under pretext of Religion, they ſeek to make out their own particular profit, which ſure had been a lecture not very plauſible to <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, nor his Inſtruments, nor in the Protectors ears after him: And ſurely, if a man ſhould ask, whether <hi>Murrey</hi> and <hi>Morton</hi> in <hi>Scotland?</hi> whether <hi>Orange</hi> and <hi>Horn</hi> in the <hi>Netherlands?</hi> whether the Admiral of <hi>France,</hi> and Prince of <hi>Conde</hi> himſelf? whether the Protector and Duke of <hi>Northumberland</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> had not their particular ends too? I believe we ſhall finde them Subject to them ſame cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. There is yet another Warrant that he is pleaſed to aſſign for the Depoſition of Princes, that muſt be forſooth, <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do gravant Conſcientias Subditorum,</hi> when they oppreſs the Conſciences of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. Then afterwards to ſhew his noble conſtancy in that opinion, is pleaſed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound his own opinion thus, <hi>Subditi ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus ſuperiorem Magiſtratum, ſe &amp; veram Religionem poſſunt etiam Armis jure Defendere, ſi aliter in Conſcientiis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>columes eſſe nequeant.</hi> Subjects may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully defend themſelves and the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by Arms againſt their Prince, if they cannot otherwiſe enjoy their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94686:37"/>So this is pretty well; <note place="margin">Idem Com. in Jud.</note> but yet he thinks fit to proceed a little further in his Commentaries upon the Book of <hi>Judges. Ma iſtratus minor poteſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere majorem.</hi> The inferior Magiſtrate may kill the ſuperior; and then explains his meaning in that caſe, <hi>Quod Tyranni domeſtici magis ſunt reprimendi.</hi> That Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick and Inteſtine Tyrants are rather to be repreſt; as if a man ſhould ſay, That Bailiffs, Sheriffs, and Perti-Conſtables, for Religion ſake, may kill Kings and Privy Counſellors, becauſe Tyrants within our doors are moſt to be feared, and ſooneſt to be cut off, upon the conſiderations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alledged. Yet <hi>Paraeus</hi> was not the onely Doctor that did impoyſon the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate</hi> with that infectious peſtilential doctrine; <note place="margin">Gracerus.</note> for <hi>Gracerus</hi> his Pew-fellow, taught the ſame things; <hi>Coercenda gladio eſt Antichriſti ambitio.</hi> That Antichriſtian ambition is to be cut off with the Sword; that is, all Princes and Prelates. And <hi>Aretius</hi> a Bird of the ſame Feather, <note place="margin">Aretius.</note> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boreth to ſtir up the people to hate the name and the authority, both of the Empire and the Emperor, with this divine Lecture, <hi>Draconem liquet dediſſe poteſtatem ſuam Imperio:</hi> It is plain, that the Devil erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94686:38"/>and authoriſed the Empire. Ask him his reaſon why, and he tells you, <hi>In Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio habitare plenitudinem diaboliſmi pro comperto eſt.</hi> For it is evident, that in the Empire dwelleth the fulneſs of deviliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but it is not onely <hi>Paraeus, Gracer,</hi> and <hi>Aretius</hi> that taught this doctrine; for it is and has been ſufficiently to be ſeen in the practice of their whole Church. <hi>Gieskenius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gieskenius.</note> a <hi>Lutheran,</hi> will tell you how they behaved themſelves at <hi>Emden. Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes illuſtrem dominum ſuum, mota ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, ferè tota ditione pepulerunt.</hi> 2. <hi>Pacti etiam ſunt, ne Illuſtriſſimus Comes habeat illius Religionis niſi Calviniſticae exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, ſubditis ſuis concedere Emdae.</hi> Firſt, they of <hi>Emden</hi> made a ſeditious tumult, and thruſt their Illuſtrious Lord almoſt out of all his Territory. Secondly, They covenanted, that the moſt Illuſtrious Count ſhould not have it in his power to tolerate any Religion, but that of St. <hi>Calvin,</hi> in any part of his dominion. And thirdly, They were graciouſly pleaſed to be ſo kinde to their Soveraign, <hi>Et tamen liceat ei habere in Aula ſua Concionatorem qui ſit Auguſtanae Confeſſionis.</hi> That for all that, he ſhould have the priviledge, if he pleaſed, in his own Court, to keep a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94686:38"/>Preacher that was of the <hi>Auguſtan</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. A very great favor indeed, and a high prerogative will doubtleſs accrue to Kings, when it ſhall be at the diſpoſition of Subjects to tolerate their Princes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and frame it for themſelves after their own cut; the Proteſtants of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity muſt direct their Governor, and he muſt obey.</p>
            <p>By theſe and ſuch like Firebrands was <hi>Bohemia</hi> put into a moſt miſerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion; the original and progreſs of which unfortunate Wars, the ſtories of <hi>Mercure Francois, Mercurius Gallob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lgicus,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others relate ſo amply, that I ſhall not need ſo much as touch upon them; and that the drift of all thoſe Riots, Uprores, and Rebellions in <hi>Germany,</hi> was onely for the ſetting up of this new no Religion, called now Proteſtants of Integrity.</p>
            <p>And firſt this will appear by <hi>Pag.</hi> 121. <note place="margin">Cancellari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a, p. <hi>121.</hi> Achatius â Donau.</note> of the <hi>Cancellaria,</hi> where <hi>Achatius â Donau</hi> writes to <hi>Anhalt,</hi> 15 <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1619. That the intention of <hi>Bethlehem Gabor</hi> and his correſpondents was <hi>pied a pied</hi> to extirpate the Antichriſtian Papacy; and as in the Articles of their Union, <hi>Art.</hi> 8. they declare unanimouſly, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Artic.</hi> 8.</note> That their intention was to extirpate Papiſm;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94686:39"/>which is as much to ſay in their ſenſe, All Monarchy and Prelacy: Nay, part of this ſenſe, <note place="margin">Bethlehem Gabor.</note> 
               <hi>Bethlehem Gabor</hi> himſelf ſpeaks plainly out in his own Letter to the Great <hi>Turk,</hi> That he muſt now labor <hi>ut raſa Pontiſiciorum Cohors è medio tollatur;</hi> that all the ſhaved heads may be quite cut off. <note place="margin">Anhalt.</note> And <hi>Anhalt</hi> made out the other part in his Letter to <hi>Donau,</hi> in <hi>May,</hi> 1619. That it were better the Turk or Devil ſhould be choſen and preferred to wear the Crown, than <hi>Ferdinand.</hi> Nay, <hi>Bethlehem Gabor</hi> himſelf by his Letters further cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies the Turk, that the <hi>Palatinate</hi> and <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> were reſolved no longer to endure <hi>Ferdinand;</hi> and that all thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces which were in their League, <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; toti Nationi Mahumeticae, corde &amp; anima omnia officia ſideliſſime praeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt;</hi> ſhould moſt faithfully perform from the bottom of their hearts and ſouls, all duty and allegiance to the Sacred Majeſty of the <hi>Sultan,</hi> and to all the noble Nation of the <hi>Mahumetans.</hi> Was not this a very holy League? were not the ends moſt charitable, and the means moſt Chriſtian? Were not theſe pure Proteſtants of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity?</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:94686:39"/>
            <p>This is that <hi>Bethlehem Gabor,</hi> who to hold himſelf in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urks good grace, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered unto him the Town and Fort of <hi>Lipp,</hi> and the Towns of <hi>Solymos, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nady, Margat,</hi> and <hi>Arad,</hi> all of them being places well fortified in <hi>Hungaria.</hi> Was not this done like a Proteſtant of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity?</p>
            <p>This is he that ſwore Allegiance to <hi>Gabriel Bathori</hi> his Soveraign Lord and Prince of <hi>Tranſylvania,</hi> afterwards moſt traiterouſly murthered him, and uſurped his ſtate. Was not this a perfect Proteſtant of Integrity?</p>
            <p>This is he who made a League with the Emperor <hi>Matthias,</hi> 1615. not to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing againſt the Liberties and Peace of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and afterwards practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the Rebells of that State, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded the Kingdom, and took upon him the Crown, 1620. Immediately baniſhed all the State Eccleſiaſtical, that he might feed his Soldiers with the ſpoyls of the Church, ſtill like a true Proteſtant of Integrity.</p>
            <p>This is that <hi>Bethlehem Gabor,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving entred <hi>Poſon,</hi> preſently prophaned the Cathedral Church of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> and ſpoiled it, and afterwards with his own
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94686:40"/>hand certified the Turk, that at laſt he had entered upon that worthy exploit; to which his Mahumetical holineſs had ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten encouraged him, that now he would with all might and main have at the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy; and ſeeing that they gloried ſo much to ſhave their Crowns, he would glory as much to cut off their heads. A proper undertaking for a Proteſtant of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity.</p>
            <p>Whereupon in <hi>June,</hi> after the Turk made peace with the <hi>Tartars,</hi> he promiſed to aſſiſt <hi>Gabor</hi> with Forty thouſand <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> at his need, to expedite that good and godly work. Pure Confederates with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of Integrity!</p>
            <p>Indeed there needs no other argument to convince and confound this accurſed League, but the bare ſubſcription of this Monſters name to it, as a principal in the Contract, whom the world muſt needs judge very unlike to be a fitting inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to advance the Croſs of Chriſt, and to reform Religion: Yet this was the man upon whoſe head the Union did agree to ſet the Crown of <hi>Hungary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I do wiſh, that the partial Reader would look upon <hi>Germany,</hi> and ſee the Picture of <hi>Troy</hi> on fire; ſee the image and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94686:40"/>horror of War, which we have already pretty well taſted of; and by the ſame means, and how well it would pleaſe them to ſee (which of late we were very near) the face of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middleſex, &amp;c.</hi> ſo disfigured with wounds, and deſolation; and they who are now moſt forward to blow the coals of diſcord and ſedition, and to inflame a State with fury and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver, may quake and tremble, when they ſhall conſider in what devaſtation all that beautiful Country of the Empire hath lain long mourning and groaning. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces about the <hi>Rhine,</hi> were wholly waſted and impoveriſhed by the Soldiers on both ſides, eſpecially <hi>Worms;</hi> all Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage was ſuſpended, Traffick decayed, Trades ceaſed, Taxes impoſed, new For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications ſtill charged the Countrey, Men were not maſters of their own Goods, and above a hundred thouſand men then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted to be ſlain. Theſe are the fruits of Civil Wars, which are bitter to them that taſte them, as I think we in <hi>England</hi> have done ſufficiently, if we do not yet long for more. And theſe are the very fruits and effects of <hi>Calviniſm</hi> it ſelf, if we can yet take warning of it, and not be longer deluded with the pitiful pretence of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94686:41"/>Proteſtancy of Integrity. For their juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying ſole Faith, can never juſtifie without it bring Charity in her boſom; and the true marks of Charity, bring Patience, Humility, Zeal, and Obedience, ſtrongly conjoyned in one link. Now the little Patience, Humility, or Obedience, that theſe new Evangeliſts, our Hot-ſpur Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of Integrity have ſhewed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince their Zeal to be counterfeit, and Faith to be fruitleſs. Could ever Charity have directed theſe godly <hi>Bethlemites</hi> to invade the Duke of <hi>Bavars</hi> Territories, if he refuſed to ſtand Neuter? Charity ſure did not counſel <hi>Anhalt</hi> in his Letters to <hi>Donau,</hi> 1619. Charity doth not uſe to direct Chriſtians to ſollicite the Turks aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance againſt their Emperors and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Nurſing Fathers of Gods Church, as <hi>Pag.</hi> 80. <hi>Cancellariae.</hi> Nor to ſet down ſuch Plots as they intended, <hi>Pag.</hi> 42. <hi>&amp;</hi> 32. <hi>&amp;</hi> 66. But theſe Minions of <hi>Geneva,</hi> now called <hi>Proteſtants of Integrity,</hi> bring Religion to plead in the defence of their Union; and that they endeavored onely to puniſh <hi>Ochoſias</hi> for conſulting with the Idol of <hi>Acharon,</hi> and to root out all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:94686:41"/>
            <p>Here indeed is the voice of <hi>Jacob,</hi> but the roughneſs of <hi>Eſau;</hi> words of Saints, but actions of Devils: All muſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently Idolatry and Superſtition that does not pleaſe their humor. Beſides, could they ſhew as good a warrant as <hi>Elias</hi> did? Did God call them, did God authorize them to deprive their Princes? <hi>Per me Reges regnant; By me Kings raign,</hi> was Gods own Propoſition; <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13</note> and St. <hi>Peters</hi> commands us to be ſubject to every hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane creature for God; whether to a King, as excelling, or to Rulers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I am ſure there is no ground for ſuch a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as to degrade and depoſe the King; and theſe Proteſtants of Integrity muſt needs finde St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in his Thirteenth Chapter to the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13 1.</note> to be of another Religion. <hi>Exeunt Paraeus, Gracerus, cum Bethlehem Gabore,</hi> with all his Proteſtants of diſloyalty; and enter ſome, if we can finde them of better of Integrity. So we change our Scene into the <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Cockatrice is now arrived in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Zealand,</hi> that horrible <hi>Akel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dama</hi> and Field of Blood, and the Theater of moſt tragical and lamentable ſtories.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94686:42"/>Now as you have heard the Axioms and Poſitions at large before, of thoſe grand Patriarchs of our pure Proteſtants of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity; ſo the practices and tyrannies of theſe their followers, are here beſt to be diſcovered; and above all the actions of their Conſpiracy in the Union of <hi>Utricht,</hi> were the moſt capital and infamous. A device it was, perfectly framed according to the rules of <hi>Junius Brutus,</hi> and in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their great Grand-father the <hi>Swiſs</hi> before ſpoken of, and of his ſanctified Cantons; which of it ſelf, is argument ſtrong enough to convince them of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, though they have been ever plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to march under the notion of Religion, and naming their War <hi>Bellum Sacrum,</hi> a Holy War. This Union was made by the States 1578. who ſeeing the fortunate proceedings of the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> and the whole courſe of the Malecoutents, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into a perpetual League, compriſed in Twenty Articles for their mutual ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and union, as they were pleaſed to term it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They of <hi>Holland, Zealand, Friezland,</hi> and <hi>Gilders,</hi> did joyn <hi>contra omnem vim, quae ſub praetextu nominis Regis aut Religionis inferretur.</hi> Againſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94686:42"/>all force that might be offered, under the pretence of the name of King, or of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>After that, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and they of <hi>Antwerp</hi> and <hi>Gaunt,</hi> came with him into the League, and ſubſcribed it the Fourteenth of <hi>February,</hi> 1579. The which was afterwards confirmed at the <hi>Hague,</hi> 20 <hi>July,</hi> 1581. And the ſcope of all this, was to abandon and expel the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and to depoſe him from his own dominion and inheritance. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon that, they eſtabliſhed an Edict, <hi>Que le Roy de Eſpagne eſt deſchen de la Seigneurie du Pais Bas:</hi> That the King of <hi>Spain</hi> was faln from his Soveraignty over the <hi>Low-Countreys.</hi> And to make it more authentical, they deviſed a form of Abjuration from the King, and a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Revocation and Diſpenſation of their former Promiſe and Oath of Obedience, in theſe words.</p>
            <p>J. W. N. <hi>Do ſwear, avow, and bind my ſelf to the Provinces united, to be loyal and faithful to them, and to aid them againſt the King of</hi> Spain, Coment un bon Vaſall du Pais Bas, <hi>as a good Subject of the Low-Countreys.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:94686:43"/>
            <p>And when they had taken that Oath, they broke all the Kings Seals, pulled down his Arms, ſeized and entred upon his Lands, Rents, Cuſtoms, and all other Hereditaments, and took the ſame into their own hands; and as abſolute Lords, they coyned money in their own names, placed and diſplaced Officers of the State, baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all the Kings Counſellors, publiſhed Edicts, poſſeſt the Church-Lands, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt all that were of another Religion, beſieged <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and uſed all the Marks and Notes of Soveraignty in their own names. Did not their Brethren here that were equal Proteſtants of Integrity, do juſt the ſame things in <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Reaſons they gave, why the King of <hi>Spain</hi> had forfeited his Title and Right, were theſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, The ſuppreſſing of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</item>
               <item>Secondly, For oppreſſing them with Tyranny.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, For abrogating their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and for holding them in Bondage and Servitude: For ſuch a Magiſtrate <hi>(they ſaid)</hi> they are not bound to obey, (and ſo indeed are, as we have ſeen, the rules of their Religion) but to eject him as a Tyrant.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:94686:43"/>
            <p>Were not theſe the very Reaſons that our Proteſtants of Rebellion in <hi>England,</hi> uſed againſt our moſt glorious good King <hi>Charles,</hi> to wage War againſt him, and afterwards to murther him? Believe it, theſe were examples and preſidents of moſt dangerous conſequence, and which not a little concern all Princes to look well to; for if Subjects may depoſe their Princes, and make themſelves Judges, when they ſhall ſo forfeit their Crowns and Dignities; <hi>Qui ſtat, videat ne cadat.</hi> He that ſtands, let him take heed leaſt he fall. Kings had need to make their Seat ſecure, and to ſit faſt if they can; for theſe men make Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy itſelf but a very ſlippery hold: And indeed, Ambition and Treaſon can never finde a fitter cloak for their wearing, than that which is made of the <hi>Holland</hi> faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the Religion of theſe Proteſtants of Integrity.</p>
            <p>Now that you ſhould the better judge of the particular quarrel of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and their Confederates, I ſhould give you the whole ſtory of that Rebellion; but it is too long to recite; I refer every ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reader to their own Annals, which will convince them of the horrideft Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy from, and Rebellion againſt both
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94686:44"/>King and Church, that was ever ſeen in the world before, nor can ever be matched, but by that of our Proteſtants of Integrity here in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is moſt true, that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan their Rebellion with <hi>Lutheraniſm;</hi> but that being too hot to hold, the gentle ſtuff of <hi>Calviniſm</hi> forſooth muſt be brought in, which carried within it, as it does every where, its curſed Quickſilver; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once admitted, made the fire ever after to be moſt unquenchable.</p>
            <p>Thus did the flame burſt out, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as in ſpight of all Laws, begun to mutiny, broke down the Kings Arms, and grew ſo wilde, as in a rage they pulled down Images, robbed Churches, rifled Monaſteries, and contemned all Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates that ſought to appeaſe the troubles. And upon what grounds did they do all this? Bleſſed St. <hi>Calvin</hi> gave them a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, which they have not been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to urge for their apology. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lih.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 13, 21.</note> 
               <hi>A man,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>once illuminated with the truth, Simul vinculis omnibus obediendi legibus &amp; Eccleſiae ſolutus eſt.</hi> That is, he that hath once perfect knowledge of their Goſpel, is preſently abſolved from all Laws, and Oaths of Obedience to the King or Church.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:94686:44"/>
            <p>Is not this a bleſſed Leſſon? are not theſe holy Evangeliſts? It is here worth noting how a certain <hi>Hollander</hi> in his third Defence of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> calleth the King of <hi>Spain, Raptorem &amp; Haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum notorium,</hi> moſt inſolently; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he infers, <hi>Annon potius Regem Hiſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae, quia Haereticus notorius eſt, ex ſuo Regno, omnibus omnium Evangelicorum viribus expellere oporteret?</hi> Thus Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming it the duty of all good Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts to expel the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> with all their might and main out of his Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, becauſe he was a robber and a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Heretick.</p>
            <p>Does not this man look like one of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilines</hi> Religion, though cloaked with this new Goſpel and pretended Proteſtancy of Integrity?</p>
            <p>Now that this was down-right Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, under that ſpecious pretext of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, their own Countryman, if they will be pleaſed to ſtudy him, <note place="margin">Honderius in Prax. Criminal. cap. <hi>132.</hi>
               </note> one <hi>Honderius</hi> ſheweth at large, and indeed has drawn up their Proceſs: <hi>Seditioſi ſunt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>qui movent conſpirationem adverſus Recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res &amp; Adminiſtratores Regnorum, vel illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citas Congregationes populi cogunt, cives Commotionibus turbant, &amp;c.</hi> They are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94686:45"/>guilty of Sedition, who contrive any thing, or conſpire againſt Governors or Deputies of Kingdoms, or make any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Meetings, or trouble Citizens with Commotions.</p>
            <p>Now what is all this, compared with their dealings againſt <hi>Alva, Don Juan,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Parma?</hi> with their many Meetings at <hi>Breda,</hi> and <hi>Oſterweal;</hi> with their incenſing and encouraging the <hi>Geuz;</hi> with their defence of <hi>Harlem</hi> and <hi>Alcmar.</hi> Are not thoſe Actions good Comments upon their Law, and clear againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? But in another Chapter he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to declare the conditions of a juſt War.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Ut Bella ſint just a,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> c. <hi>82.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>requiritur ut juſta ſit cauſa.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Recta intentio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Perſonarum idoneitas.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Autoritas Principum, ſine qua eſt laeſa Majeſtas.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, A juſt Cauſe is requiſite.</item>
               <item>Secondly, A right Intention.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, A rightful capacity of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And laſtly, The Authority of the Prince, without which, to take up arms is Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:94686:45"/>
            <p>Now if the States do but mark that <hi>ſine quâ,</hi> they may well hold down their heads, and bluſh for ſhame of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Rebellion. For in all their wars they neither had juſt cauſe, nor yet good colour of a cauſe. They were ſecured for their Religion by the Pacification of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> by the Perpetual Edict, and by the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Treaty at <hi>Colen;</hi> by which they were to enjoy all without diſturbance, and yet would not they joyn with the States General to accept the ſame.</p>
            <p>Neither could there be <hi>recta intentio;</hi> for it was onely to nouriſh diſcord and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience againſt their Prince. It is true, they pretended ever Religion, and the peoples ſafety, as all Rebels uſe to do; but it is as true, that they likewiſe proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the common ends of other Rebels; not for the love of them, nor their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but his own private ends and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation. Ambition and Diſpair were his principal Motives and Counſellors, and a Revenge upon, and Diſpoſſeſſing the King of his Soveraignty, were his perfect ends; and poor Religion his beloved Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancy of Integrity, ſerved him but as a meer ſtalking-horſe to all thoſe.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:94686:46"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Claudius le Brun in P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ax. Civ. &amp; Crim.</note>Beſides, let us but conſider what <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius le Brun</hi> lays down in his Book of <hi>Proceſs,</hi> both Civil and Criminal, who addeth, That whoſoever ſurprizeth Towns, Caſtles, or Forts, without order of his Soveraign, (as the Count <hi>de Lumay</hi> did in <hi>Holland,</hi> and <hi>Voret,</hi> and <hi>Barland</hi> did at <hi>Fluſhing</hi> in <hi>Zealand,</hi>) whereby the peace of the Country is broken: Or, who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempteth againſt the life of his Soveraign or his Lieutenant, is guilty of Treaſon.</p>
            <p>Now theſe Maximes all <hi>Europe</hi> hath ever held as Judgments and Decrees of eternal Reaſon, and inviolable Principles of State which are never to be called in queſtion. And if the States of <hi>Holland</hi> do not obſerve, hold, and practice the ſame, they can never expect peace at home, nor any order and obedience in any of their Dominions.</p>
            <p>By this it is manifeſt, That as in the beginning theſe <hi>Hollanders</hi> are juſtly to be charged with Sedition; ſo in their progreſs they ſtand guilty of Treaſon and Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And then being ſo convinced Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors by Law, is it not now a little wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that they ſhould become High and Mighty Lords by Law? I am ſure it is more by luck than cunning, that they have
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:94686:46"/>made themſelves ſo; and it may prove a good encouragement to their own Soldiers (if men can ſo win Dignities by Offences) to ſhare the Towns in <hi>Holland</hi> amongſt themſelves, or to induce them to a <hi>Bellum Pyraticum</hi> or <hi>Sociale,</hi> a ſmart and quick war amongſt themſelves, and to Cantonize that Province by their own <hi>Hogen Mogens</hi> example.</p>
            <p>Now that I call all in this Religious Rebellion <hi>Hollanders,</hi> I do it for divers reaſons. Firſt, For that they were the moſt notorious leading Cards; and for the Matter of Religion at the making of their Union, they made themſelves Heads, and Supream Governors of the Church and Religion, by theſe words; <hi>Quant au point de Religion ceux d'Hollande &amp; de Zealande s'y comporteront come, bon leur ſemblera, &amp; les autres ſelon les Placards de l' Archiduke Mathias.</hi> As to matter of Religion, they of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand</hi> might diſpoſe themſelves as they pleaſed; but all the reſt were to conform to the Archduke <hi>Mathias.</hi> So by this the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zealand</hi> got the ſtart, and mounting the Tribunal, did advance them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Heads of the Church in thoſe Provinces; for all Eccleſiaſtical Matters
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94686:47"/>muſt be, <hi>Come bon leur ſemblera.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They are now the <hi>Regula Lesbia,</hi> to ſquare, judge, direct, govern and order all things in Religion; and what they ſhall follow, muſt paſs for currant, and in that manner, and for ſo long time as they ſhall pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Thus did the Cockatrice play his game, and got footing for his beloved Children, theſe Proteſtants of integrity, in that concave Country.</p>
            <p>Now as for their pretended Priviledges, it is plain, That the King did never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to make them void; ſo they have built themſelves upon moſt falſe grounds, which ſome time or other, muſt of neceſſity fail them. And yet I would ask of them, if it had been ſo great an offence for the King to go about to abrogate their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges? is it not a greater offence for Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to uſurp his? Is it not pretty for them ſo to make themſelves Parties and Judges, and by their own authority to puniſh their Prince? Which (if it had not been backed and exactly copied out by our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants of Integrity) had been an inſolency and indignity incredible to all Poſterity; and ſuch, as neither the <hi>Swi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zers,</hi> nor the <hi>Amphictiones</hi> (the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:94686:47"/>
               <hi>Cantons</hi> of <hi>Grecia</hi>) did ever pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel, or come near. For ſo they make Monarchy to be a wilde kinde of hold, Kingdoms to be <hi>occupantium jus; qui poteſt rapere capiat,</hi> the ſtrongeſt take all, catch as catch can. A preſumption oppoſite to all Laws, and a portal to let in all confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ruine: But if the King ſhould, as they would have him, forfeit and loſe all his Authority and Juriſdiction; yet I ſee not why or how, they could alſo chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge his Lands, and private Inheritance, for that muſt needs deſcend by Law. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if the King could forfeit his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, how can he forfeit it to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects? It is true, a Subject may make himſelf <hi>Civem alienae Reipubicae,</hi> a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of another State, or ſubject himſelf to another Prince: But if he ſtay in his own Countrey, he cannot of a Subject, make himſelf no Subject, (for though he do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, as the <hi>Hollanders</hi> did, yet he is ſtill a Subject;) but it is more admirable, how of a Subject, he ſhould become a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign; that is indeed, <hi>ſcientia ſcientiarum,</hi> a very ſupernatural skill, and far exceeding my capacity.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:94686:48"/>
            <p>As for the grievous Exactions they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of; <hi>videlicet,</hi> Of the tenth peny im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Duke of <hi>Alva:</hi> It will be neceſſary here to draw the Curtains, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they labor to ſhadow and obſcure the truth. Extream neceſſity and not his own will, forced <hi>Alva</hi> to exact that, which neither he would have done, nor the King have ſuffered, if poſſibly to be avoided; but being driven to a ſad ſtrait, for ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the Soldiers, who always grow wilde without pay; and ſo to avoid a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er miſchief as he thought, he was forced to incur that inconvenience.</p>
            <p>At this time, ſome of the Counſel in <hi>England,</hi> in the Queens name, ſeized in <hi>Hampſhire</hi> Six hundred thouſand Duckets, ſent from <hi>Spain</hi> to pay the Army, without any charge at all to the Countrey. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the King of <hi>Spain</hi> had ſent the Duke of <hi>Medina,</hi> a man of a milder na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to ſucceed <hi>Alva</hi> (who partly by misfortune, partly by his ſternneſs, partly by ſome errors, but moſt of all by ſome Foreign Princes disfavors, was grown odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) who brought with him Two hundred thouſand Duckets, which the <hi>Zealanders</hi> intercepted upon the Seas; and ſo was <hi>Alva</hi> by theſe means further plunged and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:94686:48"/>perplexed. But hereby it appears plainly, That it was neither the Kings pleaſure nor purpoſe (who intended ſo largely and liberally to furniſh thoſe Countreys;) but the extremity of his preſent wants which compelled <hi>Alva</hi> to thoſe Demands and Exactions: And ſo it was rather an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſcandal and offence, reflected up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the King and <hi>Alva,</hi> than deſerved by either, and a quarrel rather made and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived, than given.</p>
            <p>But now theſe popular Orators that plead ſo earneſtly for the eaſe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and ſeem ſo careful to procure the Exoneration of the Impoſitions and Taxes laid upon the people: Why do they not now inveigh as much againſt theſe new <hi>Magnifico</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, now <hi>Hogen Mogen</hi> Lords of <hi>Holland,</hi> who are ſo far from laying down and diminiſhing the Subſidies and Exciſes there, that they have raiſed and augmented them in ſuch ſort, as at this day no King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or Commonwealth in Chriſtendom, groaneth under the like burthens. And it cannot be yet forgotten, how the Gentle Father of the people, as they call him, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> did propound and labor to wreſt and wring from them of <hi>Holland,</hi> the ſixth peny towards his charge and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:94686:49"/>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1584. I could ſhew you an endeavor to raiſe the ſixth peny upon the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> a ſtrain far higher than the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi>'s; <hi>ſed tranſeat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now one thing I muſt not paſs by, for it will illuſtrate all the reſt. <hi>Weſt-Friezland</hi> in the beginning of their Rebellion, did ſcarce contribute <hi>Denis octies centena millia Florenorum,</hi> and now they are charged to pay <hi>Quadragies centena millia librarum &amp; dues milliones.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Barnevelt in Apol.</note> I uſe <hi>Barnevelts</hi> own words in his Apology, becauſe I would not be challenged for miſtaking them: Whereas they paid before but Eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand Florins, they are taxed to pay Forty hundred thouſand Libers, and two Millions, which makes a pretty differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Who is therefore now the Grand Tyrant or Exactor? Though the people have changed their Lord, they are not at all eaſed of their oppreſſion; and where before they complained they had one, now are they ſubject to the command of many Tyrants, who fleece them to the purpoſe, nay unskin them daily. If <hi>Alva</hi> beat them with whips, I am ſure theſe new States chaſtiſe them with Scorpions.</p>
            <p>Examine but their Excizes and Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, how they are increaſt upon Meat,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:94686:49"/>Drink, Fewel, Men, Servants wages, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Loans, and Benevolencies, and you will finde that they have well leapt out of the Frying-pan into the fire.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hen. Cnic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins.</note> 
               <hi>Henry Cnickins</hi> chargeth them to exact the fourth part of their Revenues that are <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and live out of their Country; <hi>Si in Provinciis noſtris veniâ eorum, degunt, ſemiſſem jubet ſolvere; ſi ſecus, bonis exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, &amp;c. Sed de his hactenus.</hi> For theſe and ſuch like frivolcus pretences muſt they have (as all theſe Proteſtants of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity ever had) that intend Rebellion; but when they come to be ballanced in the Scales of Right Reaſon, and are found too light, and all their ſpecious Allegations not to hold water, Religion muſt be the maſter-piece to play the prize by, and a cloak that will never fail to cover knavery. So <hi>Exeunt Hogen Mogen Proteſtants of Integrity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Religious Cockatrice having with ſo much ſucceſs and applauſe plaid over his Evangelical game in the <hi>Low Countreys,</hi> ſets his <hi>Pſeudo</hi> Apoſtolical face a little more Northward, directly pointing at our <hi>Britiſh Iſlands</hi> for his next Rendezvous;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:94686:50"/>and the moſt Northern corner of all them too, he was pleaſed to chuſe out to receive the principal honor of his firſt arrival. Now we may well know aforehand, what we are to expect <hi>ab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>quilone;</hi> ſo then enter true <hi>Iſraelites</hi> indeed, our gydd and godly Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that no doubt will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove themſelves and all their Bearns to be legitimate Proteſtants of Integrity; for God forbid, there ſhould be any Baſtards in <hi>Scotland.</hi> Indeed it is not to be denied, how eminently they ever did, and do ſtill <hi>patrizare,</hi> though one would have thought that the fiery zeal of theſe Serpentine <hi>Geneva Rabbins,</hi> would have been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what qualified in a colder climate, and proceeded with better temper.</p>
            <p>Now if we look upon the Primary and and Principal Authors and Actors of the Alterations and Tumults in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the firſt and deareſt beloved brood of the Cockatrice, we ſhall finde them ſure, as violent as Whirlwinds, blowing down with their breath, all that ever ſtood in their way, even Royalty, and the very Crown ir ſelf.</p>
            <p>The Principal Inſtruments, and as it were <hi>Legati à Latere,</hi> from his Holineſs Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> for this great work, were <hi>John
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:94686:50"/>Knox, Goodman, Gilby,</hi> and <hi>Buchanan,</hi> who were bravely ſeconded by <hi>Mais, David Ferguſſon</hi> a Learned Shoomaker, and Miniſter of <hi>Dundee;</hi> as alſo Mr. <hi>Coverdale, Willax, Rous, Harriot,</hi> and <hi>Mongomery, Victrix Legio &amp; Novatores ſtrenni,</hi> a conquering Legion of the right Cockatrice kinde, ſtout Innovators and pure Proteſtants of Integrity. Not all Writers of Books, but all of them Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters (forſooth) of the new Goſpel; and ſuch rare Salt-Petermen as were fit for Fire-works, and to prepare Matter to blow up both Church and State of any Nation. What a pretty Gentleman <hi>Knox</hi> was, and how well conditioned, his Country-man <hi>Langey</hi> can amply tell you, who hath writ at large of his vertues. For <hi>Buchanan,</hi> he was ever known to be a rude and ſlovenly <hi>Swits,</hi> of a preſumptuous audacity, and a factious nature, and one of thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of Integrity, that in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> in the time of King <hi>James</hi> the Fifth, did ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly in <hi>Lent,</hi> eat the <hi>Paſchal Lamb;</hi> and being convicted of that <hi>Judaiſm</hi> (which the King himſelf ſate to examine) his Partners and Colleagues in Religion were there condemned and burnt for that Hereſie; he with ſome of his aſſociates
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:94686:51"/>eſcaped, and fled over into other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, as men reſerved to be further Plagues to their own. But by their Godly Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rems likewiſe, and Doctrinal Maxims, you ſhall be better able to diſcern them, and finde them extraordinary Doctors of Loyalty, pure Proteſtants of Integrity, and ſcarcely matchable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <note place="margin">Knox in lib. ad No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitat. &amp; Pop. Scot.</note> Gentle Mr. <hi>Knox</hi> in his Pook to the Nobility of <hi>Scotland,</hi> begins thus to inſtruct them. <hi>Neque promiſſum, neque juromentum obligare poteſt populum, ut obediat &amp; auxilietur Tyrannis contra Deum:</hi> No promiſe nor oath whatſoever can oblige the people to obey and help Tyrants againſt God. And in his Hiſtory of <hi>Scotland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. in Hiſt. Scot. pag. <hi>372.</hi>
               </note> he expreſly aſſums, <hi>That Princes may be depoſed by the people, if they prove Tyrants, and act againſt God and his truth; and in ſuch caſes all Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects are free from their oaths of Allegiance and Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Fellow <hi>Goodman</hi> alſo ſings the ſame note in his Book of <hi>Obedience,</hi> and that out of <hi>Exod.</hi> 17. <note place="margin">Goodman in lib. de Obed. in Exod. <hi>17</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Toti populo,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>hoc orus incumbit ut animadvertat in Idolola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram quemcunque; nemo excipitur ſive Rex, ſive Regina, ſive Imperator.</hi> It is a duty incumbent upon all people, ſeverely
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:94686:51"/>to proſecute all Idolaters; none is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted; neither King, Queen, nor Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror. A brave Homily to the people, to teach them how to puniſh their Princes; then he proceeds to ſhew how, and by what order that is to be done. <hi>This is Gods Commandment,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to the people; Ui in ſimili defectione Rectores ſuos, qui à Deo ipſos abduc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt, ad furcas abripiant &amp; ſuſpendant; that in caſe of ſuch a defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they ſeize upon their Princes who would ſeduce them from God, and carry them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to the Gallows, and hang them up.</hi> Is not this a rare Juſticiary over Kings?</p>
            <p>Nor is their fine Companion <hi>Buchanan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Buchan. de jure Reg. Scot. p. <hi>61.</hi>
               </note> in his Book <hi>De jure Regni Scotiae,</hi> a jot behinde theſe two gallant Fathers of the people, in his wholſome counſels to them. <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the people are above the King, and of greater authority; they have right to beſtow the Crown as they pleaſe; they may arraign their Princes, and depoſe them: To them it appertains to make Laws, and to Princes to execute them.</hi> Sure our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of Integrity here in <hi>England</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this Leſſon perfectly; we ſee they have followed it exactly: Yet this was the great <hi>Solomon</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and well choſen, if you mark it, to inſtruct his King as a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:94686:52"/>Tutor; but fitter far to infect the people as a Preacher.</p>
            <p>But if you will yet have a little pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, you ſhall hear theſe Godly Men ſpeak their ſenſe more plainly.</p>
            <p>And firſt, <note place="margin">Knox, ſol. <hi>372.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Knox</hi> tells us plainly, <hi>That it were very good, that rewards were pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly appointed by the people for ſuch as kill Tyrants, as well as for thoſe that kill Wolves, and other Beaſts of prey.</hi> But brave <hi>Buchanan</hi> enlargeth upon this point a little further in a learned Diaglogue of his, <note place="margin">Buchan. in Dial.</note> wherein he ſhews abundantly both his excellent Divinity and Humanity. <hi>They hold,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that Kings muſt be obeyed, good or bad; but it is no better than blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy ſo to ſay. It is true, That God oft placeth evil Kings to puniſh the people; and it is as true, That he often appoints private men to kill them. But in the firſt to</hi> Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, <hi>we are commanded to pray for Princes; yea, ſo we are alſo to pray for Thieves.</hi> Is not this rare? Yet again he muſt have the other firk at the coat of Kings. <hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) Paul <hi>commands obedience to Kings;</hi> he anſwers, <hi>Yea, it is true,</hi> Paul <hi>did ſo in his nonage of Chriſtianity, and in the infancy of the Church; but if he had lived now, he would have writ and ſaid far otherwiſe:</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:94686:52"/>As if the time wherein <hi>Buchanan</hi> lived, had been more enlightned with the Spirit, than that of the Apoſtles; and that he himſelf were inriched with a greater ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Holy Ghoſt, and had a more ripe and ſolid judgment than poor <hi>Paul</hi> could poſſibly comprehend.</p>
            <p>Thus are the people cloſely armed to kill Kings under the notion of Tyrants, by the Zeal of Gods Church and Truth, and the Light of the Goſpel; as by the Sword of <hi>Gideon,</hi> and the Arms of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith,</hi> which muſt be drawn and directed by the people, even againſt their Kings.</p>
            <p>Now that theſe impious Paradoxes be the Doctrines not of one <hi>Goodman,</hi> nor one <hi>Knox,</hi> or one <hi>Buchanan,</hi> but of the whole Congregation of thoſe Proteſtants of Integrity, is to be ſeen by their holy <hi>Geneva</hi> Bible, <note place="margin">Bib. Genev. <hi>2</hi> Chron. c. <hi>5.</hi> v. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> admitted by their whole Kirk, wherein their Notes upon the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Chronicles</hi> ſhew, That they allow the depoſing of Queen <hi>Maacha,</hi> by her ſon <hi>Aſa,</hi> for Idolatry, and yet reprehend him for want of zeal, that he did not put her to death by fire. The like Axioms ſure are not allowed at <hi>Doway,</hi> nor the like Notes to be found in the <hi>Rhemiſh Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> But yet the practice and execution
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:94686:53"/>of theſe poyſonous Poſitions and Doctrines is much worſe than the pronouncing of their bare Decrees. <note place="margin">Leſs. l. <hi>10.</hi> Hiſt. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Leſſaeus,</hi> the learned Biſhop of <hi>Roſs,</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Eo Knoxii pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupit audacia, ut publice Nobiles pro con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cione perſtrinxerit, quod Jeſabelem ex medio non ſuſtulerunt. Knox</hi> grew to that heighth of impudence, as publickly in a Sermon, to rebuke the Nobles of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that they did not put their Queen that <hi>Jeſabel</hi> to death; and yet theſe are all but words: But obſerve how ſpeedily blows followed; For all the Hiſtories of <hi>Scotland</hi> do ſufficiently teſtifie, That their firſt act of Reformation of Religion, as they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it, or Eſtabliſhment of their Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of Integrity, was the ſurprizing the Caſtle of St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> without Warrant or Commiſſion; then the murthering of Cardinal <hi>Belua,</hi> 1546. And from thence proceeded to the Depoſition of their own moſt Gracious. Virtuous, and Religious Queen, our Kings Great Grand-Mother, and afterwards purſued her to her murther here in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which practices were ſufficiently furthered by the reſt of their Reforming Brethren abroad, <note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>za in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>78.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Buchanan.</note> the Prime Proteſtants of Integrity, as appears by <hi>Beza</hi> in his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:94686:53"/>Letter to <hi>Buchanan,</hi> provoking him to thoſe Barbarous and Satanical Treaſons, by his bitter railings againſt that beſt of Queens, calling her <hi>Medea</hi> and <hi>Athalia,</hi> and ſaying with his foul mouth, that <hi>Nullum illius ſceleribus idoneum nomen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venio;</hi> That he could not finde out words to expreſs, or names to ſet out her wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and a great deal more in his <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ille Matin;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reveille Matin.</note> and onely becauſe ſhe was not (forſooth) a Proteſtant of Integrity. Nay King <hi>James</hi> of bleſſed memory him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, her ſon, and our Soveraigns Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, had much ado to ſcape their hands, though but in his Cradle, as he was pleaſed frequently to acknowledge, and ſo openly, that it could not paſs the obſervation of learned men abroad, eſpecially one <hi>Johu Schuts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh. Schuts</hi> his obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of K. <hi>James.</hi>
               </note> a <hi>Lutheran,</hi> who repeats the Kings words thus; <hi>Ab illis ego non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lùm â nativitate continuò vexatus fui, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum etiam abipſo matris utero propemodum extinctus, antequam in lucem editus ſum.</hi> I have not been onely vext and perſecuted by this kinde of people from my Cradle and Infancy, but alſo from my very Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers womb, and was almoſt by them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed before I could ſee light. But we know better ſure here in <hi>England,</hi> than
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:94686:54"/>any <hi>Lutheran</hi> abroad could poſſibly, how that great, moſt judicious and knowing King was ſatified in their Religious rogue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and what he thought of them to his dying day; and the warning he gave his moſt vertuous ſon upon his death-bed, to beware of them: Which how well he did obſerve, I know not; but this I am ſure of, That they were the principal movers of all his, and his Kingdoms troubles, and the curſed hands that joyned with the Engliſh Proteſtants of Integrity here, to work his final ruine. <hi>Sed tranſeat cum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquiis erroribus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now here before I proceed any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I muſt be bold to make a ſtand, and ſadly intermix the water of my eyes with my mourning and ſorrowful Ink, and with a black diſtempered Pen, deplore the madneſs of thoſe malicious men, who were the firſt engagers of us in our late unnatural Wars.</p>
            <p>Ah poor <hi>England,</hi> Paradiſe of the Earth, Eye of the World, Pearl of all Beauties! How many times by the means of theſe Infernal Spirits, Spawn of the Cockatrice, <hi>Proteſtants of Integrity,</hi> haſt thou ſeen thy fruitful boſom, heretofore crowned
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:94686:54"/>with Ears of Corn, and Guilded with Harveſts, all briſtled over with <hi>Battalia</hi>'s? How many times haſt thou ſeen thy Land covered with Swords, and thy Seas with Ships? How many times haſt thou felt the arms of thy Children encountring within thy proper Entrails? How many times haſt thou ſeen flames of Brothers hoſtility flying through thy fat and fragrant Fields? When haſt thou not ſweat in all the parts of thy beautiful body? When have not Rivers of Blood been drawn from thy Veins, and ſuch Blood as would have ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the beſt Bulwarks for thy beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, againſt all foreign enemies what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; and if well employed, had made the great enemy of Chriſtendom, the <hi>Turk,</hi> ere this to tremble at thy Standards, and have replanted again the beautiful Plains of <hi>Paleſtine?</hi> But all hath been ſacrificed to ſuch Religious Furies.</p>
            <p>Nor could theſe ſacred Blood-Leeches yet reſt ſatisfied, till they had embrued their hands, and made their hearts drunk with His, whoſe every drop was worth a whole Ocean of ours. Murther they muſt, the moſt Religious and Clement Monarch of the Univerſe; a Prince wiſe as <hi>Apollo,</hi> Valiant as <hi>Achilles,</hi> Vertuous as <hi>Socrates,</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:94686:55"/>Pious as <hi>Aeneas,</hi> and Beautiful as an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazon,</hi> muſt paſs away as a Pearl parcht up with Lightning, and leave his Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Head upon a Scaffold as a ſacrifice to theſe Religious Monſters of Mankinde: An action ſo dire and dreadful, a Tyranny ſo barbarous, that no voice or pen can ere be able to expreſs it; it makes the hair ſtand an end on the heads of all good men ſo much as to think upon it; nay nothing but a ſtile of fire, or pen of Adamant ſteeped in blood, is capable to declare it. And certainly, (as it was ſaid of <hi>Sylla</hi>) <hi>If that Mercy her ſelf had come upon the Earth in humane ſhape, they would have murthered her.</hi> Are you not yet aſhamed of your ingratitude, you children of the <hi>Scotiſh Belial?</hi> Had you had one drop of true <hi>Engliſh</hi> blood in your bodies, you would have been readier to ſpend that for Him, than to take His from Him.</p>
            <p>What, you would have been all Kings? We remember indeed too lately, that you were ſo, and would have a perpetual ſeat in <hi>Parliament,</hi> as you once thought you had got. And truly, it is great pity but it were ſo again, eſpecially being ſo good Patriots, as you have been? I wonder tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that then you did not vote your ſelves
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:94686:55"/>to be immortal too! So you might have been too hard for <hi>Dun,</hi> and the Devil himſelf.</p>
            <p>Let any temperate and knowing man in <hi>England</hi> now be judge, whether when you ſate ſo with all your power and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor about you, ſo loudly proclaiming your ſelves ſuch Magnifical Members, you did not ſtink in the noſtrils of the people; who generally looked upon you then but as buſie Apes upon a houſe top, and as a towering ſmoak in the Socket of a greaſie Candleſtick. <note place="margin">St. Bern. l. <hi>1.</hi> de Conſid. c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>For ſuch</hi> (as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> tells us) <hi>are all dignified perſons without merit;</hi> and ſo accordingly you went out in your own ſnuff, the ſtench whereof is not yet, nor ever will be in all ſucceeding Ages ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed. But I forbear, leaſt I loſe my ſelf in this vaſt field of Paſſion, Wonder, and Aſtoniſhment; and indeed I would willingly paſs over this diſcourſe with ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, as over coals covered with aſhes, were it not that as it was fit to expoſe maſſacred bodies to view, thereby to cure the madneſs of the <hi>Mileſian</hi> Maids: ſo we are bound to diſcover the bloody effects of this late unnatural War, to raiſe a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in all good ſouls, againſt the wicked and diabolical cauſes of it; thoſe bloody
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:94686:56"/>Religionaries, covenanting Cockatrices, in a word, <hi>Proteſtants of Integrity;</hi> for killing and robbing more villainous than ever was a <hi>Cacus,</hi> or a <hi>Polyphemus;</hi> more like <hi>Centaurs</hi> than men, much leſs Saints; and if you could but look into them, you would finde for all their reverend preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to purity and godlineſs, their hearts all ſpotted over like the skin of a <hi>Panther.</hi> Wretched Religionaries, who carry with them the voice of <hi>Jacob,</hi> but the hands of <hi>Eſau;</hi> whoſe godlineſs truly is not unlike a Tomb of Glory, full of rotten Bones; and a fair Eye to ſhew, but purblinde at hand: And yet truly, notwithſtanding all out unworthy ſufferings from this kinde of Cockatrice-Chriſtians, we in <hi>England</hi> have now no little reaſon to rejoyce in thoſe very miſeries, and congratulate with our ſelves, that very blood-ſhed it ſelf of thoſe unnatural wars, if we could at no cheaper rate have acquired the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of thoſe moſt ineſtimable bleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and benefits, which we have ſince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the undeceiving of the good people of the Nation, from this grand cheat of <hi>Presbyterian Religion,</hi> and above all the reſt, the ſoveraign influence of that moſt precious perſon his Sacred Majeſty,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:94686:56"/>and moſt gracious Government. Thrice bleſſed <hi>England</hi> in ſuch a purchaſe, though with ſo much coſt and pains! O happy voice of thunder, which made this Hinde to bring forth ſo glorious a Birth, after ſo many terrible throws, and ſuch direful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations of many years!</p>
            <p>Methinks I ſee ſtill, and it will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways preſent with me, how upon his entry into <hi>London,</hi> all the hearts of the poor Subjects of this Nation, which ſo much ſighed in the Civil Wars, and under the late Uſurpers, freſhly bloomed, and new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly opened themſelves as Roſes, at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nign and gentle aſpect of this incomparable Prince. Some ſtedfaſtly beheld him, and became as ſtatues, yet ſhewing by their eyes, that they were not made of marble: Others ſpake to him with an infinity of dumb teſtimonies of a never ſilent and hearty affection: The reſt made the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments of their hearts burſt forth from their lips, not being able to withhold from Acclamations.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall we ſay then, if our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Proteſtants of Integrity</hi> have been the cauſes of all this great happineſs, both to Prince ann People? I am ſure they glory in it, as their own proper product,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:94686:57"/>which if truly done by them, out of a true reſentment of loyalty, without any mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of their own private and pernicious deſigns, and a perfect repentance for their paſt crimes, no doubt will prove ſufficient expiation both in the ſight of God and man, for whole myriads of their treaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able tranſgreſſions before. For this dry victory of his Majeſty over us, hath been the greateſt and moſt conducing to the publick good, that ever was heard of in the whole world. It was well obſerved of <hi>Tacitus.</hi> that <hi>Ingens victoriae decus citra domeſticum ſanguinem bellanti,</hi> the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt glory of a victory is that which a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain gains by the leaſt expence of home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred blood. And this hath been his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſt es conſtant ſtudy to do, ever ſince his moſt barbarous baniſhment: Nay, his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor likewiſe hath been to ſave as much as he could of his very enemies blood. He hath never ſought to purchaſe fame by ſuch a cruel vanity, as <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great did, who building a Temple to <hi>Minerva,</hi> cauſed to be engraven over the Gate of it, how he had taken, routed, and ſlain, Two mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions one hundred fourſcore and three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men; pillaged and ſunk Eighty hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred forty and ſix Ships; made deſolate One
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:94686:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>thouſand five hundred thirty eight Cities and Towns. If this be the way to glory, his Sacred Majeſty ſure hath ſteered a clean contrary courſe; for he hath written and engraven by his actions on the Gate of the Temple of <hi>Eternity,</hi> the Men, Ships, Cities and Towns that he hath preſerved. <hi>Haec divina potentia eſt, gregatim &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licè ſervare,</hi> ſaith the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt Excellent <hi>Sentca;</hi> It is a piece of no leſs than di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine power, to ſave publickly, <note place="margin">Since, de Clem. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> and by troops. By the other way, it may be his Majeſty might have rendered himſelf more remarkable and terrible, like a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Comet, by the ruine of his Kingdoms; but his gracious goodneſs knew, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be ſo honorable as to ſave: And it is not his Majeſties fault, if not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all thoſe great and fierce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions of peeviſh ſpirits, we are not yet reconciled into a brotherly amity, and as one mans children, if we do reverence his Sacred Majeſty as our common Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Our Cattel are as plentiful as ever, our fields no leſs fertil and fragrant; nor yet are our Hillocks leſs filled with Ears of Corn, than they were before cur late unnatural Wars; all which we muſt needs attribute
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:94686:58"/>to his Majeſties moſt pious care and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, in whoſe power it was for our ingratitude, to have thrown us all into our deſerved confuſion, and conſequently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; by which means he hath built himſelf a living monument in the hearts of all true Engliſhmen; in which he will live more honorably a thouſand times, and ſo be repreſented to after ages, than all thoſe great Monarchs of <hi>Egypt,</hi> in their rich Marbles, Pyramids, and Obelisks. And if our <hi>Proteſtants of Integrity</hi> have been, as they pretend, ſo highly inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental in this happy production, it is fit they ſhould have their due honor and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement; and very requiſit it is, that we ſhould all joyn in prayers to God, that they may perfectly forſake the Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice and all his works, and continue like good Chriſtians in the payment of thoſe dues of obedience and loyalty which they have ſo worthily begun.</p>
            <p>But now you muſt give me leave to tell you a ſtory, which though in its ſurface may ſeem ſomething fabulous, yet is grounded upon very good Hiſtory, and the whole moral of it will be found, I fear, to be too perfect truth. That Monſieur <hi>De Bean Mannoir,</hi> a Noble Breton, being as
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:94686:58"/>honourably, as religiouſly engaged in the holy Warrs, took part with a Lion, that was combated by a Serpent, in a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> and killed the Serpent with his ſword, who had in all likelihood, otherwiſe worſted the Lion, is as fair and faithful Hiſtory, as any humane Authority can derive to us. But upon this it is not impoſſible but ſome skillful Mythologiſts might erect this Fable. A Princely Lion that was for long time acknowledged King of the Wilderneſs of <hi>Sinai,</hi> made himſelf a moſt ſtately den, a Palace equal to the dignity of his Royal Perſon and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Now there was a brood of moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile and moſt miſchievous ſerpents there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, who had an evil eye upon the ſtate and authority of this Royal Lion, and a deſire to make themſelves Maſters of his den. This wicked deſign of theirs they moſt ſecretly and craftily carried on, by private plots and conſpiracies, bandying in his counſels, and ploughing with his Heifers. But prevailing nothing with all that, they entred into a Solemn League and Covenant, by arms and open force to expel him from thence, or reduce him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their obedience. Upon this very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Battels were fought betwixt them, but
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:94686:59"/>the valour and vigilance of the Lion, was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o great, and ſuch the fidelity of his other good Subjects, that in ſome years they could yet gain little or nothing from him. At laſt the Serpentine power growing ſtronger, and the good Lions weaker, by their ſubtil inſinuation into his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and intelligence with ſome of his unfaithful Counſellors, and when almoſt all his honeſt friends power was exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, both purſes and perſons ſpent in the purſuance of the Royal right; the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh ſerpents at laſt took him priſoner, ſeized upon his Royal den, and at length moſt villanouſly murthered him before the very door of it.</p>
            <p>The young Lion in the mean while ſeeing two moſt vaſt and hideous Serpents had gotten the poſſeſſion of his Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Den, endeavoured to ſave himſelf by flight from their infernal ſerpentine fury, and accordingly tranſported himſelf into another country, where he lived for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeers a diſconſolate ſtranger, and not a little diſtreſt: Yet notwithſtanding let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſlip no opportunity that might ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his Intereſt in <hi>Paleſtike;</hi> at length after many moſt valiant Eſſays and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, to regain what his father had loſt,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:94686:59"/>and with little or no ſucceſs, he calls a Forreſt Council about him, and was at laſt adviſed by the Fox to lye quiet for a while, not to ſtir at all; for all his quick and active oppoſition, did but keep his enemies more waking, and hold them ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented togerher in bonds of ſtricter uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ſo he was contented to ſit ſtill for a while, and give that viperous brood more leiſure to deſtroy one another: which fell out according to the Fox his counſels, and the Lions expectations; For the two great Serpents that had made themſelves Princes of the place, and uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the Lions right, fell into ſuch fierce and unreconcileable differences, that the quarrel could never have end till one had baniſht and driven out the other; for it is moſt certain, as the wiſe Spaniard informs us, <hi>in el amar, in el mandar no quieren compania;</hi> nor love, nor lordſhip can brook any Rival: There is but one Sun neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in heaven, and one King in a Country; a great ſpirit cannot endure a crown made Creſcent-wiſe, but will furniſh out the roundneſs of the Circle.</p>
            <p>In fine, the worſted Serpent now being beaten into extream deſpair, addreſſeth himſelf to the young Lion, and proffers his
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:94686:60"/>utmoſt aſſiſtance to reſtore him effective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his right, ſo he will be pleaſed but to let him have onr corner of his Den, and a part of his power; to which the Royal-hearted Lion readily aſſented; ſo with mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual forces they prevailed to repoſſeſs the Den, and ſlay the Maſter Serpent. Now it is very notorious, that the beaten and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht Serpent, was aiding and aſſiſting to the Lion, not for any kindneſs, or love to him, or his cauſe; but for his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and to revenge himſelf upon his treacherous companion. And it is ſaid, that ſo noble and ſo perfidious a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture not being able to cohabit long in peace together, the Serpent ſtill according to its Deviliſh Luciferian nature, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring to be <hi>aut Ceſar, aut nihil,</hi> ſole King or nothing; they fell into a moſt bloody combat, at the ſame time that this Seignior of <hi>Beaumanoir</hi> was paſſing by, who like a noble, cordial Cavalier, enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his ſword in the Lions behalf, ſlew the Serpent, and ſo freed that Monarchy from any more of the Serpentine ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</p>
            <p>But now here I muſt be forced to draw a curtain over the horrid miſdeameanours of my own Countrymen, which are not
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:94686:60"/>onely paſt, but thoſe that are feared to come, leaſt if I ſhould make any Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I may be miſ-conſtrued, and appear to ambitiate rather the buſineſs of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet than a Hiſtorian; ſo I refer every man to his private application, and the whole Nation to their earneſt prayers, that it would pleaſe God in his goodneſs to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert what the malice of ſome does threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en us withal.</p>
            <p>So I return to my buſineſs, and to ſearch out if I can, the very firſt bed of this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous brood; the proper Pedigree of theſe State Serpents, and the very ſource and origin of thoſe Religious Cockatrices before ſpoken of, from whence they are truly and lineally deſcended.</p>
            <p>Now there are three derivations alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but a fourth I beleeve is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable. The firſt is from the old <hi>Wickle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſts</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> who are regiſtred by Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> amongſt his Martyrs, and are ſtill accounted by ſome of the late Doctors of Integrity, <hi>Inter primos teſtes veritatis,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mognſt the firſt Wineſſes of the Truth: and yet we ſhall finde that they did hold as the <hi>Knoxians</hi> did ſince them in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that the people might correct their Princes, if they offend: And therefore
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:94686:61"/>
               <hi>Melancthon</hi> a reforming Brother too, <note place="margin">Melanct. in com. ſuper Pol. Ariſt.</note> in his Comment upon <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Politicks, ſaith, <hi>Varias Tragoedias excitavit Wicklef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus, qui contendit eos qui non habent Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Sanctum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem in lib. de jure Magiſt. Oſiander, cent. 9.</note> 
               <hi>amittere Dominium: Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleff</hi> raiſed ſtrange Tragedies, by teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they loſe all right of Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who have not the Spirit of God: And in his Book, <hi>de jure Magiſtatus,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>Inſaniit Wickleffus, qui ſenſit impios nullum dominium habere. Wickleff</hi> was mad who thought that no wicked man had any right of dominion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oſiander</hi> witneſſeth the ſame in his ninth Century, and divers others of the ſame reforming race, who have them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves written altogether as Rebel Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, yet tax <hi>Wickleff</hi> highly for this; that all wicked men ſhould loſe their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety: So as if Princes be ſo, which reſts in their ſanctity onely to judge, they muſt preſently forfeit their Crowns. And yet Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> calleth him, <hi>Stellam matutinam in medio nebulae, &amp; Lunam plenam in die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus illis,</hi> a morning ſtar in the middle of a fog, and the full Moon of the time; and the conſequence of thoſe Doctrines may be ſeen in the ſtories of Sir <hi>John Oldca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> Lord <hi>Cobham,</hi> and Sir <hi>Roger Acton,</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:94686:61"/>two of <hi>Wickllffs</hi> Diſciples, who raiſed a Rebellion accordingly, and were by that active King <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth, defeated, and deſervedly put to death for Hereſie and Treaſon. And how careful that phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical <hi>Oldcastle</hi> was of his Followers, may be ſeen in his Speech to Sir <hi>Tho. Erping<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> that if he ſaw him riſe the third day from the dead, he ſhould procure quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and favour to thoſe of his Sect: But by his not reſurrection as he promiſed, his Sect lay ſtrangled in the Cradle, and buried with him till King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt his days, when ſome ends of it were taken up again, and ſet out with more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation then ever in that Princes Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority; and what rare effects of obedience, were by that means produced in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time, who brought them up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the Teſt, may be eaſily read in our Chronicles. Wherein it is plain, that in the poor five years of her Reign, there was <hi>de facto</hi> more open and violent oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and rebellion made by her own Subjects, than Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had in fortie five yeers, or any Prince before, or ſince the <hi>Wickliffian</hi> Doctrine; till the ſame ſmothered fire broke out at laſt in our good King <hi>Charles</hi> his time, to his
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:94686:62"/>utter ruine, and the ſhaking of the very foundations of his Monarchy.</p>
            <p>And yet to this very day is <hi>Wickliff</hi> held for a grand Apoſtle amongſt all the Phanaticks in <hi>England,</hi> who are at preſent more numerous than ever. Howſoever it cannot enter into me to beleeve that he deſerved the Honour to be reputed the firſt Father of our Proteſtants of Integrity; though he might poſſibly by that ſingle Doctrine of his, open a gap to all thoſe gallant Champions againſt Kings that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him. So <hi>exit Wickleffus;</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter valiant <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> who is by ſome, and truly not altogether undeſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuppoſed to be the great Grandfather of theſe prodigious Doctrines againſt the State, Dignity and Perſons of Kings and Princes.</p>
            <p>It is well known that in the yeer of our Lord 1514 the whole eſtate of the Church joyed a ſetled Peace, and all their ancient Rights and Priviledges: All Princes with great devotion were Nurſing-Fathers and Protectors of it; there was a perfect har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and correſpondence, (for all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion and Faith) between the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Princes and Common-Wealths of all Chriſtendom.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:94686:62"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno</hi> 1515. <hi>Martin Luther</hi> an Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtane Frier, a man of a turbulent ſpirit, was indeed the firſt that broke this long and happy peace, who having interpoſed himſelf in the fatal buſineſs of Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (ſent by Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth into <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi>) began firſt as Proctor for his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to preach againſt the injury done to his fraternity, againſt the covetouſneſs and abuſes of the Collectors, and againſt their Authority which did nominate them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And finding (as Novelty is ever at firſt well entertained by the multitude) <hi>Populo placere quas feciſset fabulas,</hi> and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving alſo ſome of the greateſt Princes in <hi>Germany</hi> did hear him, and would be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to back him upon all occaſions, and in all his proceedings, pufft up with vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, and an ambitious conceit of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he preſently ſet himſelf upon higher ſtrains, and as a man grown ſick in his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and of a fiery diſeaſe, he begun to rave and defame all Church Government; he abandoned his Cloiſter, caſt off his Habit, and renounced all obedience to his Superiours: For now he preacheth againſt the whole Clergy, againſt the Tyranny and Superiority of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> (whoſe Authority in matters Eccleſiaſtical
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:94686:63"/>was till then held ſacred) perſwaded thepeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not to render him or them any obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: The Pope he termed <hi>Sataniſſinum Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pam, &amp; Meſſem Aſino;</hi> the Prelates, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led blind guides; the Religious, he termed Swine, and Candles ſet under a Buſhel.</p>
            <p>Thus he ſought <hi>non purgare abuſus, ſed tollere ordinem, Triticum cum zizanio evel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere ſtuduit;</hi> not to cleanſe the Church of abuſes, but to extirpate all Order, and to pluck up the Wheat with the Weeds.</p>
            <p>Now his firſt ſtep towards all the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies he intended, was this; that he might work his miſchief and confuſion in the Civil State the better he firſt tears in pieces the Eccleſiaſtical, and ſo proclaims open War againſt all the Biſhops in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many;</hi> and therefore writes a Book expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Contra ſtatum Eccleſiae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luth. in lib. cont. ſtat. Ecc. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; adverſus falſo nominatum ordinem Epiſcoporum,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the State of the Church, and the Order of Biſhops falſly ſo called; in which he ſends out his Bull, as he calls it, in theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Attendite vobis Epiſcoporum umbrae, vult vobis Bullam &amp; Edictum legere, non valdè teneris veſtris auribus placiturum;</hi> and this was his Lecture worth the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Omnes quicunque opem ferunt, bona,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:94686:63"/>famam &amp; ſanguinem in hoc impendunt, honorem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſunm in hoc exponentes, ut Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copatus Pompatici devaſtentur, tam remoti &amp; alieni ab omni functione Apoſtolica, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hoc Satanicum Regimen Epiſcopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum extinguatur; Hi ſunt dilecti filii Dei &amp; verè Chriſtiani obſervantes praecepta Dei;</hi> Whoſoever ſhall ſuccour us in this buſineſs, with their goods, good name, or blood, and lay out all their honor too in it, that theſe pompous Biſhopricks may be laid waſte, and all the Devilſh Regiment of Biſhops be extinguiſht; <note place="margin">Id. in lib. cont. Sylv. Pricat. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> dat. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenbergh.</note> theſe are the beloved children of God, and true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians obſerving the Commandements of God. And in another Book he tells us, <hi>Si fures furca, latrones gladio, haereticos igne tollimus, cur non potius hos magiſtros perditionis, hos Cardinales, hos Papas &amp; totam iſtam Romanae Sodomiae colluviem, omnibus armis impetimus &amp; corum ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne manus noſtras lavemus?</hi> Nothing muſt now ſerve his turn but to waſh his hands in the blood of Biſhops: But here he muſt not ſtop neither; the ruine of the whole Hierarchy of the Church will not ſatisfie his furious Reformation: But as if it were, as I doubt not but it was, purpoſely to bring in Barbariſm, and to put out the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:94686:64"/>eyes of the poor <hi>Almains</hi> for ever, that neither they nor their poſterity might ever diſcover his Frenetick Errors, he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours madly in the next place to ruine and deface all Univerſities, as in his Book <hi>Contra Ambroſiam Catharinam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. in lib. cont. Amb. Cathar.</note> he ſaith thus, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t videat ad Evangelium funditùs aextinguendum, nec aſtutius, nec efficacius inveniſſe Satan commentun quam erigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darum Univerſitatum,</hi> the Devil never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented a more ſubtil and effectual means to extinguiſh the Goſpel than that of founding Univerſities.</p>
            <p>And in his Book <hi>de abroganda Miſſa,</hi> there he diſſwades the people from ſending their children to the Univerſities, <note place="margin">Id. in lib. de abrog. miſſa.</note> and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally condemns them all in theſe words; <hi>Academi is per Idolam Moloch figuratas puto,</hi> That Univerſities were figured out to us by the Idol <hi>Moloch;</hi> and gives the Reaſon after, <hi>Ex iſto enim fumo prodeunt iſtae Locuſtae, quae omnes Cathedras occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant;</hi> for out of that ſmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, ſaith he, do iſſue thoſe Locuſts, which ſwarm in all Chairs, and poſſeſs Pulpits: And ſo in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to that Doctrine did his learned Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion <hi>Caroloſtadius</hi> chooſe to go to Plough, <note place="margin">Caroloſtad.</note> rather then he would read one Lecture more.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:94686:64"/>
            <p>And his <hi>fidus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Melanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in Dyd.</note> 
               <hi>Philip Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthon,</hi> in his Book called <hi>Didymus,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Equidem ſapientem virum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udico fuiſſe Wickieffum Anglum, qui omnium primus, quod ego ſciam, v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dit univerſitates fuiſſe Satanae Synagogas:</hi> I take truly <hi>Wickliff</hi> an Engliſhman to have been a wiſe perſon, who was the firſt of all that I know, who diſcovered Univerſities to be the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues of Satan.</p>
            <p>Nor could this famous Reformation ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie it ſelf with the extirpation of theſe two the talleſt Cedars in the Empire; that is the Hierarchy, and the Univerſities; but a greater miſchief muſt follow, and that muſt be the ruine of the Empire, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelf: Which is firſt to be ſeen plainly by his prodigious incivility, arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, and diſobedience, towards the Emperour, and the Princes of <hi>Germany:</hi> Nay, what a reverent eſteem had he for Sacred Majeſty, by his uſage of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luth. in lib. cont. Regem Angliae.</note> in his Book that he entituled againſt him? he called him an envious mad fool, full of Cowardiſe, and without any vein of Princely blood in his body: After that he ſaith, He was a Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisk, to whom he denounced damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:94686:65"/>
            <p>And <hi>p.</hi> 335. he ſaith, This glorious King, lieth ſtoutly like a King: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 335</note> And again, He is a lying <hi>ſcurra,</hi> covered with the title of a King, and a choſen veſſel of the Devill: And <hi>p.</hi> 338. Thou art no more a King, but a Sacrilegious Theef: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 338.</note> And then moſt mannerly, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 333.</note> and like himſelf, <hi>p.</hi> 333. <hi>Jus mihi erit majeſtatem tuam ſtercore conſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, &amp;c.</hi> For more of that ſtuff I refer you to Sir <hi>Thomas Moor</hi> the famous Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sir Tho. Moor. cont. Lutherum.</note> who recapitualtes them in his Latine work againſt <hi>Luther:</hi> But iudeed it is no great wonder how he treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. when we do but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how he behaved himſelf towards the Princes of the Empire, and to <hi>Caeſar</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who was his own Soveraign Lord, to whom whether he gave what was due to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or did preach and perſwade obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Magiſtrates, as a good Chriſtian ought, we ſhall ſee anon: And firſt in his Book, <note place="margin">Luth. in lib. cont. duo man data Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</note> 
               <hi>Contra duo mandata Caeſaris,</hi> he gives him and all the Princes of the Empire the plain Lye; <hi>Turpe quidem eſt Caeſarem ac Principes manifeſtis agere mendaciis,</hi> it is a ſhameful thing that <hi>Caeſar</hi> and the Princes ſhould deal in ſuch manifeſt lyes: And a little after calls them all Beaſts, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us mihi dedit negotium non cum hominibus
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:94686:65"/>ratione praeditis, ſed Cermaniae Beſtiae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent me occidere,</hi> meaning that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the ſavage Beaſts of <hi>Germany,</hi> ſhould murther him; then he proceecs to make them worſe than <hi>Turks, Ne ullo pacto eos ſequar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vel in militiam ire, vel dare aliquid contra Turcas: Quandoquidem Turca deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es prudentior, probior<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quàm ſunt Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes noſtri; quid tal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bu fatuis,</hi> &amp;c. he would neither follow them into the War, nor give any thing againſt the Turks, <note place="margin">In lib. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. <hi>500:</hi> in Art. <hi>361</hi>
               </note> or the Turk was ten times an honeſter, and a wiſer man than his Princes; what had he to doe with ſuch fools? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet further in his Book of Articles, <hi>Quid ergo boni in rebus divinis vel decernant, vel conſrituant Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranm tam impii &amp; prophani?</hi> what good can ſuch impious and prophane Tyrants do, <note place="margin">In lib. de Seculer. Poteſt.</note> or determine in Divine matters? before they were liars, beaſts, fools, and worſe then Turks; and now plainly Tyrants, impious, prophane. And yet a little higher ſtill, in his Book of Secular Power, he delivers his opinion of all Kings and Princes in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and how they are to be eſteemed; <hi>Scire deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s quod aeb initio mundi, rariſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma avis eſt prudens Princeps, ac multo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior probus; ſunt communiter maximè fatui, &amp; nequiſsimi Nebulones in terrâ</hi> from the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:94686:66"/>beginning of the World Princes general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are, and ever have been, the arranteſt Fools, and wickedeſt Knaves living; and for fear he ſhould not be ſufficiently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, he interprets himſelf preſently after, <hi>Quis neſcit Principes eſse carnem fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinam in coelo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In lib. de Bello cont. Turcas.</note> as great a dainty in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as Veniſon is upon the earth, that a Prince ſhould have a ſaved ſoul: And then in his Book of War againſt the Turks, he concludes them abſolutely unfit to govern the affairs of Chriſtendom. <hi>Caeſarem neque caput eſſe Reipub. Chriſtianae, vel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſorem Fidei, &amp; Evangelii: &amp; oportere ſane. Eccleſiam habere alium defenſorem quàm ſunt Imperatores &amp; Reges:</hi> That is doubtleſs to ſay, That he will have no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Head of the Church, nor Defender of the Faith, but his own ſanctified ſelf. Kings at leaſt cannot be; for he gives his Reaſon for that, <hi>Eos namque eſſe peſsimos hostes Christianiſmi &amp; fidei.</hi> Did ever any Prophets, Apoſtles or Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, uſe ſuch a barbarous liberty of ſpeech againſt their Perſecutors? no not againſt <hi>Nero, Diocleſian,</hi> or <hi>Julian,</hi> the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Tyrants that ever the earth bore. Did <hi>Elias</hi> his Prototype, as his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples would have him to be, ever rage ſo
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:94686:66"/>madly againſt <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezabel?</hi> Did not St. <hi>Paul</hi> uſe <hi>Feſtus</hi> with more Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence? And without doubt no Chriſtian and true zeal can be ſo irregular, ſo rude and ſo intemperately paſſionate, as to give the plain lye to <hi>Caeſar</hi> his Soveraign, and to the Princes of the Empire: To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim him and them Salvages, Baboons, Fools and Tyrants, blind Buzzards; and that the Turk was a wiſer, and an hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter man than they. To affirm as it were in ſcorn and hatred of Majeſty and Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, that a wiſe and a good Prince is as rarely to be found as a black-Swan; that commonly Kings and Princes be the moſt doting Fools, and Reprobate Knaves in the world, that they were a curſed and a damned Crew; as if there were no place vouchſafed in heaven for ſuch Caitiffs as Kings. Theſe are rare motives doubtleſs to the people, to render due obedience to their Princes.</p>
            <p>But yet leaſt this rayling ſhould not do his feat, and that the world ſhould fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably interpret all that language to be but a paſſionate heat againſt ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons; and not that he did intend to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe and enervate the very ſacred Power it ſelf and function of Kings: nay to take the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:94686:67"/>Crown from off their heads if he could, and to expoſe their Prerogatives and all Regalities to the malice and contempt of the people, he muſt yet determine the buſineſs more poſitively and cathedrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally againſt them; and therefore in his book againſt the Bores, <note place="margin">Lo. <hi>1.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Ruſti cos.</note> he ſends this greeting to the Princes; <hi>Sciatis Boni Domini Deum ſic procurare quod ſubditi nec poſsunt, nec debent, nec volunt, Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nidem veſtram ferre duitius.</hi> Know ye my good Lords, that God has ſo provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that your Subjects neither can, ſhall, will or ought to endure your Tyranny any longer. Then in his Common places, <hi>Pulchrè vero non turbandam pacem Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam arbitraris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lo. Com. claſs. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; turbandam pacem aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Dei; non ſic Palatini, non ſic:</hi> As if it were undoubtedly true, that the peace of God, and the peace of the Empire, were incompatible: I am ſure the old Lawes and Government of the Empire, and <hi>Luthers</hi> new Goſpel were very incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent.</p>
            <p>But yet more plainly he ſets it down as a divine Decree, <note place="margin">L.de Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiv. Babyl. c. de Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmo.</note> in his book of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byloniſh Captivity; <hi>At omnibus hominum legibus exempti ſumus, libertate Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na nobis per Baptiſmum donata,</hi> we are
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:94686:67"/>exempted from obedience to all humane Lawes by our Chriſtian liberty given us in Baptiſm: And in the ſame book in his chapter of Matrimony, <hi>Scio,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>nullam Rempublicam Legibus feliciter ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrari;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid. c. de Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio.</note> I know no Common-wealth that is happily governed by Lawes: <note place="margin">Ibid in c. de ſacris Ordinibus.</note> and again in his Chapter of Holy Orders, <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe enim eſt &amp; iniquiter ſervile, Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num hominem qui liber eſt, aliis quam coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtibus &amp; divinis legibus ſubjectum eſſe.</hi> It is a foul thing, and moſt wickedly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile, that a Chriſtian man who is free, ſhould be ſubject to any other but the Divine and Heavenly Lawes.</p>
            <p>So that it is moſt plain, that it was not <hi>Luthers</hi> deſign onely to pull down Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, but all other kinds of Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and to extirpate all humane Lawes, and ſo to ſubject the People onely to his interpretation of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>And indeed he excellently well and very ingenuouſly expreſſeth his own mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his book to the Nobility of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. ad Nobilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniae.</note> firſt giving his ſentence upon the Imperial Chamber at <hi>Spyci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; Tribunal Camerae Imperialis; ecce quam Diabolica eſt Meretrix:</hi> Behold what a diveliſh whore the Tribunal of the Imperial
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:94686:68"/>Chamber is become! Then proceeds thus, <hi>Ferunt nullum eſſe pulchrius Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men quàm apud Turcam, qui tamen ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Canonicum, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Civile jus habet, ſed ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Alchoranum. At nos fateri oportet, nuſquam eſſe turpius Regimen qaàm apud nos per jus Civile &amp; Canonicum.</hi> They ſay there is no better Government any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where than amongſt the Turkes, who yet have neither Canon or Civil Lawes, but onely their Alchoran. But we on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide muſt acknowledg, that there is nowhere a worſe Government than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us by the Civil and Common Law. Now ſee I pray you, and obſerve whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was not this grave Doctors mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to aboliſh all Lawes, and that men ſhould be onely governed by his Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Now by theſe and ſuch like abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Doctrines, was not he onely the cauſe of thoſe horrible tumults which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in his dayes, but of all the ſad wars and moſt dreadfull deſolations that have followed ſince, and ſo muſt derive ſtill an unhappy influence to all Poſterity? For if it were lawfull for the Elector of <hi>Saxony</hi> his great Maſter and Patron to take Armes for defence of Lutheraniſm, becauſe he was perſwaded by him, that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:94686:68"/>there was no other true and infallible Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion but his; why might not another Prince with the ſame pretext take Armes for <hi>Calviniſm,</hi> and <hi>Hulberſtat</hi> for <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm,</hi> and a <hi>Muncer</hi> for <hi>Anabaptiſm;</hi> and ſo by an Anarchy under colour of their liberties, and the prerogative of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, tear the Empire in pieces, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the Ports of <hi>Germany</hi> to let in the Turk, as they have very often done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready? and all the Princes of this later age have too ſadly ſeen the dangerous and diſmal conſequences of that Doctrine, <hi>That it is lawfull for Subjects by their ſwords to defend their Religion againſt their Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor did this Civil Gentleman uſe with more reſpect and reverence his Friends and Patrons of the houſe of <hi>Saxony.</hi> As for Duke <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Leipſwig,</hi> he call'd him once, when he was diſpleaſed with him, the Apoſtle of Sathan, and ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully gives him the Title of <hi>Illuſtriſſima Inclementia veſtra:</hi> and ſo to old <hi>John Frederick</hi> his chiefeſt friend and favourer, upon occaſion of a Commiſſion or viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his which diſoleaſed him, <note place="margin">Lo. in ferm. Dom. Lo. contra Ambros Cathar.</note> 
               <hi>Ite,</hi> quoth he, <hi>eis viſiatoribus,</hi> and then he tells you preſently, becauſe he was not
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:94686:69"/>himſelf called to counſel about it, <hi>Neſcio qua de cauſa me praeterierit Princeps;</hi> and in another place, ſaith he, <hi>Si licet mihi Decretales Papae, Conciliorum decreta, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges &amp; mandata Imperatoris, omnium<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Principum, pro libertate Chriſtiana, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum contemnere ſed &amp; conculcare, veſtráſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne res geſtas praeclarae viſitationis, legum vice acceptem?</hi> If it be lawfull for me not onely to contemn, but tread under foot the Popes Decretals, the Decrees of Councils, the Lawes and commands of the Emperour, and all Princes, for the defence of Chriſtian liberty; muſt I be forced to accept the tranſactions of your pittifull Viſitation, in the place of Lawes? See how he ſerved his own Maſter; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed Ile ſay that for him, he dealt his blows againſt Princes very impartially.</p>
            <p>Now indeed after all this, may it not be very well imagined, that this Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monarchical Egg of the Religious Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice was laid in <hi>Martin Luthers</hi> boſome? eſpecially if we well obſerve how <hi>Calvin</hi> and he do ſymbolize together in the point, how they ſpeak one language, wear both the like colours, and the very ſame faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if you will obſerve a little further out of <hi>Luther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 7. <hi>fol</hi> 441.</note> 
               <hi>Nebulones iſti ex Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:94686:69"/>Tyranni &amp; qui inducunt animum ideo nobis Evangelium dediſſe, eoſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ex car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Pontificio expediviſse, ut poſſint ipſi avaritiae ſuae litare:</hi> Theſe Knaves, ſaith he of the Nobility, theſe Tyrants per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelves that God has therefore given us his Goſpel, and delivered us out of Popiſh bondage, that they may ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to their own Covetouſneſs. <note place="margin">In Epiſt. fol. <hi>350.</hi>
               </note> And in his Epiſtles he ſayes, <hi>Principem eſſe &amp; non ex aliqua parte Latronem eſſe, aut non aut vix poſſibile eſt,</hi> To be a Prince and not an Oppreſſour, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 32 5.</note> nay an arrant Thief and Robber, is not at all, or very hardly poſſible: and again, <hi>Non eſt Principis eſſe Chriſtianum, &amp;c.</hi> It is not the part of a Prince to be a Chriſtian. Nay yet again, <note place="margin">Tom. <hi>6.</hi> fol. <hi>143.</hi> in Pſal. <hi>101.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mirum non eſt ſaeculares Reges Dei hoſtes eſſe, ejuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> verbum hoſtiliter perſequi; hoc ipſis a Natura eſt inſitum, haec corum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietas,</hi> It is no wonder, ſaith he, that ſecular Kings are Gods enemies, and do with all hoſtility perſecute his word; it is planted in their very natures ſo to be, it is their inſeparable propriety.</p>
            <p>Thus by his Rules as well as <hi>Calvins,</hi> there is a plain Antipathy between Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and Religion; and ſo I am ſure by better conſequence between their Religion and Loyalty.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:94686:70"/>
            <p>But to proceed a little further: <hi>Aulaes Principum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tom. <hi>3.</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin: fol. <hi>459</hi> in. Pſalm <hi>45</hi>
               </note> ſaith he, <hi>verè poſſunt dici ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; Thronus Diaboli, ubi tot ſunt Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boli, qnot fere Aulici;</hi> Courts of Princes, ſaith he, may be truly ſaid the Seats and Thrones of the Divel, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence Kings muſt be the Devils, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>f.</hi> 8.</note> though he ſaith onely that Courtiers are ſo. Yet again, <hi>Principes ſunt flagitioſiſſimi Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulones:</hi> Princes, ſaith he, are moſt wicked Knaves; the reaſon followeth, <hi>Sunt enim Dei Lictores, &amp; Carnifices quibus ira di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina ad puniendos improbos uti ſolet, &amp;c.</hi> For they are no better than Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants, Executioners and Hangmen, to puniſh people upon earth. Yet further, <hi>Nullum ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> jus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fol.</hi> 190.</note> 
               <hi>ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fidem, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem apud Principes ſaeculares reperire licet;</hi> There is neither faith nor truth to be found amongſt ſecular Princes; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>fol.</hi> 149.</note> they have neither honeſty or juſtice. And then you may take for a very good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, <hi>Quid ergo Principes doceam &amp; huſuſmodi Porcis ſcribam?</hi> To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſhould I go about to teach Princes, or inſtruct ſuch ſwine as they are?</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee how theſe holy men and bleſſed Reformers, have divinely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired in this unity, (how different ſoever
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:94686:70"/>they are in other points, even diametri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally oppoſite in all other doctrines) as led by the ſame Spirit, to arrive at the ſame moſt Chriſtian and holy end, to nouriſh a deadly feud againſt all Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, animate them to Rebellion, and in effect to ſubvert all Civil Government.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Luther</hi> was a Proteſtant, is moſt certain; but what his integrity was you have fully ſeen; nor will I deny that <hi>Zuinglius, Calvin, Beza, Paraus, Grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, Knox, Buchanan, Gilby,</hi> were all as good Proteſtants as <hi>Luther</hi> himſelf in this point, and of great integrity, who have all like great and glorious Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Proteſtant Faith, attempted to Cantonize all Kingdoms into ſeveral Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, as they have done already their French Church, which they call their new Ark to preſerve and redeem the miſerable world from a pretended inundation of impiety, ignorance, and irreligion.</p>
            <p>Thus I have been bold to draw the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Faction abroad, that is now diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by the title Proteſtants of inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, with a face ſo full of frowns and ſternneſs, that by the very phyſiogmony of them, you may eaſily judg how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet and turbulent the conſtitution of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:94686:71"/>them is like to be; but yet we cannot juſtly determine who is the great Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father of theſe ſeditious, rebellious and King-killing Doctrines.</p>
            <p>But now at length by tedious travel, we are at laſt arriv'd at <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, and there we are told, that we ſhall not doubt to find the <hi>Origen</hi> of this pernicious Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atrice.</p>
            <p>Now firſt the Reverend Picture-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker <hi>Ormer</hi> aſſures us, 'that this was Dr. <hi>Allens</hi> Divinity; <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Allen</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng Apol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and he taxeth him highly, that men may murther their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and that in his Apology for the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries, he citeth the 25 of <hi>Numbers,</hi> and thence concludes, that Subjects may fairely take their Soveraigns and hang them up: ſo impious a poſition, and ſuch unchriſtian words, that certainly could never come into the heart, tongue or pen, of any true Roman Catholick whatſoever, though I muſt confeſs Dr. <hi>Allen</hi> did ſpeak a little too profuſely as to the point, yet not comparably ſo dirtily as he has pleas'd to quote them: He was better read in his friend <hi>Goodman,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Goodman <hi>in lib.</hi> de obedientia</note> and I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that in his quotation he miſtook one for t' other; for <hi>Goodman</hi> indeed in his Book of <hi>Obedience,</hi> hath juſt the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:94686:71"/>very ſame language that he puts upon Dr. <hi>Allen,</hi> and in his Deſcant upon the ſame place: So the miſtake is very eaſie. <hi>Factum illud,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>quod me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moratur, Numb.</hi> 25. <hi>perpetuumeſt exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum in omnem aeternitaten, <note place="margin">Numb. 25.</note> &amp; certa de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciatio populo, ut in ſimili defectione à Cultu Dei, Rectores ſuos qui à Deo ipſos abduount, ad furcas abripiant &amp; ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant; &amp; quamquam poſſit videri haec magnae confuſio, ut populus ſibi tantum aſſumat, tamen quum Magiſtratus officio ſuo fungi deſinit, populus ita conſiderandus eſt, ac ſi careret omni Magiſtratu, &amp; tum Deus ipſe gladium in populi manus tradit, &amp; Deus ipſe efficitur immediate eorum caput.</hi> That fact, ſaith he, in the Twentieth fifth of <hi>Numbers,</hi> is commemorated for a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing example to all eternity, and a cerrain Declaration to the people, that in the like defection from the ſervice of God, they take their Kings and Rulers, who would ſeduce them from God, away to the Gallows, and hang them up. And though this may ſeem to cauſe a great confuſion, that the people ſhould aſſume to themſelves ſo great a power; yet when Magiſtrates are ſo ſlack, as to deſiſt from performing of their duty, the people is
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:94686:72"/>to be conſidered as if they had no Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate at all, and then God himſelf puts the Sword into the peoples own hands, and God himſelf is immediately made their Head and Conductor.</p>
            <p>Now let us ſee the Doctors words, and examine the difference between them. He ſaith thus, <note place="margin">Cap. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Pro Catholica Religione certare praeclarum eſt, ſed modo &amp; tempore, ut conſcientiae lex Sacra ſupremi Paſtoris ſententiâ dirigatur.</hi> It is glorious, ſaith he, to contend for the Catholick Religion, but in good manner and time, that the Sacred Law of Conſcience may be guided and directed by the ſentence of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Paſtor. And then he recites, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. and <hi>Numb.</hi> 25. and infers. <hi>Illud autem in omnibus iis exemolis eſt notandum, populum non ſua voluntate &amp; impetu ad has caedes, ſed à Prophetis &amp; Sacerdotibus commonefacti: Id quod omni Poſteritati ſequuturae exemplo eſt, ne alias privato odio, ſuperbia, &amp;c. in errores ruamus, &amp; improbitatem noſtram religionis velo tega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> But this is to be obſerved in all thoſe examples, that the people did not ruſh violently, and upon their own heads, into thoſe ſlaughters, but as they were admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by their Prophets and Prieſts;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:94686:72"/>which may be an example to all following poſterity, leaſt otherwiſe by private Spleen, or Pride, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we fall into terrible errors, and think to hide our wickedneſs with the cloak of Religion.</p>
            <p>This as I take it, ſerves not to their purpoſe. I am ſure here is more diſcretion and duty, than <hi>ad furcas abripere,</hi> to hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them away to the Gallows; more Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Government, then preſently <hi>ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendere,</hi> to hang them up: And if we mark well, we ſhall finde that in this laſt Century of years, there have been more Princes depoſed and murthered for their Religion, by theſe Proteſtants of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, than have been in all the others ſince Chriſts time, by the Popes Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or the attempt and means of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Catholicks. How can then the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this age, walk amongſt ſo many ſhelves and precipices, not ſo much as once opening their eyes to behold the Abyſs that they have under their feet! ſo many heads cruſht in pieces by theſe cruel Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atrices, may ſerve as broken Maſts, and ſhivers of a ſhipwrack, advanced on the Promontory of Rocks, to give them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of their deplorable events, whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples they ſtill purſue; yet they look
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:94686:73"/>on them (for ought I ſee) with arms acroſs, and daily in their own dangers, like wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Victions, leap and skip between the very Ax and the Knife.</p>
            <p>But the greateſt tempeſt of tongues which I ſee ready to riſe againſt the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts,</hi> and indeed the main ground why any thing of theſe opinions was ever ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected upon them, was a falſe ſuppoſition, That <hi>Mariana,</hi> a Jeſuite, and all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of his Society, did maintain that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and treaſonable poſition of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering and Depoſing of Princes for their Religion.</p>
            <p>As touching <hi>Mariana,</hi> it will not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to be his perſonal fault; I ſay <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana</hi>'s proper opinion onely; yet was he not reſolute in that opinion neither, but handled it onely problematically, incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning indeed to the worſt part; but yet he abſolutely and dogmatically affirms it not. His words are theſe, <hi>Falli poſſum ut hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus; ſi quis meliora attulerit, gratias agam.</hi> I may be deceived as a man; and if any man bring me to a better light, I ſhall be thankful to him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, His queſtion was not for kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Kings, but for killing of Tyrants; which ſomething alters the caſe, though
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:94686:73"/>gives too great a latitude to Rebellion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, His whole Order diſavows his Poſition, and have Categorically deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the contrary.</p>
            <p>Cardinal <hi>Tolet</hi> in his <hi>Summary, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. aſſerteth, That is is not lawful to attempt againſt the life of a Prince, though he never ſo much abuſe his power; and that it is flat hereſie to maintain the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. So <hi>Greg. de Valentia, part.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 64. And of the ſame opinion is Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine, cap.</hi> 13. of his Apology; and <hi>Salmeron, Tom.</hi> 2. expounding the Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Chapter to the <hi>Romans,</hi> where he referreth the act of <hi>Ehud</hi> againſt King <hi>Eglon,</hi> to Gods expreſs Commandment. So learned <hi>Leſſius,</hi> in his Book <hi>de Scienitiae &amp; jure, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>dub.</hi> 4. The like does <hi>Serrarius</hi> in <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>Scid. Azor.</hi> in his <hi>Inſtitut.</hi> And <hi>Becanus</hi> in his Anſwer to the Ninth Aphoriſm. <hi>Gretzer</hi> in his <hi>Veſpertilio Haeretico-Politicus,</hi> confutes all <hi>Mariana</hi>'s Grounds; and ſo doth <hi>L. Richcorni</hi> in his Apology. Over and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all this, That opinion of <hi>Mariana</hi> was condemned by a Provincial Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the ſame Society that was held at <hi>Paris,</hi> 1506. And that condemnation was ratified by <hi>Claudius Aqua Viva,</hi> then
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:94686:74"/>General of the Order. The Doctors of <hi>Sorbonne</hi> likewiſe in the ſame year, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and avowed, that it was an unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ungodly poſition: And laſtly this Doctrine of <hi>Mariana</hi>'s was moſt juſtly condemned by the Court of Parliament of <hi>Raris</hi> in the ſame year.</p>
            <p>By this time, I hope, the tempeſt is pretty well laid: I am ſure, I have been ſo happy as to ſatisfie divers of my good Friends, whom I have found ſcandalized at the Fathers of the Society, for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting ſo villainous and treaſonable a Theſis. King <hi>James</hi> himſelf in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation of the Seventh of <hi>November,</hi> was pleaſed to declare his good opinion and aſſurance of <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks in that point, notwithſtanding the horrid conſpiracy then of ſome few.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We are,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>by good experience ſo well perſwaded of the Loyalty of divers Subjects of the Roman Religion, that they do as much abhor this deteſtable conſpiracy, as we do our ſelves.</hi> Nay hear a Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of the mouth of the greateſt adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary they ever had, that is, the Oracle of <hi>Geneva,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calvin in cap. <hi>1.</hi> Hoſ. &amp; in c. <hi>9.</hi> Amos.</note> upon the Firſt of <hi>Hoſea,</hi> and Ninth of <hi>Amos, Et hodie,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>quàm multi ſunt in Papatu qui Regibus accumulant
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:94686:74"/>quicquid poſſunt juris &amp; poteſtatis.</hi> And at this day there are moſt in the Papacy, that heap upon Kings whatſoever they can, of right and power. Of that, I am ſure, <hi>Geneva</hi> was never guilty. And truly it is not a little obſervable, that this prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating <hi>Calvin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. <hi>136.</hi> id Coren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> was pleaſed frequently to ſay, <hi>Magis ſibi placere Reformationem Scoticam quam Anglicanam;</hi> and he gives his reaſon, <hi>Corruptelis Papatus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huc relictam eſſe congeriem, quae non obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret modo ſed propemodum obruat purum &amp; genuinum Dei cultum.</hi> That he was better pleaſed with the Scotiſh than the Engliſh Reformation, becauſe there was a heap of Popiſh corruption left amongſt us, (that is, too much affection to Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy and Prelacy) which did not onely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, but almoſt extinguiſh the pure and genuine worſhip of God: That is, afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not ſo fair a latitude for his fowl practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Nay the beams of his Evangelical Sunſhine, did break out pretty early too amongſt us in <hi>England,</hi> as you may ſee by Mr. <hi>Dudley Fenner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fenner in lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> who jumps right with the Apoſtle of <hi>Geneva,</hi> in his Fifth Book, where he gives this fearful ſentence on an evil Prince as he calls him, <hi>Hunc tollant, vel pacificè, vel cum b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llo, vel Regni ephori,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:94686:75"/>vel omnium ordinum conventus:</hi> Let him be cut off, either privately, or by open War, or by the judgement of the Peers of the Realm, or by the aſſembly of States. Who ſays now, that <hi>Calvin</hi> had not a very forward diſciple here in <hi>England?</hi> and I think he hath been pretty well followed too. But if he had lived in this laſt age, and had ſeen what people have done and ſuffered, he would have liked our late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, as well as that of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and adopted our Engliſh Proteſtants of Integrity for his whiteſt Boys, and beſt proficient Schollars.</p>
            <p>By all this it is plain, that <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo far from being the Author and Fountain of theſe Rebel doctrines, that all Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is in their reputation Popery. Would you know how much they of <hi>Rheims</hi> condemned Treaſon and Diſobedience? you may read in <hi>Page</hi> 301. their Notes upon the Teſtament lately Printed: Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects were bound in temporal things to obey the Heathen, being lawful Kings, and to be ſubject to them, even for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; to keep their Temporal Laws, to pay them tribute, to pray for them, and to do all other natural duties. And Dr. <hi>Kelliſon</hi> in his learned Survey, gives a
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:94686:75"/>good reaſon for it: <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Faith is not neceſſarily required to juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, neither is authority loſt by loſs of Faith.</hi> Which was the monſtrous opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Wickliff,</hi> and of the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and hath ſince continued amongſt all the greateſt part of our Reforming Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of Integrity.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> tells us expreſly, <note place="margin">St. Thom lib. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimine Principum cap. <hi>6.</hi> Decret. <hi>2.</hi> Part. Cauſ. <hi>23.</hi> q. <hi>6.</hi> de Epiſcop.</note> 
               <hi>Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus non poteſt à quopiam, privata authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate interfioi:</hi> A Tyrant cannot be killed by any private authority; quite contrary to the rules of <hi>Paraeus</hi> and <hi>Knox, &amp;c.</hi> Nay, the Canon Law it ſelf may give the beſt ſatisfaction, where it doth decree thus, <hi>De Epiſcopis vero &amp; quibuſlibet Clericis, quod nec ſua authoritate, nec authoritate Romani Pontiſicis, arma accipere valeant, probatur.</hi> As to all Biſhops and the Clergy, it is clearly proved, That they can neither by their own, no nor the Popes authority, take up arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay the Canon Laws of <hi>England</hi> do explain it yet more fully, as by the Provincial Conſtitutions in the Council held at <hi>Oxford,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Provinc. Conſtit. Concil. Oxon. <hi>1228.</hi>
               </note> by <hi>Stephen</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> 1228. And <hi>Anno</hi> 8. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. an abſolute Excommunication is decreed againſt all thoſe, <hi>Qui pacem &amp; tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem Domini Regis &amp; Regni perturbant,</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:94686:76"/>who ſhall go about to diſturb the peace and tranquillity of our Lord the King and his Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>But to avoid all queſtions whatſoever, the General Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, That it is an error in Faith, to maintain that Subjects may kill their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, being Tyrants; the words are theſe. <hi>Nuper accepit Sancta Synodus quod non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nullae aſſertiones erroneae dogmaticae ſunt Rei Publicae ſtatum evertere cupientes, <note place="margin">Concil. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanc. Seſs. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> &amp;c. Scil. ut quilibet Tyrannum poteſt &amp; debet licitè &amp; meritoriè occidere, per quem cur que Vaſallum ſuum &amp; Subjectum, etiam per clanculares inſidias, non obſtante quocun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que juramento, nec expectata ſententia &amp; mandato judicis, &amp;c.</hi> And thereupon the Council determined, <hi>Eam eſſe doctrinam erroneam in fide &amp; moribus:</hi> Then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth it, and enacteth, <hi>Quicunque do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinam hanc pernicioſiſſimam pertinaciter aſſerentes, ſunt Haeretici, &amp; tanquam tales juxta Canonum Sanctiones ſunt puniendi.</hi> The holy Synod hath underſtood of late, that ſome erroneous dogmatical Aſſertions have been broached, endeavoring to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Civil State, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To wit, That any Tyrant may lawfully and meritoricuſly he put to death by any of his Vaſſals or
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:94686:76"/>Subjects, even by any ſecret contrivance, notwithſtanding any Oath, or expectation of Sentence, and command from Higher Powers. This doctrine is erroneous in Faith and Manners; and whoſoever ſhall pertinaciouſly aſſert this damnable and moſt pernicious doctrine, are Hereticks, and are to be puniſhed as ſuch, according to the Sanctions of holy Councils.</p>
            <p>All this I am ſure, accords with the doctrines of the moſt ancient Fathers of the Church, as St. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> teſtifieth, who ſetteth down amongſt Hereſies, <note place="margin">St. Irenae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> to think that Kings are given to men caſually, and not by the divine providence, and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God; and his ground was, <hi>quia omnis poteſtas à Deo,</hi> becauſe all pover is of God. And St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith plainly, <note place="margin">St. Ambroſ. contra Auxenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>un.</note> 
               <hi>Lachrymae meae arma-mea, aliter nec de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo nec poſſum reſiſtere.</hi> My tears are my Arms; I neither ought, nor can reſiſt otherwiſe. <hi>Valentinian</hi> the Emperor ſent <hi>Calligonus</hi> his Chamberlain to threaten the ſaid St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and terrifie the ſaid St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> from his opinions, by the name of death, and torments; he anſwered in another tune than our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of Integrity have taken up; <hi>Deus permittat tibi ut impleas quod minaris; ego
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:94686:77"/>patiar quod eſt Epiſcopi, tu facies quod Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donis.</hi> God permit to thee that thou ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill what thou threatneſt; I will ſuffer what belongs to a Biſhop, <note place="margin">Theodorct. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>14</hi>
               </note> and thou wilt do what belongs to an Eunuch. <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> decreed to baniſh <hi>Euſebius</hi> from <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſata,</hi> the people reſiſted, but <hi>Euſebius</hi> appeaſed the ſedition, diſſwaded the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and obeyed the Decree. Theſe were true Chriſtians of Integrity; will you hear yet what St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſayes further in his Sermon <hi>de verbis Domini?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sr.</hi> Aug. in ſerm. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bis Dom. in Matth.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon</hi> did fall into moſt grievous ſins, <hi>Ad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſundum Idololatriae lapſus at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> demerſus,</hi> He was fallen into, and drowned in the depth of Idolatry, and did notoriouſly, and directly contrary to Gods Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to keep and marry ſtrange women of the Gentils; <hi>Non ingrediemini ad illas,</hi> Thou ſhalt not go in unto them: beſides he worſhipt <hi>Moloch</hi> and <hi>Aſtarthes,</hi> the Gods of the <hi>Sidonians;</hi> yet neither Prieſt, nor people did riſe againſt him, to depoſe him; they left it to the proper Judg of Kings, who in his wrath did appoint and raiſe up <hi>Jeroboam</hi> to ruine his Son: If any Rebel of theſe times could ſhew as good a Commiſſion, and ſo immediate a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, he were indeed excuſable. <hi>Julian</hi>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:94686:77"/>proved a perfidious Apoſtate; yet though the Doctors of the Primitive Church, as <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> and others, did ſharply reprove and deteſt his impiety, they never perſwaded, nor taught the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to deprive him.</p>
            <p>He that proclaimed the Prerogative of Kings, <hi>Vos eſtis Dii,</hi> Ye are Gods; he taught the world, that as Gods have <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Imperium,</hi> the chief command, ſo the people are to obey; and are therefore called <hi>Subditi,</hi> Subjects, becauſe of their ſubjection: And there were never any but Gyants heard of to fight againſt the Gods, and yet they periſhed for all their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for that hand muſt needs wither which rudely toucheth Gods annointed. Now he that takes Armes againſt him, doth provoke the King into the field, and when the flame rageth, who can tell where the ſparks will light?</p>
            <p>And yet he that gave Kings that glory, <hi>Vos eſtis Dii,</hi> Ye are Gods, did likewiſe give them this caveat; that for iniquity and impiety, he would <hi>transferre Regna de gente in gentem,</hi> transfer Kingdoms from one Nation to another. He is the Judg of the Princes, and his Audit is dreadfull, and to that alone we muſt leave them.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:94686:78"/>
               <hi>Xiphilin</hi> in the life of Mar. <hi>Antonius</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth us, <note place="margin">Xiphilinus in Vita M. Ant.</note> that <hi>Solus Deus est judex Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipum,</hi> only God is the judg of Princes. <hi>Belloy</hi> yet more plainly, <note place="margin">Belloy in Ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol. par. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Orationibus tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum pugnandum,</hi> We are to fight onely with our Prayers; Armes againſt Princes have no warrant. <hi>Quis est Judex ſi Rex tranſgreditur conditiones Regni? Solus Deus:</hi> Who is Judg if the King tranſgreſſeth the conditions of his Kingdom? onely God. <hi>Navar Cunerus,</hi> and all the Catholick Doctors that ever I have ſeen, <note place="margin">Navar. Cunerus.</note> agree per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly in this ſame ſentence.</p>
            <p>Now if you'l be pleaſed to take the pains to compare theſe Primitive Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and truly Chriſtian Doctrines and Duties, with the opinions and practices of our modern Evangeliſts, and late Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of Integrity, which we have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy deduced, you will quickly find their pedigree, whether they are deſcended from Jeſus Chriſt, or the Cockatrice. And truly it is worth the noting, what an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> they carry about them, how they ſhuffle up and down, and flut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter like ſhot birds, to evade their duty of obedience, their oathes, and natural ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations; and ſometimes ſpeak good and godly ſenſe, but only the better to palliate
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:94686:78"/>their more treaſonable deſigns. As firſt you may ſee <hi>Melancthon</hi> in his Epitome of moral Philoſophy, <note place="margin">Phil. Mel. in. Epit. moral. Philoſ.</note> preach very gravely and wiſely to this purpoſe: <hi>Violare leges civiles ſeu edicta Magiſtratum civilium, eſt peccatum mortale:</hi> It is no leſs than a mortal ſin to violate the Civil Laws, or the edicts and commands of civil Magiſtrates. This is very Catholick and Chriſtian-like; ſo on: <hi>Sciamus conſcientiam fieri ream, ſi non obtemperemus, &amp; conſidera quantum eſt hoc vinculum obedientiae &amp; publicae tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitatis.</hi> We are to know that we bring a guilt upon our conſciences, if we do not obey, and conſider well how great and obliging this bond of obedience is, and of publick tranquillity: all this is very good ſtill, but now comes the Killcow; <hi>Debet autem haec ſententia de Magiſtratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um edictis prudenter intelligi, ſcilicet de iis edictis quae non jubent facere con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum Dei.</hi> But ſaith he, this that I ſay concerning the edicts of Magiſtrates, is to be prudently underſtood of thoſe edicts which require nothing againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of God. Then as I ſaid before, <note place="margin">Id. in lib. de Conſil. Evang.</note> he ſays, that the inſeriour Magiſtrates may cut the throats of the Superiour, and all this for reforming of Religion, and the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:94686:79"/>overthrow of Idolatry. So that if ſome Juſtices of Peace, or petty Conſtables, be pleaſed to judg in their Conſciences that the Prince erreth in his Religion, then are they both to judg, and give Lawes to their Prince.</p>
            <p>Nay <hi>Luther</hi> himſelf likewiſe, when he is in his right wits, preſcribes very well matter of obedience to <hi>Municipal</hi> Lawes, <note place="margin">Luth. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. <hi>3.</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenb.</note> as in his 3. <hi>Tom.</hi> but if you object to him <hi>ne excitetur tumultus, &amp;c.</hi> then he falls into <hi>Melancthous</hi> Gap; <hi>An ideo negliget verbum Dei &amp; peribit Populus?</hi> Shall the Word of God therefore be neglected, and the People periſh?</p>
            <p>Nay examine the Confeſſion of the French Church, and you will find ſome things very well ſaid as to matter of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, but the ſting lies ſtill in the Tail of all that, <note place="margin">Confeſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Prot. Gal. Art. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> as in Art. 39. <hi>Affirmamus parendum eſſe legibus, ſolvenda Tributa, ſubjectionis jugum tolerandum, etiamſi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fideles fuerint Magiſtratus:</hi> We affirm that Lawes are to be obeyed, Tributes to be payed, and the yoke of ſubjection to be born, although the Magiſtrates be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels. Thus far excellent well; but that which follows ſpoils all, with a <hi>dummodo Dei ſunmum imperium integrum maneat;</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:94686:79"/>and as their French edition hath it, <note place="margin">Art. Bearn. 1572.</note> 
               <hi>Le Soverain Empire de Dieu demeurant Touſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jours en ſon entier:</hi> So long as the chief and Soveraign. Empire of God is not vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated. Here is a gallant latitude ſtill for diſobedience and rebellion. Nay this deſrerate <hi>dummodo</hi> is explained in the Articles of <hi>Bearn.</hi> 157<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Dei imperium dicitur manere illibatum, cum Rex extermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata Catholica Religioze ſolam veram &amp; puram extollit:</hi> that is, Gods Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are then ſaid not to be violated, when the King ſhall have rooted out the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion, and advanceth onely the true and pure one; that is as much as to ſay, when their own is eſtabliſht; that is Calviniſm, now called Proteſtantiſm of Integrity. And in caſe the King main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his own Religion againſt them, what then follows? they have rods in piſs for him. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fol.</hi> 349.</note> 
               <hi>Rex a populo poteſt exauthorari per ordinum in Regem authoritatem,</hi> That the King may be dethroned by the States of the Realm, who have an authority over him: and again, <hi>Nec omnes Regni partes commituntur Regi, ſed tantum ſuperior Regni dignitas, cujus tamen, ſuo modo, &amp; certis conditionibus, inferiores Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratus ſunt participes, maxime officiarii
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:94686:80"/>Coronae;</hi> Nor are all the parts of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom committed to the King, but onely the ſupream dignity; and of that too the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Migiſtrates have their ſhare, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Officers of the Crown. Then that which follows, mends the matter; <hi>populi juramento tacita aut expreſſa eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio, ſemper ſe obtemperaturum Regibus, quamdiu juſto imperio rem gererent:</hi> that is, there is alwayes in the peoples oathes either a tacit, or expreſt condition, that they will obey their Kings, ſo long as they command juſt things: which they muſt be judges of too. Thus they will have one evaſion or another ſtill to cozen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Rebellion. Our Oathes muſt onely bind us to obſerve and obey the King ſo long as he ſerves God, which we are likely to be very capable judges of. Nov indeed as to all oathes of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> from his high Cathedral and Conſiſtorian Tribunal gives this Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution; <note place="margin">Calvin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>13</hi> § <hi>21.</hi> Liſtitut.</note> 
               <hi>Quibuſcunque hujus Evangelii lux affulget, &amp;c. ab omnibus laqueis &amp; juramentis abſolvitur:</hi> Whoſoever ſees the ſunſhine of <hi>Geneva</hi> Goſpel, is preſently abſolved and diſcharged of all oathes, and from all ſnares that do enthral the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:94686:80"/>
            <p>It would be but to throw water into the Sea, to ſhew more largely how theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel Doctrines are backt by the generality of thoſe that call themſelves Proteſtants, that Subjects may not onely by Armes defend their Religion, <note place="margin">Dan. l. <hi>6.</hi> Polit. c. <hi>3.</hi> P. Mart. in cap. <hi>11.</hi> Jud. &amp; in loc. com. Althuſ. Polit. c. <hi>35.</hi> p. <hi>137.</hi>
               </note> but offend alſo: yet you may pleaſe to look into <hi>Danſus</hi> in his book of Politicks, and 3. Chapter, and <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> upon the 11 of <hi>Judges,</hi> and in his Common-places, and <hi>Althuſius</hi> in his Politicks, <hi>chap.</hi> 35. and <hi>page.</hi> 37. where he makes three juſt cauſes of War:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Juſtitiae denegatio,</hi> A denial of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice:</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Purae Religionis defenſio,</hi> The defence' of the pure Religion:</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitio rerum ablatarum,</hi> Recovery of goods taken away.</item>
               </list>
The famous Miniſter <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reau,</hi> called <hi>Roſures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sureau, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> Roſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Bellfor. <hi>l. 6. c. 102.</hi>
               </note> who was after im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned at <hi>Paris,</hi> writ a book expreſly to prove, that it was lawful to kill <hi>Charles</hi> the Ninth, and the Queen Mother, if they would not obey the Goſpel, that is <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſm:</hi> and to this <hi>Belforest</hi> is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient witneſs. Nay <hi>Zuinglius</hi> the grand Ringleader of them all, moſt dogmatical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concludes, <hi>Dum flagitioſi loco non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventur, totus populus a Deo punitur,</hi> Whilſt wicked men (meaning Kings and Princes) are not taken away, or remain unpuniſhed,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:94686:81"/>the whole people are puniſhed by God. So as I begun with this Gentleman, I will even make an end with him; for I am truly weary with talking unto theſe naſty dunghils; and ſo I fear I have tired my Readers patience. But my abundant care to have the good people of <hi>England</hi> clearly diſabuſed from that abominable rebellious blood of Presbyters, that vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous crew of Cockatrice Chriſtians, that call themſelves Proteſtants of Integrity, I hope will plead my pardon for all that prolixity.</p>
            <p>And now after my ſo long beating a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the banks of all the branches and ſtreams of this Infernal River, I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as far from finding the head and ſource of it, as I was before I begun; which proves clearly that it is an inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed War-tower: But yet becauſe I am obliged by promiſe, I will boldly give my gueſs, and you ſhall have it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Negatively from <hi>Rome</hi> it cannot be; for its Doctrines, with the opinions and practices of all its Doctors, are as we have ſhewed, quite contrary, and all that is ſaid againſt that Church in this particular, is meer calumny. It cannot be in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Low-Country, Palatine, or Bohemia,</hi>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:94686:81"/>for they had it all from <hi>Geneva.</hi> It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be in <hi>Geneva</hi> neither, for it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived thither out of <hi>Switzerland.</hi> Nor could <hi>Smalcald</hi> be the fountain, for thoſe bitter waters were piſt thither from <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg;</hi> And <hi>Luther</hi> may very well pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to have taken his waterccurſe from the Conduit of <hi>Wicklefiſts</hi> and <hi>Waldenſes;</hi> and they again have borrowed out of the broken Ciſterns of Gods Church, thoſe ancient ſons of diſobedience and Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the declared enemies and caſtaways of Chriſtianity in all ages; I mean the whole gang of old condemned Hereticks, till you come up to the Grandfather of them all <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> who was the faithfull ſcholler, and legitimate ſucceſſor of the Traytor <hi>Judas,</hi> who was undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly the firſt Chriſtian of this crew, that now call themſelves Proteſtants of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity.</p>
            <p>And if you pleaſe to marke it, our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Proteſtants of Integrity that bought, and their Religious brethren the Scots that ſold, playd the very ſame game with our late moſt gracious Soveraign, as that Arch-Traytor <hi>Judas,</hi> with his confederate purchaſers did with our Saviour, the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal King of Glory: that one would ſwear,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:94686:82"/>that reads both Stories, that they had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly copied out their treaſons from his: &amp; ſo like him beſides they will be found in all his lineaments and particular conditions, that all the world may very well conclude him to be their true Apoſtolical Father, and Prototype.</p>
            <p>But yet God forbid that we ſhould here ſet a ſtop to the Princely Pedigree of our pure Proteſtants of Integrity; for the noble ſpirit of Rebellion reignd ſure before Jeſus Chriſt as well as ſince; and good Jewes of Integrity there were, before the kind of Chriſtians. And now me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I ſee the old Phariſees, and our young ones called Proteſtants of Integrity, ſitting very lovingly together in our San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrim, and agreeing perfectly together in all points, as <hi>Buchanan</hi> and his Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces did ſince about the Paſcal Lamb. How religiouſly did thoſe old Jews of Integrity murther the true Prophets of the Lord, that he had graciouſly ſent unto them, and harkened to dreamers of Dreams, and new fangled falſe Prophets of the Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atrice kind, that blew and bolſterd them up in their wickedneſs! Juſt ſo did our late Proteſtants of Integrity murther their pious, reverend and learned Prelates; as
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:94686:82"/>the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> with the Sword, and others with Impriſonments, Exiles, and Starving.</p>
            <p>Did not this Spirit of Integrity poſſeſs <hi>Abſolom,</hi> when he rebelled againſt his King and Father, and ſpoke buttered words to the people? and <hi>Shimei</hi> when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled the Lords anointed? It did ſo ſure, and the one for his rebelling, and the other for his reviling, were perfect Patterns, as well as Predeceſſors, to our Proteſtants of Integrity.</p>
            <p>To paſs by all others (for I ſhould be infinite to enumerate all particulars) let us come to the murmuring and diſobedient <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Wilderneſs, againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> the Civil as well as Spiritual power, eſpecially <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> and you will ſwear, that theſe are lineally deſcended from thoſe: A bleſſed Off-ſpring from moſt precious Parents.</p>
            <p>From hence let us ſtep up to <hi>Nimrod</hi> and his aſſociates, making Fortifications againſt Heaven, and daring God himſelf into the Field, and we ſhall ſee that whole ſtory perfectly modelled out to us by their followers, theſe Proteſtants of Integrity in all the late Wars of Chriſtendom,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:94686:83"/>where Subjects encouraged by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of theſe Captains, and influence of thoſe Doctrines, have dared to take Sword in hand againſt God, and his Anointed, their Sacred Soveraign: And this you will ſay is ſtrange, to fight againſt God for Religion.</p>
            <p>Nay let us paſs the Flood, and we ſhall finde in the very infancy of the world, this Religion of our Proteſtants of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, copied out to us in <hi>Cains</hi> lean Sacrifices; which beſides his diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, argued more his ingratitude: And will not our <hi>Cainists</hi> diſobey God and the King at any time, to ſave charges? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing grieves them more, than what they are to pay to God and the King; and therefore they have inſtituted a Religion that will diſpence with giving to neither: For to the King we are not bound, longer than we pleaſe, to pay any thing; and to give any thing to God, or the poor for his ſake, is Superſtition. Who ſays now, that our Proteſtants of Integrity are not of a very ancient Extract?</p>
            <p>But yet we muſt trace them a little higher; who was it preached and practiſed Diſobedience in Paradiſe, was it not the Serpent? and to whom was this Doctrine
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:94686:83"/>of Rebellion firſt preached? to a woman: which makes all our Presbyterian Tribe ſtill to be tampering with that ſex. And as one ſaid, that the beſt way to raiſe an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my was to preſs the women, for that men would follow: ſo they as the old Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice did with <hi>Eve,</hi> firſt enſnare the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple weomen, and make them to drag their Husbands by the horns after them.</p>
            <p>And upon what pretence does the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent work? that mankind might know Good and Evil forſooth; ſuch ſpecious pretences have our Diabolical Brethren now, to bewitch poor people from their duty and obedience.</p>
            <p>Nay this Serpent too was the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel that ever was, for he would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned God himſelf: What do our Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciferian Crew endeavour leſs every day, making him in their Doctrines guilty both of ſin and folly, and fighting againſt his Images and Vicegerents upon earth? So then I think We have it, this Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice egg was laid in Paradiſe it ſelf, and what greater Petigrce can be than from the high and mighty <hi>Lucifer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now truly to make theſe preſumed deer children of God thus to proceed from their
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:94686:84"/>Father the Devil may be taken for a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs and extremity of paſſion in me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Party, and hate to their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which I proteſt before God I am clear from, (for I have and alwayes had many of my neereſt relations unhappily engaged that way) but only a deteſtation of their impious opinions, and more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious practices, which do cleerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate them to be deriv'd from the Divel, or all the world beſides to be ſo; For the doctrines of the whole Church of Chriſt have alwayes been diametrically oppoſite to theirs; if they then ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in the ſight of God, Chriſtianity it ſelf muſt of neceſſity fall to ground, which God has promiſed never to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer.</p>
            <p>Over and abone all this, I did ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, the derivation of thoſe Doctrines to be from the Devil long before I made this ſtrict ſearch and inquiſition into their extract and petigree: and my reaſon was onely this, becauſe their poſitions did not at all conſiſt with humanity; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man, nor any power humane, could at any time be founder, or undertake to be defender of them.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:94686:84"/>
            <p>We have ſeen ſufficiently already, how much theſe terrible Tenets do contradict both reaſon and Religion, Canon Lawes, and Divine Relveations, the opinions of all Primitive Chriſtians, and the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the whole Church: nay are they not moſt cleerly convinced by Civil and Common Law, nay Philoſophy and Common ſenſe. The Law is plain, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus non alligati ſumus,</hi> we are not tyed to Lawes; who then is capable to judg a King, that is above Lawes? though it is a great part of their goodneſs to obſerve Lawes, as the ſame Emperour declares, <hi>Legibus tamen vivimus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> and again, <hi>dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na vox eſt Majeſtate regnantis legibus alligatum ſe Principem profiteri,</hi> It is a Princes dignation to deſcend to oblige himſelf to Lawes: and the reaſon of all this is, becauſe he is preſumed to be a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Law.</p>
            <p>The Law again is plain, as has been ſhewed already, that no war can be made without the Authority of the Prince, <hi>ſine qua eſt laeſa Majeſtas;</hi> otherwiſe it muſt be treaſon; and this I ſay is a fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Law in every Monarchy: but it is plain our Proteſtants of Integrity would turn the whole world into a Democracy,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:94686:85"/>by leaving the bridle in the peoples hands, which what a pretty beaſt it is when it has aſſembled its many heads and horns to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they beſt know that have felt its Arietations. We in <hi>England</hi> I am ſure have reaſon to put into our Litanies, From a Popular Tyranny, <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay heart St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> once more, the moſt ancient and learned Father of the Chriſtian Church, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>St.</hi> Auguſt. l. <hi>22.</hi> cap. <hi>75.</hi> contra Fauſtum.</note> how contrary to the falſe Principles of theſe Religionaries, he proceeds to back theſe Civil Lawes, with the Law of nature it ſelf. <hi>Ordo naturalis mortalium paci accomodatus hoc poſcit, ut ſuſcipendi belli authoritas at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſilium pones Principem ſit;</hi> The courſe of nature it ſelf accommodated to peace, requireth that the only authority and counſel of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king War ſhould be in the Prince: and he gives a reaſon; for <hi>non eſt poteſtas niſi a Deo vel jubente vel ſinente,</hi> For there is no power but of God, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 76.</note> either command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or permitting: and then he anſwereth the objection of all thoſe, who think they ought by force of Armes to reſiſt their Princes for Religion, and that by the example of the Apoſtles; <hi>Iſti,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>non reſiſtendo interfecti ſunt, ut potiorem eſſe docerent victoriam pro fide veritatis
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:94686:85"/>oscidi:</hi> They were not put to death re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting, that they might teach us, that it is the greateſt victory to be ſlain for the truth. The Philoſophers themſelves may teach the ſame thing to theſe wretched Religionaries.</p>
            <p>The King in the Philoſophers ſence, is, <hi>Anima Corporis, Spiritus vitalis, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put membrorum, vinculum per quod cohae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret Res publica, ſine quo nihil Res publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca ipſa futura, niſi onus &amp; praeda, ſi mens illa imperii detrahatur:</hi> He is the Soul of the Body, the vital Spirit, the Head of the Members, the bond by which the Commonwealth holds together, without whom the Commonwealth it ſelf will be but a burthen to it ſelf, and a prey to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, if this ſoul of the Empire be taken away.</p>
            <p>This was <hi>Senecas</hi> opinion, <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> and a ſound propoſition; for if the Soul offend the Body, the Body cannot puniſh it, without participation of the puniſhment. Neither is it a proper faculty of the Body to judg, but of the Soul and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: ſo much Philoſophy as this, the very Bees underſtand in their little Monarchy, <note place="margin">Virgil Georg.</note> as <hi>Virgil</hi> teſtifieth of them, <hi>Rege incolumi mens omnibus una; Amiſſo rupere fidem;</hi>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:94686:86"/>Whilſt the King is well, all is well and in union; but he being gone, all falls in pieces.</p>
            <p>To conclude, Let us look a litle up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Common Law, which, if any thing, by our own Kings condeſcentions, has prov'd prejudicial to Monarchy; and its Profeſſours moſt of them, the forwardeſt Incendiaries, and the greateſt Knaves in our late troubles; yet that gives the King power and prerogative enough; for it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes him to be the body Politick, which is a dignity Royal annext to the natural body, whereby he is made Lord Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount, and is not ſirnamed as others are, but ſtiled by the name of the Body Politick, declaring his Royal Function, as <hi>Carolus Rex:</hi> And to ſhew the Nature, Quality, Majeſty and Prerogative of that Body, I pray you obſerve the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It cannot hold lands in joint-Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy, nor endure a Partner.</p>
            <list>
               <item>2. It cannot be ſeized to uſes, and ſo limited.</item>
               <item>3. It is not bound to give Livery and ſeizin of Lands, nor tied at all to the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of a natural body.</item>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:94686:86"/>
               <item>4. It is ſuppoſed to be everywhere, ſo cannot be Nonſuited.</item>
               <item>5. It cannot do homage, having no Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour.</item>
               <item>6. That Body is ſo precious, that the very imagination onely to compaſs his death, is Treaſon, though there be no at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt at all.</item>
               <item>7. That Body veſted in a blood, ought to deſcend; and though the natural Body be attainted of Felony or Treaſon before, yet by the acceſs of this Body Politick, he is to take his Inheritance; for that dignity alwayes purgeth the blood, as it did in <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, and <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth; for this Body was founded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Letters Patents, not onely by the Civil and Common Lawes, but thoſe of Nature, and of Nations, and for the defence of the people: And if Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal cauſes cannot diſable the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, much leſs can they diſenable his Title, when it is deſcended. For the Crown of <hi>England</hi> is Independent; his <hi>jura Regalia</hi> are holden of no Lord but the Lord of Heaven: ſo it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eſcheat to any, being holden of none.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:94686:87"/>
            <p>From this ſacred Fountain is all autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and honour derived: Judges are created by it, and have their Commiſſion from the King, to judge both Criminal and Civil Cauſes. The Conſtables and Marſhals Court for Armes and Honour; the Chancery for equity, the Exchequer for the Revenues of the Crown. The King then alone appointing Judges, who is I would fain know to judg him? I very well underſtand what a Parliament means, which at it is ever ſummoned by the King, ſo their Acts muſt be judged, allowed, and confirmed by the King, before they can be Lawes; in the Senate reſts <hi>Conſilium,</hi> but in the King is the power and majeſty of the Realm; and he is to judg and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low or diſallow what he pleaſeth. In fine as the Spaniard very wittily and truly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves <hi>Ni Rey Traydor, ni Papa deſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgado,</hi> No King can be a Traytor, nor Pope excommunicated. There can be no Judg above the King, nor Court of Law higher than the Kings Bench, where I ſhall now be bold to leave theſe Proteſtants of Integrity to anſwer Guilty, or Not guilty, for their future deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits;
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:94686:87"/>and let every one joyn with me, to ſay</p>
            <closer>God ſave the King, and deliver him from ſuch Treacherous Friends, undermining Adverſaries and Hypocritical Religionaries as are our Pretended <hi>Proteſtants of Integrity.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
